좋습니다.
Hello, everyone, 그리고 welcome to 강의 3 of
CME 295.
오늘은 a 매우 exciting day, 왜냐하면 we're입니다.
~할 예정입니다 to 마지막으로 소개하다 대규모 언어모델.
하지만 I guess 전에 we go into that I'm 그냥.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다, traditionally,
with some announcements.
그래서 some of you 원했습니다 to have the 슬라이드 전에
the 수업.
참고로, in 경우 you.
원하다 to 사용하다 the 슬라이드 to do some
annotations,.
they're on the 웹사이트 right 이제.
원문 의미: 그래서 feel free to get them.
그리고 with Shervin, we'll try to, 그냥 on a
regular basis,.
원문 의미: every Thursday evening, have them
publish on the 웹사이트.
원문 의미: 그래서 that you can download them 그리고
annotate.
좋습니다.
그럼 이제 시작하겠습니다.
그리고 as usual, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 요약하다 지난
week's episodes.
기억하신다면, 강의 1 그리고 강의 2.
원문 의미: were all about introducing the 개념
of self-attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 linking them to the construct
of the 트랜스포머.
그리고 what we did 지난 강의 was 보다 at all the
types of 모델들.
원문 의미: that are out there 그리고 how they
were all.
원문 의미: based on the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: 그래서 there are 셋 categories, 셋 main
categories of 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 하나 that we saw was
encoder-decoder 모델,.
원문 의미: which 기본적으로 relies on the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: It has the encoder of the 트랜스포머,.
원문 의미: the decoder of the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: 그리고 typically, the tasks there are
input text.
원문 의미: 그래서 text in, text out.
원문 의미: 그래서 we saw that 하나 예시 was T5 그리고
all the variations.
The 둘째 type of 모델 is where.
원문 의미: we remove the decoder from the
트랜스포머.
그리고 we obtain an encoder-only 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 we went deeper into BERT, which
is.
원문 의미: the typical encoder-only 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess, we also saw that what.
원문 의미: BERT has is this nice property that
it's encoded.
원문 의미: embeddings are 매우 meaningful 그리고
expressive of the inputs.
그리고 그래서 we saw the 예시 of classification,.
원문 의미: sentiment extraction.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we did was, in
particular,.
원문 의미: 가지다 into consideration the encoded
embedding.
원문 의미: of the CLS 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess in real life, BERT is
used to encode documents.
원문 의미: to encode sentences.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 later in the 수업.
원문 의미: how these 모델들 are useful.
그리고 그다음 지난 하지만 not least, we have.
원문 의미: the 셋째 category of 모델들, which is
decoder only.
원문 의미: 그래서 we only keep the decoder 부분 of
the 트랜스포머.
그리고 그래서 here, we also do a little bit of a
modification.
원문 의미: 그래서 we remove the cross-attention
왜냐하면 we.
don't 필요하다 it anymore.
원문 의미: We don't have an encoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 these kinds of 모델들 are text in,
text out.
그리고 그래서 GPT is a 매우 good 예시 of such 모델들.
원문 의미: 그리고 실제로, most 모델들 these days,
they're decoder-only.
원문 의미: 그래서 these are the 셋 main kinds.
원문 의미: of 모델들 that you can 보다 out there.
원문 의미: 그래서 far 그래서 good for everyone?
좋습니다.
그래서 with that, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to 소개하다 the
term LLM.
원문 의미: 그래서 LLM stands for 대규모 언어모델.
그래서 what is a 대규모 언어모델?
그래서 첫째 of all, a 대규모 언어모델.
is a 언어모델.
그래서 a 언어모델 is a 모델 that assigns 확률.
to 시퀀스들 of 토큰들.
그래서 in this 경우, our 모델 always.
predicts the 확률 of the 다음 토큰.
그래서 it's, in that sense, a 언어모델.
하지만 also, a 대규모 언어모델 is large.
그래서 why is it large?
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that these 모델들,.
원문 의미: they are 실제로 scaled up in terms of
size.
그래서 첫째 of all in terms of 모델 size.
그래서 these days, it's not uncommon to 보다
모델들.
on the order of hundreds of billions of
파라미터들.
원문 의미: 하지만 typically, when we say LLM we.
원문 의미: say at least on the order of a
billion.
원문 의미: These 모델들, they've also been 학습된 on
a huge amount of 데이터.
원문 의미: 그리고 hereby amount of 데이터, we
quantify that.
원문 의미: by the 번호 of 토큰들 that they were
pre-학습된 with.
그리고 이것은 on the order of magnitude입니다.
of hundreds of billions of 토큰들.
or even trillions of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 the biggest ones are
like on the tens of trillions.
of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 huge 학습 sets.
그리고 they're also large 왜냐하면 they 필요하다 a
lot of 컴퓨트.
그래서 typically you 필요하다 a bunch of GPU들 to
만들다 them work.
원문 의미: Although these days there's been a
lot of optimizations.
원문 의미: to have them work on consumer based
GPU들.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that later on.
원문 의미: 하지만 in LLM is large according to
these categories.
그래서 another thing that I 원하다 to 포인트 out.
원문 의미: is that all these terminologies,
they're relatively new.
그래서 I 기억하다 in 2018, '19, there was.
원문 의미: no real definition of an LLM.
I 생각하다 no 하나 실제로 talked about LLMs.
원문 의미: In the beginning, maybe people
talked about LLMs.
원문 의미: They included BERT.
하지만 Bert is an encoder-only 모델.
원문 의미: that does not produce text.
원문 의미: 그래서 with the current definition of
an LLM,.
원문 의미: which right 이제 has been pretty well
established,.
원문 의미: BERT would not be an LLM 왜냐하면 it
doesn't produce text.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, we only consider 언어모델.
원문 의미: that do text to text, that are 매우
large in size, in terms.
of amount of 데이터 that have been 학습된 on 그리고
in terms.
of 컴퓨트.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 as we saw 전에, these 모델들 are
decoder-only.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, what we do is we remove
the encoder,.
원문 의미: we only keep the masked self-
attention,.
원문 의미: the feedforward 신경망, 그리고 그다음 the
addition.
그리고 정규화.
원문 의미: 그래서 we only keep this.
그리고 이것은 the backbone of LLMs.입니다.
그리고 그래서 I mentioned GPT is kind of a good
예시.
하지만 it's not 그냥 that.
원문 의미: You have plenty of other 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you may have heard of LLaMA
from Meta, Gemma.
원문 의미: from Google, DeepSeek, Mistral,
Qwen, 그리고 그래서 on.
원문 의미: The list is long.
원문 의미: I would say roughly—
원문 의미: I mean, more than 90% of modern day
LLMs,.
원문 의미: they're all decoder-only.
그래서 I 생각하다 that's something to keep in
mind.
좋습니다.
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 you how LLMs are made of.
원문 의미: 하지만 there is something else that
people these days also.
소개하다 to these 모델들.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in a bit.
원문 의미: 그래서 I mentioned that these 모델들 are.
원문 의미: huge in size, again, typically
hundreds of billions.
of 파라미터들.
그래서 it takes a lot of 컴퓨트 to 그냥 컴퓨트 하나
추론,.
or also to 학습하다 these 모델들.
원문 의미: 하지만 you may wonder, do you 정말.
필요하다 to have all these 파라미터들 be.
원문 의미: activated during a forward pass, to
만들다 a 간단한 prediction?
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to have a little
metaphor.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you enter in a
room.
원문 의미: 그리고 in the room, there is a
mathematician, a physicist,.
a chemist 그리고 a historian.
원문 의미: 그래서 you come in this 수업, there's.
원문 의미: a bunch of people who are expert in
what they do.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have a 문제, you have a math
문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 a 문제 I have for you is, who
would you ask your 문제?
원문 의미: Would you ask the mathematician?
원문 의미: Would you ask the chemist?
원문 의미: Would you ask everyone?
원문 의미: Well, right 이제, we ask everyone.
We ask all 파라미터들 of the 모델.
원문 의미: to be involved in the computation
of the generation.
그리고 그래서 the 아이디어 here is given an input,.
원문 의미: maybe it's not necessary to ask
everyone.
원문 의미: to be involved in the computation.
아이디어는 let's 실제로 그냥 have a subset of the
모델입니다.
be involved in the computation of the 다음
토큰.
그래서 I'm 그냥 introducing this 아이디어 of
experts.
그래서 let's suppose we're introducing.
원문 의미: the following notation.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have n
experts.
그래서 생각하다 of it as your mathematician, your
chemist,.
원문 의미: historian, whatever.
원문 의미: 그래서 these are your experts.
그리고 the 아이디어 is given an input x, you're
~할 예정입니다 to ask yourself.
원문 의미: who should be involved in the
generation of the outputs.
원문 의미: 그래서 you're ~할 예정입니다 to have, let's
say, another network.
Where we're ~할 예정입니다 to call it G like
gates,.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's also sometimes called
router.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have some
gates that tells us.
원문 의미: which experts should be involved in
the 추론.
원문 의미: 그래서 if we have that, 그래서 let's
suppose here,.
the gate tells us OK, 그래서 실제로, expert 번호
2.
is well suited to 답 your 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, the 아이디어 is that the
input is 그냥.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to flow into that expert,
하지만 not the other experts.
원문 의미: 그래서 this has a name.
원문 의미: It's called mixture of experts.
그래서 it's denoted MoE.
원문 의미: Everyone talks about MoE.
원문 의미: 그래서 these are a mixture of experts.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 the formula that you will
보다 a lot is this 하나.
원문 의미: 그래서 the output y, which is denoted
y hat.
원문 의미: is the sum of the expert output
weighted by some quantity, which.
원문 의미: is the output of the gate, which
tells you.
원문 의미: how 중요한 the output of each expert
is.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
그래서 the 문제 is, how do you 학습하다 G?
How do you 학습하다 E. 그래서 typically,.
원문 의미: you 학습하다 them jointly.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that maybe in a
little later.
하지만 you can 생각하다 of it as 그냥 학습 as usual.
원문 의미: You do your forward pass, you 컴퓨트
the loss.
원문 의미: 그리고 you backprop.
그리고 it's 실제로 an interesting 문제.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 there is some challenges that
come with 학습 MoEs.
that we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 in a 둘째.
원문 의미: Yeah.
문제 is, what are these E's.
원문 의미: What is the architecture of these
E's?
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose right 이제 that
there's 그냥 some network.
원문 의미: We're not specifying them for 이제,.
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 this in a 둘째.
원문 의미: Let's suppose for 이제, it's some
network.
좋습니다.
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 I told you that what if we
don't activate everyone.
원문 의미: What if we activate a subset?
원문 의미: 하지만 this formula, 실제로, I guess,.
원문 의미: assumes that we're 실제로 considering
all expert outputs.
그래서 I 그냥 원하다 to distinguish 둘 kinds of
MoEs.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's 하나 kind that is called
a dense MoE.
원문 의미: 그래서 a dense MoE 실제로 does not have.
원문 의미: any constraints on the 번호 of
experts that are involved.
원문 의미: 그래서 these 가중치, they can be anywhere
between 0 그리고 1.
그래서 생각하다 of them as a 확률분포.
하지만 it's 그냥 ~할 예정입니다 to put more 가중치
towards some experts.
원문 의미: compared to others.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to the 예시 that I had, 그래서
let's suppose.
I have a math 문제.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to ask the
mathematician,.
원문 의미: the chemist, the historian.
그래서 I'm probably ~할 예정입니다 to add a higher
가중치.
원문 의미: to what the mathematician says
compared.
원문 의미: to let's say, the historian.
이것은 the 아이디어.입니다.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the interesting thing is.
원문 의미: when we constrain the 번호 of
experts.
원문 의미: that are activated, 왜냐하면 here,.
원문 의미: as we mentioned previously, what
we're.
원문 의미: interested in is to not involve
everyone.
is to 만들다 some savings in the amount of
컴퓨트 that we do.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a 둘째 kind of MoE that's
called the sparse MoE.
원문 의미: 그리고 what it does is it only selects
the quote unquote,.
원문 의미: "top k" experts.
그래서 k can be equal to 1.
그래서 하나 expert or even 둘.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's a hyperparameter that you
choose.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 here, the expression of the
output.
원문 의미: becomes the sum over all the chosen
experts.
of a G of x times E of x.
원문 의미: 그래서 far, 그래서 good?
좋습니다.
그리고 of course, there's a lot more to it.
원문 의미: 그래서 in 경우 you are interested in
learning more,.
원문 의미: feel free to go into the resources
that.
원문 의미: are at the bottom of the 슬라이드.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 thing that I will say is
that we.
원문 의미: have a unit of measure of the
amount of 컴퓨트.
원문 의미: that these 모델들 produce for each
pass.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 보다 the term FLOPS.
원문 의미: 그래서 have you seen the term FLOPS
out there?
No, not 정말.
원문 의미: 그래서 it stands for floating-point
operations.
원문 의미: 그래서 it quantifies how many
생각하다 of it as additions, multiplications.
원문 의미: are involved in a forward pass
let's say.
원문 의미: 그리고 it 기본적으로 quantifies how 컴퓨트
heavy is your task.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, what we say is when.
원문 의미: we go through a sparse MoE as
opposed to a dense Moe,.
원문 의미: we have a lower amount of FLOPS.
원문 의미: 이것은 the unit of measure that you
will 보다.입니다.
원문 의미: 하지만 back to your 문제, 그래서 what are
these experts?
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, I mean, 10 minutes ago, we
said that LLMs,.
원문 의미: they are decoder-only 모델들.
그래서 I have a 문제 for you.
원문 의미: Let's suppose we 원했습니다 to put some
MoEs in our LLM.
원문 의미: Where would we put it?
원문 의미: 그래서 here, I guess, we have 셋
choices.
원문 의미: We have the masked self-attention
layer.
원문 의미: We have the feedforward 신경망.
그리고 그다음 we have this 정규화.
원문 의미: 그래서 문제 for you, I guess, where
would you put this?
I guess, where do you 생각하다 is—
원문 의미: I guess, the most complex parts of
the network.
원문 의미: Where is there a lot of operations?
원문 의미: Feedforward?
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 답.
그래서 it's indeed the feedforward 신경망.
원문 의미: 그리고 the reason for that is I 생각하다
Shervin mentioned it,.
I 생각하다, in 강의 1.
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, the feedforward 신경망.
원문 의미: is a network such that you have the
input, which.
원문 의미: is your D-dimensional input 벡터.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have this being
projected into, let's say,.
원문 의미: a DFF dimensional space.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 it goes back to the
D-dimensional, I guess, space.
원문 의미: 그래서 the DFF is typically larger
than your 차원 of, I guess,.
원문 의미: the inputs.
원문 의미: When I say input, it's here.
그래서 it's typically larger.
원문 의미: 그래서 the amount of 파라미터들 that you.
원문 의미: have in that feedforward 신경망.
원문 의미: is something on the order of
magnitude of D 모델 times.
원문 의미: DFF times 2 plus some bias.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 your order of magnitude.
원문 의미: 그리고 the attention layer, if you
기억하다,.
it's 기본적으로 composed of the projection
행렬들,.
원문 의미: what is the 차원 of the projection
행렬들.
그래서 it's D 모델 times the 차원.
of keys to 차원 of queries the 차원 of values.
원문 의미: 그리고 this 차원 is typically much
lower.
그래서 생각하다 of it over 100.
그래서 your D 모델 is typically O over 100, O
over 1,000.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the projection here, the
DFF is O over 1,000,.
O over 10,000.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 is everyone 이제 convinced that
this.
원문 의미: is a good way, good place to put
the mixture of experts?
원문 의미: Yeah?
좋습니다.
이것은 실제로 how it's done.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 in modern day LLMs, this 아이디어
of not involving everyone.
in the computation of the 다음 토큰 예측.
원문 의미: is such that you would put the
mixture of experts.
where the fn is 그냥 기본적으로 here.
원문 의미: 그리고 typically you would have a
sparse mixture of experts.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to your 문제, 그래서 these
experts.
원문 의미: are 실제로 feedforward 신경망.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have several networks
that you can 학습하다,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you would only activate 하나.
그래서 typically, k would be equal to 1.
It can be also equal to 2 하지만 it would
only be a subset.
그래서 that's my 포인트.
원문 의미: 그리고 this routing would be done at
the 토큰 level.
기억하신다면, the decoder, it 기본적으로.
원문 의미: takes something as inputs.
그래서 a bunch of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, what I'm saying is that
each 토큰.
원문 의미: will be processed by an expert that
may be.
원문 의미: 다른 from the other 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 the router here would 가지다 the
representation of the 토큰.
원문 의미: as input 그리고 figure out which
expert should be best.
원문 의미: for this 토큰 to flow towards.
원문 의미: Does this 아이디어 만들다 sense?
원문 의미: 그래서 I have a little illustration
later.
원문 의미: on that hopefully will help.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 back to your 문제 about how
you 학습하다 this 모델.
원문 의미: Do you 학습하다 the router separately?
원문 의미: Do you 학습하다 the experts separately?
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 challenge that people have.
원문 의미: is when they 학습하다 these MoE-based
모델들, to 만들다 sure.
원문 의미: that all experts are, I guess,
having a 가중치, are being used.
왜냐하면 it's 매우 possible that you 학습하다 your
모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 that somehow only, I don't 알다,.
원문 의미: 하나 or 둘 experts always get
activated.
원문 의미: 그리고 the other 하나, they always are
inactive.
원문 의미: They are never involved in the
computation.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 문제 is called routing
collapse.
원문 의미: 그래서 why is it called routing
collapse?
원문 의미: It's 왜냐하면 the router always
chooses.
원문 의미: some experts, 하지만 not others.
이것은 a challenge.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 the way people try to mitigate.
원문 의미: this challenge is by changing the
손실함수.
원문 의미: 그리고 adding it some extra term,
which is written here.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's 기본적으로 some hyperparameter
alpha times.
원문 의미: the 번호 of experts times the sum of
quantities.
원문 의미: that depend on whether or not 토큰들.
원문 의미: went to a certain expert's eye, 그리고
그다음 summed.
원문 의미: over all experts.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's not super 중요한 that you
completely understand.
원문 의미: exactly how that formula works.
원문 의미: The only thing that I 생각하다 you
should 가지다 away from this 슬라이드.
원문 의미: is that this extra loss allows
these quantities to converge.
원문 의미: more towards uniform distributions.
원문 의미: 그래서 what are these quantities, 그냥
as a reminder.
그래서 f of I is the fraction of 토큰들.
that are routed to expert I. 그리고 P of I.
원문 의미: is the average routing 확률 for
expert I.
원문 의미: 그래서 when I say that all experts
should be used the 같은, what.
I'm saying is I 원하다 this 확률 to be.
원문 의미: kind of uniform across experts.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, I guess, when.
원문 의미: do you 컴퓨트 these quantities?
그래서 yeah, you can 생각하다 of it as a regular
학습 process.
원문 의미: You do some mini batch, you go
through the 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 컴퓨트 all these
quantities.
그리고 그다음 what you do is you do your 역전파.
원문 의미: based on that.
그리고 I guess what I 원하다 you to 기억하다.
원문 의미: is that this incentivizes the 확률,.
원문 의미: I guess, the choice of the writer.
원문 의미: to be more uniform across experts,.
원문 의미: which is something that mitigates
this routing collapse.
원문 의미: phenomenon.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, can we 사용하다 Dropout?
원문 의미: Of course.
원문 의미: You can always bundle that with
some other techniques.
원문 의미: 그래서 people have 그냥 kind of found
this to be 매우 helpful.
원문 의미: 그래서 speaking of other techniques,
there.
원문 의미: is something that I've not talked
about,.
원문 의미: which is 매우 similar to the Dropout
아이디어.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's called noisy gating.
원문 의미: Noisy gating is 기본적으로 you have your
predictions.
원문 의미: from the gates, 하지만 그다음 you add
some noise to it.
그래서 기본적으로, it's by pure chance,.
원문 의미: it 그냥 allows other experts to be
involved in the computation.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's also some other technique.
원문 의미: There's a bunch of techniques.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, Dropout is indeed quite
useful for things.
원문 의미: like overfitting.
그리고 the 아이디어 can be reused in 다른 settings.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, how can you—
원문 의미: 그래서 do you mean differentiable?
원문 의미: 그래서 here, I guess, how do you 가지다
the derivative.
원문 의미: Is that your 문제?
원문 의미: How is the derivative— can you 설명하다
a bit more.
원문 의미: what your concern is?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess, to this 문제, 그래서 the
average routing 확률.
원문 의미: 그래서 that 하나 is a function of the
gate output.
그것은 하나.입니다.
PI.
그래서 I guess, your 문제 is for FI.
For FI, OK.
I don't have a good 답 on top of my head,.
원문 의미: 하지만 I 생각하다 people have some
techniques.
원문 의미: 그리고 these days, you 그냥 don't even
have to do this by hand.
원문 의미: You have the built in thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 maybe I can follow up with you
for FI.
하지만 for P of I, do you 보다 that this 하나 is
quite clean.
원문 의미: It's 그냥 the average of the
probabilities from the gates.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 기본적으로 the 확률—
원문 의미: the output 확률 from the gate,.
원문 의미: you can 생각하다 of it as 그냥 the 벡터
being projected.
원문 의미: on a space of n, where n
corresponds.
to your 번호 of experts.
그리고 그다음 it's gone through softmax.
그래서 your output is 기본적으로 summing up to 하나.
원문 의미: 그리고 each of these 차원들, they.
원문 의미: represent the value corresponding.
원문 의미: to what expert I would be, I guess,
used for.
원문 의미: For instance, the 첫째 차원 would be
for expert 1,.
둘째 차원 would be for expert 2, 그리고 그래서 on.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 그냥 가지다 the average of this,
그리고 this 하나,.
원문 의미: you can express it from all the
파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 you should be fine with
that 하나.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is if we increase the 번호 of
MoEs,.
does it increase the 번호 of 모델 파라미터들?
그래서 it's a great 문제.
그래서 it's 실제로 하나 of the ideas behind MoE-
based 모델들,.
원문 의미: which is that you can scale the 모델
without having.
원문 의미: to incur the cost of having
significantly more 컴퓨트.
at 추론 time.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can increase— 그래서 people
say capacity.
원문 의미: Can increase the capacity of your
모델,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you will still keep some, I
guess, like controlled amount.
of active 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그리고 active 파라미터들 are the 파라미터들
that.
원문 의미: are used for a forward pass.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, people 그냥 사용하다 that.
그래서 yeah, it would 그냥 increase the 번호 of
파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why you 보다 some MoE-
based 모델들 that.
원문 의미: are even bigger than the ones that
we.
원문 의미: had on the order of hundreds of
billions.
원문 의미: We even have on the order of
trillions of 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance here, 하나 reading I
recommend.
is switch 트랜스포머, which scaled up to 하나
포인트.
원문 의미: something trillion 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, it's definitely more.
원문 의미: 하지만 that being said, 그래서 if you
read the paper,.
원문 의미: you will also 보다 that these 모델들,
there.
원문 의미: are more what they call sample
efficient.
원문 의미: 그래서 they 가지다 less time to be as
good as what.
원문 의미: the 모델 would have been with a lower
번호 of 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you draw the 학습 curve.
as a function of the 학습 time,.
원문 의미: you 보다 that these 모델들 are typically
more sample efficient.
원문 의미: Sorry.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah, exactly.
원문 의미: Everything here is a trade off.
원문 의미: Yeah.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, each attention head.
원문 의미: will have a 번호 of experts.
그래서 it's 실제로 regardless of the attention
heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 the attention heads, you can
생각하다 of them.
원문 의미: as being independent, something
else.
그리고 the 번호 of experts is independent of
that.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Right.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: The 문제 is whether every block will
have a 번호.
원문 의미: The 답 is yes.
원문 의미: 그리고 typically those 가중치 are not
shared.
그래서 typically, you— 그래서 실제로, we're ~할
예정입니다 to 보다 an 예시.
원문 의미: It can 매우 well be that layer 1,.
원문 의미: there is the expert 번호 at all.
원문 의미: 셋 that was chosen, 하지만 layer 2,
there is expert 번호 1,.
그리고, you 알다, it's all free.
It's trainable.
그래서 the 문제 is we will decide.
원문 의미: where the expert will go to.
원문 의미: 그래서 all of that is decided by the
gates, which is this quantity.
원문 의미: Everything is decided by the
gates,.
원문 의미: which has trainable 가중치.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of this as 그냥 some
projection from the input.
원문 의미: x to an n dimensional space, where.
n is the 번호 of experts.
그래서 the 문제 is, at what 포인트 during the 추론.
is it decided?
그래서 let's suppose we're at 추론 time.
원문 의미: 저는 walk you through how it works.할
것입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have your x.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have this attention 메커니즘.
원문 의미: 그래서 it interacts with all 토큰들 from
the past given that.
원문 의미: its decoder-only.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's like the mask.
원문 의미: It goes here.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the beginning of the
feedforward 신경망.
원문 의미: block, the 토큰 is, of course,
contextual.
원문 의미: 그래서 it has the information from
these other 토큰들.
왜냐하면 it's attended.
원문 의미: 그리고 what it does is it goes here.
그래서 x 첫째 goes into G. G computes this 확률.
원문 의미: 분포 over all experts.
원문 의미: 그리고 given here that we are in a
sparse MoE setting,.
원문 의미: we will only choose the top k.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose the top 하나, 그냥
the highest 확률.
그리고 we 알다 which experts this 하나 will be.
그리고 그래서 as a 결과 of that, you will only.
원문 의미: 컴퓨트 the output value of the expert.
원문 의미: that the input was chosen.
원문 의미: 그래서 can you elaborate on that 실제로?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: At what 포인트 exactly?
원문 의미: 그래서 it's 후에 the self-attention
layer.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we have 다른
classification.
원문 의미: for 다른 heads?
No.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's only 하나 router.
그래서 I 생각하다 I understand your 문제.
그래서 your 문제 is, what do you do.
원문 의미: given that you have 다른 attention
computations ~할 예정입니다 on.
원문 의미: in parallel with the heads?
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, the attention layer.
원문 의미: has these 다른 heads.
하지만 at the end of it, what it does.
원문 의미: is it concatenates all the results
from each of these heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 projects it once again in
the D 모델 space.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we have 다른 Gs?
원문 의미: 그래서 the only thing I can tell you
is that the G is 그냥.
원문 의미: layer specific.
원문 의미: It's layer specific.
It's trainable.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 ~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 how to
process all these inputs.
원문 의미: 그래서 the G, the only thing I can
tell you for your 문제.
is ~할 예정입니다 to be layer specific.
그래서 the G is ~할 예정입니다 to be 하나 G for let's
say.
원문 의미: the 첫째 layer, another G for the 둘째
layer, 그리고 그래서 on.
그리고 that 하나 is ~할 예정입니다 to be 학습된.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Looking at the time.
원문 의미: Do we have any other 문제들 here?
We're good.
원문 의미: Perfect.
그래서 이제 I 그냥 원했습니다 to 보여주다 you a cool
thing.
원문 의미: that I believe the Mistral team
was.
원문 의미: showing in 하나 of their papers.
원문 의미: 그래서 what they're showing here was
for a given piece of text,.
원문 의미: to 보여주다 in which experts each 토큰
was rooted.
그래서 as we noted 전에, 그래서 experts.
원문 의미: are 다른 from 하나 layer to another.
그래서 I believe here, for layer 0, 그래서 it's.
원문 의미: like for 하나 given layer.
그리고 we do 보다 that roughly, these 토큰들,.
원문 의미: I guess, they leverage like a
uniform amount.
원문 의미: of experts, more or less.
원문 의미: What you would not 원하다 to 보다 is.
원문 의미: to have every 토큰 be the 같은 color.
하지만 luckily it is not.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, 그래서 that's 하나 cool way of
그냥 representing.
원문 의미: how the routing is done is to 그냥
have your input text.
원문 의미: 그리고 그냥 represent where each 토큰— in
which experts.
원문 의미: each 토큰 went.
좋습니다.
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we 그냥 saw was 하나 way that
modern day LLMs changed.
원문 의미: their architecture to incorporate
the fact that we may.
원문 의미: 원하다 to scale the 모델, 하지만 not
increase the computation.
원문 의미: complexity for 하나 forward pass.
원문 의미: 그리고 we saw that with MoEs.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 보다 a lot of MoE-based
LLMs out there.
원문 의미: 그리고 이제 what we will do is knowing
that we have an LLM,.
우리는 focus on—할 것입니다.
원문 의미: don't worry.
원문 의미: 우리는 focus on how a response is
being generated.할 것입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 기억하다, when I told you that
these modern day LLMs, what.
원문 의미: they do is they 가지다 some text in
그리고 they have some text out.
그래서 it's typically these task of 다음 토큰 예측.
그래서 you have a 토큰 in.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say, beginning of
sentence,.
원문 의미: you go through your LLM 그리고 it 그냥.
원문 의미: generates the 다음 word or the 다음 토큰.
그래서 A, 그리고 그다음 you 가지다 A, 그리고 그다음 it goes
to teddy.
그리고 그다음 teddy bear is, et cetera, et
cetera.
원문 의미: 하지만 그래서 far, we have never 정말 dug.
원문 의미: into exactly how we chose the 다음
토큰.
그래서 what we're ~할 예정입니다 to do right 이제.
is to 보다 exactly how we're generating the
다음 토큰.
그래서 as you 알다, here, our LLM is 그냥.
원문 의미: a decoder-only architecture.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, what you have is a
decoder with your inputs here,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 your output there.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose for a 둘째 that
everything that's.
원문 의미: happening in the middle.
그리고 we're 그냥 obtaining output
probabilities.
원문 의미: that are ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a little
bit like this.
그래서 given a 토큰 or some 시퀀스 of 토큰들 as
inputs,.
원문 의미: you have an output 확률분포.
원문 의미: that represents what the 모델 thinks
is the likelihood.
원문 의미: that there will be a 다음 토큰, let's
say,.
그것은 equal to A, to airplane, to fluffy, et
cetera.입니다.
원문 의미: 이것은 what you have.입니다.
그래서 이제 my 문제 to you is, if we told you.
we have some 시퀀스 as inputs 그리고 we 원하다.
to choose the 다음 토큰, 그리고 if I told you
that our 모델 is.
giving out 실제로 a 확률분포,.
원문 의미: I guess, how would you choose the
다음 토큰 based on this?
원문 의미: Sorry.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: The 토큰 with maximum 확률.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그래서 yes, the 첫째 아이디어.
Let's 그냥 가지다 the 토큰 with highest 확률.
그래서 it's a 매우 natural approach.
원문 의미: 하지만 I'm not sure if you've been
using things.
원문 의미: like ChatGPT or Gemini.
원문 의미: Every time you ask something, it
always.
원문 의미: responds something that is slightly
다른.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you always choose the 토큰.
원문 의미: with the highest 확률, given that the
computation here,.
우리는 보다 is all deterministic.할 것입니다.
원문 의미: What that means is you're always ~할
예정입니다.
원문 의미: to generate the 같은 thing regardless
of,.
원문 의미: I guess, with the 같은 input.
그래서 that's 하나 limitation.
그래서 it's not 매우 diverse.
원문 의미: The 둘째 문제 is if you choose the
highest 확률.
원문 의미: 토큰 on, I guess, iterative basis,
your locally optimal,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you're not necessarily globally
optimal.
원문 의미: 그래서 what does that mean?
그래서 I guess, if you 생각하다 about it,.
원문 의미: our objective is for us to produce
a 시퀀스, an output.
시퀀스 of 토큰들 that is, I guess, of a high 확률.
원문 의미: 하지만 the 문제 is, if you always choose
the highest.
원문 의미: 확률 토큰, you will not necessarily
obtain the highest.
확률 시퀀스.
원문 의미: Are you convinced of this
statement, by the way?
그래서 let me 주다 you an 예시.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have the 다음
토큰 where 하나 토큰 is.
0.8, the other 하나 is 0.7.
그리고 그다음 you choose to go with the 0.8.
No, 실제로, it's not 0.7 왜냐하면 it has to sum
to 1.
그래서 let's say 0.2.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose if you go ahead
with the 시퀀스 that.
원문 의미: starts with the 0.8, let's suppose.
원문 의미: all other 토큰 probabilities are 매우
low.
기본적으로, you will have an 출력 시퀀스.
원문 의미: that will have a lower 확률 than
let's.
원문 의미: say, the other path, which would,
let's suppose,.
원문 의미: have higher 확률 predictions in the
later steps.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 this in a 둘째.
하지만 this is the 아이디어.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you choose the highest
predicted 확률,.
it's a good 첫째 아이디어.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's locally optimal, 하지만 not
necessarily globally.
원문 의미: optimal.
그리고 이것은 the reason why we have입니다.
원문 의미: a 둘째 method that is about keeping
track.
원문 의미: of the k most probable path.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if you've heard of
beam search.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what beam search does.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, k, is sometimes called
the beam size or the beam width.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you hear these terms, these.
원문 의미: are 그냥 names that are given to the
번호 of paths.
원문 의미: that we keep track of.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 this works as follows.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we 시작하다 our
generation with the beginning.
of sentence 토큰.
We 원하다 to figure out what the 다음 토큰 is.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have here, in
this 예시, a 매우 basic.
예시 like 셋 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's suppose the 둘 highest
probable 토큰들.
원문 의미: are A 그리고 the.
그래서 if we have k equal to 2, what we're ~할
예정입니다 to do.
원문 의미: is to keep track of these 둘
branches.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's the 첫째 iteration.
The 둘째 iteration is we're ~할 예정입니다.
to 보다 at all the probabilities of 다음 토큰
예측.
원문 의미: for these 둘 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to always save
the 둘 most probable paths.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, for instance, let's
suppose.
if it's like the, 그리고 그다음 fluffy 그리고 그다음 A
그리고 cute.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to what I was saying
earlier,.
원문 의미: 그래서 what I was saying was here, if
you were choosing.
원문 의미: the path that went along the
highest 확률.
원문 의미: 토큰 path, like the the, it's 매우 much
possible.
원문 의미: that the highest 확률 토큰.
원문 의미: 후에 there would be a much lower 확률.
than the 하나 후에 A.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 this is what beam search
tries to do.
원문 의미: It tries to have a more globally
optimal 해결책.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we continue that.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 at the end of the day, we
obtain, I guess,.
a 번호 of potential, I guess, choices 그리고
the k.
원문 의미: potential choices.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 we pick the 하나 that is the
highest, likely,.
원문 의미: the 시퀀스 with the highest 확률.
원문 의미: 그래서 people typically what they do
is.
원문 의미: they 가지다 the sum of the logarithm
of the probabilities.
of the 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 what they say is they say, OK.
그래서 the log 확률 of the 시퀀스.
원문 의미: is the sum of the log 확률.
of each 다음 토큰 예측.
그래서 it's the log 확률 of A, knowing BOS, 그리고
그다음 cute,.
knowing BOS 그리고 A, 그리고 그래서 on 그리고 그래서
forth.
하지만 I 그냥 원하다 to 포인트 out 하나 limitation of
this approach,.
원문 의미: which is that the more you generate
토큰들, the lower your,.
I guess, end 시퀀스 확률 will be.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you 생각하다 about it, all
these probabilities.
are between 0 그리고 1.
그래서 생각하다 of it like in the multiplied
sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have the 확률.
of the whole 시퀀스, which is 그냥.
a multiplication of the 확률 of the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: The more you add probabilities
below, like less than 1,.
원문 의미: the more this quantity will go
towards 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess this method, as is,
will prioritize.
원문 의미: 시퀀스들 that are shorter.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 for that reason, beam
search.
원문 의미: has some additional term that
기본적으로.
원문 의미: counteracts that effects.
그래서 something on the order of 1 over 번호 of
토큰들.
원문 의미: to the power of something.
원문 의미: 그래서 in practice, there is some
technique.
원문 의미: to 만들다 sure that things kind of
work relatively well.
OK.
원문 의미: Let's suppose we figure out all
these things.
The 문제 is that we 필요하다 to keep track.
원문 의미: of this most probable path.
원문 의미: We 필요하다 to do all this kind of
saving, et cetera.
그리고 it requires a lot of computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 the other thing is we're still.
원문 의미: interested in the most probable
path, which 기본적으로 will lead.
to a 시퀀스 that is 매우—
원문 의미: that the 모델 thinks is 매우 likely.
원문 의미: 하지만 sometimes what you 원하다 is for
your output.
원문 의미: to be more diverse or more
creative.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why beam search is 실제로
not something.
원문 의미: that people typically 사용하다.
원문 의미: People 사용하다 beam search for things.
원문 의미: like machine translation, where you
실제로.
원문 의미: 필요하다 to have something that is
close to something.
원문 의미: being 매우 likely.
하지만 실제로, people 사용하다 a 셋째 method.
원문 의미: 그리고 this method is called also the
샘플링 method.
그래서 I told you we have a 확률.
원문 의미: 분포 over 토큰들 regarding.
원문 의미: what the 다음 토큰 should be.
그리고 그래서 what people do is they 그냥.
원문 의미: sample the 다음 토큰 using that 확률분포.
원문 의미: Does this 만들다 sense?
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 예시, fluffy, gentle,
kind, 그리고 let's say.
원문 의미: smart will have a higher 확률 of
being drawn.
원문 의미: as opposed to let's say airplane,
that have a lower.
확률 of occurring.
원문 의미: Non-zero 확률, 하지만 they have a 확률 of
occurring.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 그래서 far?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Right.
그래서 the 문제 is it's not for 학습, it's for
추론.
원문 의미: Yes, correct.
생각하다 of it as a response generation.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have your 모델
that is 학습된.
원문 의미: What you 원하다 is to generate an
output.
원문 의미: 그래서 what would you do?
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 I guess, 그냥 to complete my 답, 그래서
during 학습,.
원문 의미: what you would do is care about the
output probabilities.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 compare them with the
actual label, which.
원문 의미: is, most of the time, like your
hard label.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, this is what you would
compare.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나 is let's suppose you
have an LLM that is 학습된,.
원문 의미: how would you generate a response?
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Are on goods?
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, how do you do 샘플링 in this
situation.
그래서 it's 실제로 my 다음 슬라이드.
하지만 I 그냥 원하다 to 만들다 sure everyone.
원문 의미: was on the 같은 page regarding 그냥 the
직관.
원문 의미: 그래서 highest 확률 is called greedy
decoding.
원문 의미: It's probably not something that we
원하다.
원문 의미: Beam search is a little bit better.
원문 의미: It's more something that is
globally optimal.
원문 의미: It's not globally optimal 하지만 more
towards that.
그래서 it's better 하지만 it lacks diversity.
원문 의미: It lacks creativity.
Which is why what we 원하다 to do is.
to 실제로 sample each 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess, we have a few methods.
원문 의미: that also restrict the kinds of
토큰들.
원문 의미: that we 원하다 to sample from.
왜냐하면 I mentioned, these 매우 low 확률 토큰들,.
원문 의미: they can still, theoretically, be
sampled.
하지만 it's not necessarily something that we
원하다.
원문 의미: 그래서 what people do is they
typically restrict.
원문 의미: the highest 확률 토큰들 그리고 only sample
from them.
원문 의미: 그래서 you may have heard of this
term, top-k 샘플링.
원문 의미: Who has heard of this term?
원문 의미: Yeah, a little bit.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you do is you select the
top highest probable k—
원문 의미: 그래서 the top k highest probable 토큰들
그리고 you sample from them.
그래서 let's suppose if k is equal to 4,.
원문 의미: you 가지다 the 넷 highest probable.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 그냥 sample with them.
원문 의미: 그리고 there's something else that is
quite similar in 아이디어.
원문 의미: which is called top-p.
원문 의미: 그래서 top-p is that you limit
yourself.
원문 의미: to the top to the highest probable
토큰들 such.
원문 의미: that their cumulative 확률 is.
원문 의미: more than a threshold p.
원문 의미: 그래서 again, it will do the 같은 thing.
원문 의미: It will select the highest probable
토큰들.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 there is a 부분 that I still
left out,.
원문 의미: which is how do you obtain these
probabilities to 시작하다 with?
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, here, I had mentioned that
we 그냥 assume.
원문 의미: we have the probabilities.
We 그냥 have them 그리고 we 원하다 to choose what
the 다음 토큰 is.
하지만 이제 the 문제 that I'm asking.
원문 의미: is 이제 that we 알다 what we will do
with these probabilities,.
I guess, 하나 문제 is, how do you.
원문 의미: obtain these probabilities to 시작하다
with.
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, these 트랜스포머-based
architecture.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 computes an encoder
representation of the input.
원문 의미: 그리고 what you have is some final
layers.
원문 의미: at the 매우 top of the figure, which.
원문 의미: aims at projecting the 벡터 into the
space.
of the 어휘집.
왜냐하면 what you 원하다 to do is to have a 확률.
원문 의미: 번호 for how probable it is for you
to sample a given 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, what you would do is at
the 매우 top.
원문 의미: of the architecture, have your
input,.
원문 의미: which is your encoded embedding of
the 토큰.
원문 의미: Go through a linear layer, which
기본적으로 projects your D 모델.
벡터 into a space of 차원 size of v.
원문 의미: 그리고 of course, what you 원하다 is
probabilities.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have a softmax
layer,.
원문 의미: which 기본적으로 converts everything to
probabilities.
원문 의미: such that everything sums to 1.
그리고 in order to 컴퓨트 the probabilities,.
원문 의미: 이것은 the formula that you would
사용하다,입니다.
원문 의미: which is the softmax layer.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is a hyperparameter that.
원문 의미: is quite 중요한 that I 원하다 to talk to
you about,.
원문 의미: which is the temperature T. 그리고 그래서
this is where it pops up.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the 확률 of the 다음 토큰
being a given.
원문 의미: word, which is equal to the
exponential.
원문 의미: of the input with respect to the
given word over temperature.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you normalize that by the
sum.
원문 의미: of all the other exponential of the
quantity over t.
그리고 이제 what we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 is what
that T is used for.
원문 의미: or what that T 실제로 does in
practice.
그래서 전에 we go into that, 그냥 하나 문제.
원문 의미: Has anyone heard about temperatures
when it.
원문 의미: comes to response generation?
원문 의미: Yeah.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 hopefully that will 주다 you a
better 아이디어.
원문 의미: of how the temperature kind of
influences.
원문 의미: your output predictions.
그래서 I guess, the 문제 that I 원하다.
원문 의미: to ask you is, what would be the
impact of having.
원문 의미: a low temperature versus a high
temperature?
원문 의미: 그래서 low temperature would
correspond to a diverse of what?
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 we will come to that in a 둘째.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, do you have a—
원문 의미: a lower temperature?
원문 의미: Increase in temperature.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess, back to the
explanation about,.
원문 의미: I guess, lowering the temperature.
원문 의미: 그리고 what impact it will do to the—
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess do you have a suggested
response to that?
원문 의미: I guess, lower temperature.
원문 의미: Let's suppose you have a lower
temperature, what happens?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess— 그래서 the long story
short.
원문 의미: is low temperature will create a
spiky 분포.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 high temperature will
create a uniform 분포.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess, I 생각하다 you had the
right 직관.
원문 의미: 저는 maybe write this in more
mathematical terms.할 것입니다.
OK.
원문 의미: Let's suppose you have your 확률,
which.
원문 의미: is the exponential of xi over t,
over the sum of exponential.
of xj over t.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 mathematically, you can 실제로.
원문 의미: prove what is happening here.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have the
index of the highest xi.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's call that k.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose what I do is I
will factor by this quantity.
원문 의미: 그래서 실제로, here, I don't have space.
그래서 let's do here.
그래서 it will be ae of k temperature.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 here, you have the sum of
over all j of exponential.
원문 의미: of xj over t minus xk over t.
그래서 what I did is I 그냥 multiplied.
원문 의미: the numerator 그리고 the denominator.
by exponential of xk over t.
원문 의미: 그래서 I multiplied numerator 그리고
denominator.
원문 의미: 그리고 of course, they cancel out.
하지만 그다음 what I have here is xy minus xk
over t.
그리고 here, xj minus k over t.
그래서 when i is equal to k, this term is 0.
원문 의미: It's exactly 0, regardless of the
temperature.
그리고 here, xj minus xk is always negative
or 0.
그래서 here, if i is equal to k, you have 0
over t.
그래서 here, it's 1.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have 1 plus—
원문 의미: I guess, some quantity.
그래서 j minus xk over t, which is ~할 예정입니다
to be negative.
그래서 the t ~할 예정입니다 to 0.
그래서 that 하나 will be, I guess, ~할 예정입니다
to,.
원문 의미: let's say, minus infinity.
그래서 exponential of minus infinity is 0.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you will end up with is
something.
원문 의미: where for i equal to k, you will
have a non-zero 확률.
하지만 그다음 for i not equal to k, you.
원문 의미: will have 0 over something that is
not equal to 0, which is 0.
그래서 그냥 mathematically, if you factor by
exponential of xk.
원문 의미: over t, where k is the index of the
highest value,.
원문 의미: I guess, the highest logit or the
highest activation 벡터,.
원문 의미: can 실제로 보여주다 that for a small
temperature, only.
원문 의미: the highest—
원문 의미: 그래서 the index of the, I guess,
highest value.
원문 의미: will be the 하나 that will be highest
probable with the spike.
원문 의미: there.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 when you have a high
temperature,.
기본적으로 it will 보다 like a uniform 분포.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 all these quantities, 그래서 when
t tends to plus infinity,.
원문 의미: this tends to 0.
그래서 exponential of 0 is 그냥 e.
원문 의미: Sorry, not e, 1.
그래서 1.
그래서 it's 1 over the 번호 of j.
그래서 it's 1.
그래서 그냥 a uniform 분포 across all the 토큰들.
of your 어휘집.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, how can I interpret
a small—
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, can I interpret that
as a Gaussian?
I 생각하다.
그래서 it's kind of tough 왜냐하면 Gaussian,.
원문 의미: you have some continuous quantities
in the x-axis.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, you have 토큰들.
그래서 it's kind of discrete.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's not something that you can
order.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 그냥 probably interpret that as
small temperature.
is 매우 spiky.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 정말 have a given set of
토큰들.
원문 의미: that are the highest probable that
will appear more.
원문 의미: 그리고 if you have a high
temperature,.
원문 의미: 그다음 기본적으로, 토큰들, even the ones.
원문 의미: that were not there to be the
highest probable,.
원문 의미: will 실제로 have an adjusted 확률 that
will be higher.
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of it as some kind
of scaling in that sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 long story short, what I 원하다 to
tell.
원문 의미: you is if you have a small
temperature,.
원문 의미: it will encourage the 다음 토큰 to be
geared towards being.
원문 의미: the highest probable 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 if you have a high
temperature,.
원문 의미: I guess the 분포 of probabilities.
원문 의미: will be kind of closer to a
uniform.
원문 의미: if you're 정말 increase that
temperature by a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 your output will be more
creative.
원문 의미: You will have 토큰들 that you would
have not.
원문 의미: drawn that would be drawn.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 what that means in
practice, if you're.
원문 의미: with your favorite LLM.
그리고 let's suppose you 원하다 to, I don't 알다,.
원문 의미: write something 매우 creative.
원문 의미: 그래서 which 하나 would you 사용하다?
원문 의미: Would you 사용하다 a low temperature or
high temperature?
원문 의미: High temperature?
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 원하다 something that is
more deterministic, more,.
원문 의미: I guess, closer to something that
is 매우, I guess,.
원문 의미: what you 생각하다 would be high
quality, will 사용하다.
원문 의미: more of a lower temperature.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 note here is that if you
have a strictly positive.
원문 의미: temperature, every time you run
your 모델 over an input,.
원문 의미: you will obtain a 다른 output.
그래서 something I 원하다 to 포인트 out is nothing
in the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: architecture is probabilistic.
원문 의미: Everything is deterministic.
원문 의미: The only thing that is not
deterministic.
원문 의미: is how you sample the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: It's the only thing that is not
deterministic.
원문 의미: 그래서 what will you do to have a
deterministic output?
원문 의미: You have t equal to 0.
원문 의미: T equal to 0, you 알다 for sure that
your output.
원문 의미: will be 그냥 하나 thing 그리고 nothing
else.
원문 의미: Well, that's what it's the
theoretical property.
원문 의미: 하지만 in practice, you have some
stuff.
원문 의미: 그것은 happening in the computation
that입니다.
원문 의미: introduces some non-deterministic
operations.
원문 의미: It's much more advanced than the
scope of this 수업,.
원문 의미: much more advanced of the scope of
this 수업.
I 그냥 원하다 to call out that in practice, t
equal to 0,.
원문 의미: may lead to 다른 results 왜냐하면 of this
kind.
원문 의미: of practical piece.
원문 의미: 그래서 what I recommend.
그래서 there's a suggested reading in 경우.
원문 의미: you're completely optional.
그래서 there is a 매우 recent article.
원문 의미: around defeating non-determinism in
LM 추론.
원문 의미: 그래서 I recommend that you read it in
경우 you're interested.
원문 의미: 그래서 the high level 아이디어 is our
GPU들, our hardware,.
원문 의미: when they reduce some of these
operations,.
원문 의미: sometimes they are reducing numbers
that.
are on 정말 다른 scales.
원문 의미: 그래서 the order at which these
operations are happening.
is 실제로 quite 중요한.
아이디어는 if these operations입니다.
원문 의미: they happen in 다른 order, it.
원문 의미: may lead to 다른 results.
원문 의미: Even if in theory, it should be
exactly the 같은,.
원문 의미: in practice, it may not be the 같은.
원문 의미: 그리고 this article 실제로 does a great
job.
at 그냥 explaining the 직관.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, 그냥 if you're interested,
completely optional.
좋습니다.
I 알다 I'm kind of late, 그래서 I guess,.
원문 의미: 지난 thing that I 원하다 to say is let's
suppose,.
what you 원하다 to do is to generate an
output in a 매우.
원문 의미: specific format.
원문 의미: Let's suppose a JSON format.
그래서 I guess, a 매우 naive approach.
원문 의미: would be to tell your LLM, well,
please generate this in JSON.
그리고 그다음 it produces something.
그리고 그다음 you try to 보다 if it's a valid
JSON.
원문 의미: If it's not, you repeat—
원문 의미: you 그냥 tell it to generate again.
원문 의미: until it does something well.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's the 첫째 naive approach.
원문 의미: Well, there is a 둘째 approach that
is called guided decoding.
원문 의미: 그리고 what that does is during the
generation process,.
원문 의미: it filters out what it calls
invalid 다음 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, let's suppose I 원하다 to
generate this JSON.
I 알다 for sure that my 첫째 토큰 must.
원문 의미: be something that opens the—
원문 의미: I forgot what the English word was
for this,.
원문 의미: 하지만 it 그냥 opens the brackets.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Open the brackets.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can only have this 그리고 그다음
you.
원문 의미: can only have the property name 그리고
그래서 on 그리고 그래서 forth.
원문 의미: 그리고 sometimes you can have more
than 하나 permitted 다음 토큰,.
원문 의미: in which 경우 you would go back to
our 다음 토큰 strategy.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, how do you restrict
the other 토큰들?
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a bunch of papers that
go into that.
원문 의미: We will not cover this.
원문 의미: 하지만 I can 주다 you some pointers.
원문 의미: 그냥 type finite state machine FSM
컨텍스트 grammar.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a bunch of papers that
do that.
원문 의미: We will not cover that here.
좋습니다.
그리고 I 생각하다 with that, we will go to the 둘째
부분.
원문 의미: with Shervin.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Thank you, Afshin.
그래서 이제, together, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다.
원문 의미: at 다른 prompting strategies.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 that how responses are
generated,.
우리는 보다 how to get responses할 것입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 how to get great responses.
그래서 let's go back to our favorite 예시.
원문 의미: about our cute teddy bear.
그래서 그냥 I 원하다 to 소개하다 하나 piece of 어휘집.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you have some kind of
input,.
원문 의미: you have the length of your inputs.
measured in 번호 of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 you will 보다 in the literature.
원문 의미: that it can have 다른 names.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 보다 it called 컨텍스트
length, 컨텍스트 size,.
원문 의미: window size.
원문 의미: 그리고 I 생각하다 the latest tools if you.
원문 의미: code on Cursor or any other code-
assisted tool,.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 they call it more 컨텍스트
length,.
원문 의미: 하지만 all these terms are equivalent.
원문 의미: 그리고 denote the 같은 thing.
OK.
그래서 이제 I 원하다 to 가지다 some time to discuss
what can be.
원문 의미: some orders of magnitude here.
원문 의미: 그래서 like modern day LLMs, they
tend.
원문 의미: to be in the order of magnitude of
tens of thousands,.
원문 의미: hundreds of thousands or millions
of input 토큰들.
원문 의미: as inputs.
이것은 the kind of input it can 가지다.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 sometimes, you hear some new
LLM boosts some 번호.
그리고 그다음 that 번호 of 컨텍스트 length is exactly
that.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's how much 토큰들 can it
accommodate in a single pass.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 yeah, the 모델들, you have.
원문 의미: seen maybe some advertisement of
these 모델들.
그래서 I 생각하다 at Gemini 그리고 others that.
원문 의미: are in the million territory.
원문 의미: Does that mean it's all nice 그리고
pretty?
If we have more 컨텍스트 length, is it ~할
예정입니다 to solve everything?
원문 의미: 실제로 not.
원문 의미: There is a phenomenon that was
recently.
원문 의미: dubbed as 컨텍스트 rot in a paper from
earlier this summer, where.
원문 의미: 기본적으로, the authors are
experimenting.
원문 의미: the capacity of the 모델 to retrieve.
원문 의미: some piece of information in a test
called needle.
in a Haystack.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, they ask some 문제.
원문 의미: 그리고 in larger 그리고 larger pieces of
text, they bury the 답.
원문 의미: 그리고 they try to 보다 at the capacity
of the 모델.
원문 의미: to surface that 답.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you can 보다 that with
respect to an increasing 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: length, that ability to ground the
information.
원문 의미: with the 답 that is in the 컨텍스트
decreases.
그리고 the paper I 생각하다 is a 매우 interesting
하나.
원문 의미: It controls with respect to what
else is in the 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: There is a term of distractors,
where they put some noise.
그리고 그다음 they 보다 distractors 기본적으로.
원문 의미: contribute in decreasing the
retrieval capability.
원문 의미: 그래서 also, what is in your 컨텍스트
matters.
원문 의미: 이것은 why in general, when you have a
retrieval입니다.
원문 의미: 문제, where you 원하다 to 사용하다 your LLM
to solve it,.
원문 의미: you have some good incentive to
try.
원문 의미: to target as much as possible, the
right piece of 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: for your LLM to 보다 그리고 predict on.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, is the 컨텍스트 length
exactly what.
원문 의미: is shown during self-attention?
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그리고 그다음 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다— 그래서 I.
원문 의미: 생각하다 we saw 지난 time that sometimes
there.
원문 의미: are some tricks that are used for
the complexity.
원문 의미: of the self-attention 메커니즘 not to
be n squared.
원문 의미: 이것은 what is being used to manage
basically입니다.
원문 의미: the complexity of the computations.
원문 의미: as the 컨텍스트 length grows.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 하지만 great call out to that.
그것은 exactly what is it about.입니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
질문 있나요?
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
OK.
좋습니다.
그래서 이제, let's 정의하다 what do 프롬프트들 usually
보다 like.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is no formal theory on
how to structure a given 프롬프트.
원문 의미: 하지만 these are the main lines that
are usually found.
in 프롬프트들 presented to 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can distinguish a 부분 that.
원문 의미: is setting up the 컨텍스트 where you 그냥
put the setting, you.
원문 의미: 만들다 it clear to the 모델, what kind
of query you 원하다 to issue.
원문 의미: 그다음 let's say, if you have some
tasks that you.
원문 의미: 원하다 the 모델 to perform, you have
instructions.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 these instructions are some
of them function.
원문 의미: that 가지다 as input something.
원문 의미: 그래서 you add some inputs.
원문 의미: 그리고 in order to get what you 원하다
out.
원문 의미: of the 모델's response, you may 원하다
to add some constraints out.
of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, we took our favorite 예시
with a teddy bear.
원문 의미: The 컨텍스트 is what is the teddy bear—
원문 의미: 기본적으로, what is the mood of the
teddy bear?
What do we 원하다 to do in order to 만들다 our
teddy bear happy?
그리고 그다음 we 주다 some input regarding.
원문 의미: where the story that we 원하다 to
generate is.
그리고 그다음 we 주다 some constraints.
원문 의미: If you 원하다 some other 예시 in the
LLMs.
원문 의미: that you query every day, 그래서 the
컨텍스트 could be some sentence.
원문 의미: that says, you are ChatGPT.
원문 의미: We are October 10.
It is 4:44 PM.
원문 의미: 그래서 you set the setup.
원문 의미: The instructions can be 기본적으로.
원문 의미: what the user queries alongside the
inputs.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 constraints might be
things.
원문 의미: that you don't 보다 as a user, 하지만
that.
원문 의미: might be present in the 프롬프트들 given
to the LLM, such as safety.
원문 의미: instructions.
원문 의미: For 예시, do not generate any
contents that might lead.
원문 의미: to harm, or things like this.
원문 의미: 그래서 every time you 보다 an input
being fed to an LLM,.
I 생각하다 these projections, these 넷 차원들.
원문 의미: can be a good mental 모델 of seeing
which pieces correspond.
원문 의미: to what goal in that structure.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: OK, great.
그래서 이제 that we 알다 what kind of mindsets.
원문 의미: we might have for inputs to an
LLM,.
let's 보다 how we can get an LLM to do what
we 원하다.
그리고 let's 보다 how we can get an LLM to do
what we 원하다.
원문 의미: without tuning any 가중치.
그리고 we can do 그래서 with a 개념 called in-컨텍스트
learning,.
원문 의미: where the learning is a bit of a
term that is overloaded.
왜냐하면 you don't 실제로 배우다 anything.
원문 의미: with respect to the 가중치 of the
LLM,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you can distill some knowledge
inside of it.
as 부분 of the 컨텍스트 in order to do what you
원하다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you distinguish 둘 main
categories.
of in-컨텍스트 learning.
그래서 there is 하나 category that is 매우 간단한.
원문 의미: In mindset, it's called zero-shot.
원문 의미: It's 기본적으로 you don't 주다 anything
other than your input,.
원문 의미: your input query.
원문 의미: You 그냥 ask the LLM to do what you
원하다 to do.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there is another school of
thought.
원문 의미: called few-shot learning, where
you.
주다 예시들 of inputs 그리고 outputs to the LLM.
원문 의미: 전에 asking the input that you're
interested in.
그래서 in the 경우 of a teddy bears 그리고 a
bedtime stories, 그래서.
원문 의미: you might name your teddy bears.
원문 의미: 그래서 maybe you have teddy bear
that's called Teddy.
원문 의미: 그리고 you generated a story.
원문 의미: 그래서 you put your query, you put the
story.
원문 의미: that you 원하다 to generate, 그리고 you
주다 multiple such 예시들.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's say you have another
teddy bear that's called Bob.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 원하다 to generate a story
for Bob.
원문 의미: 그래서 you put all of these 예시들,.
원문 의미: 그리고 you ask the LLM to generate the
story.
원문 의미: that you're interested in.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 this is 기본적으로 what we call
a few-shots setting.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제, generally, when you 보다 at
the performance.
원문 의미: of the resulting task, giving 예시들.
원문 의미: tends to steer the LLM nicely into
the task.
원문 의미: that you're interested in.
그냥 왜냐하면 you have given an 아이디어.
원문 의미: to the 모델 of what you are looking
for.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 it can 사용하다 what it has
learned during its 학습.
원문 의미: process to connect the dots 그리고
기본적으로 replicates.
하지만 of course, you 필요하다 to gather such
예시들.
이것은 costly.입니다.
원문 의미: This will put some more 토큰들 in the
컨텍스트 윈도우.
그래서 you will 필요하다 to more 컴퓨트.
원문 의미: 하지만 there is an interesting trade.
원문 의미: off here that we 보다 in recent 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 they are gaining more 그리고 more
reasoning capabilities,.
원문 의미: which is why I put the generally
nuance in italic here.
원문 의미: 그래서 they are generally better, few-
shots, 하지만 not always.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 these days, with these better
모델들,.
원문 의미: people have seen that with 기본적으로
making the instruction.
원문 의미: better, you could 만들다 the
performance.
원문 의미: of in-컨텍스트 learning on par, or even
better than.
if you provide 예시들, 왜냐하면 기본적으로, when you
생각하다 of it,.
원문 의미: when you provide 예시들, you constrain
your 모델.
원문 의미: into given sets of 예시들 that are
finite.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you are at 추론 time,.
let's say, you 원하다 to perform a task on a
분포 of 데이터.
원문 의미: that has not been seen, it is
harder for the 모델.
원문 의미: to generalize 왜냐하면 it will try to
align on what.
원문 의미: it has seen in the 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: Whereas if you turn your
instructions into something that.
원문 의미: is more reasoning based, you 설명하다.
원문 의미: how to do the task with natural
language,.
it can 사용하다 its reasoning abilities to 실제로
do it.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 something that you 보다 more
그리고 more these days.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 the literature on this, I 생각하다,
is still in progress,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you have some papers like a
plan.
원문 의미: 그리고 solve that's I 생각하다 came out
recently.
원문 의미: 그리고 that shows if you ask the LLM
to plan itself 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: solve something, it can have 매우
good performance.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, this is an interesting
fact.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 that we have seen 기본적으로 the
kinds of learning.
that we have, 이제, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다.
원문 의미: what we can do to improve the
quality of the response.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is this 개념 called chain
of thought,.
원문 의미: where researchers have seen that if
you force the 모델 to come.
원문 의미: up with some rationale to some 답.
전에 실제로 giving it, it would 주다 higher
performance.
원문 의미: 이것은 what people call as chain of
thought.입니다.
It's 기본적으로 what led you to the 답.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, for 예시, if you ask
yourself,.
원문 의미: how old is this teddy bear?
원문 의미: 그리고 if you force the 모델 to respond
directly with a 번호,.
원문 의미: it might not be able to do the
connection as.
원문 의미: to exactly why the Teddy bear is a
given age.
원문 의미: Whereas when you 주다 the full chain
of reasoning,.
원문 의미: 그다음 it becomes clear as to what led
to that response.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 this is the main mindset
behind this technique.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로, this is something that
can.
be used in in-컨텍스트 learning.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 주다 few-shot 예시들, how old
was this Teddy.
bear, you 주다 some 번호 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: you slightly change the query.
그리고 그다음 based on the reasoning,
formatting, 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: the response, the LLM can adjust
the reasoning 그리고 the response.
원문 의미: accordingly.
원문 의미: 그리고 it will force the 모델 to output
some reasoning.
원문 의미: alongside the response, which shows
an improvement.
in 기본적으로 metrics.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 yeah, something else that I
원하다 to say,.
let's say, you 원하다 to do a task 그리고 you
원하다 to do it well.
원문 의미: m you will always have some samples
that do not work.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 for them, you 원하다 to have
debugging ability.
원문 의미: 그리고 usually when you debug with
LLMs,.
원문 의미: you don't debug like the old days.
원문 의미: You don't 보다 at 가중치 at the
intrinsics of the LLM.
원문 의미: What you 원하다 is something more
interpretable.
that comes out of it in terms of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 usually, with these
techniques,.
원문 의미: you can 보다 the reasoning that the
모델 had 전에.
원문 의미: outputting a given response.
원문 의미: 그리고 you can debug 기본적으로 what went
wrong.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you ask how old will the
bear be 다음 year.
그리고 if in the chain of thought it says,
hey, we're in 2019,.
원문 의미: you 알다 that somehow in your 컨텍스트,.
원문 의미: oh, maybe I put the wrong dates in
there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can trace back to—
원문 의미: you can do some root causing 매우
easily.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's also used for that.
원문 의미: 그리고, exactly, in the 같은 way as
other techniques.
원문 의미: that increase the 번호 of 토큰들,.
원문 의미: 이것은 a trade off that you have to
manage,입니다.
원문 의미: that it will, of course, 가지다 more
time to infer 왜냐하면 you.
필요하다 to generate more 토큰들.
하지만 typically, we're fine with it.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 on COT?
원문 의미: OK, great.
그래서 이제 let's 가지다 it 하나 step further.
그래서 I 원하다 to 소개하다 even to 만들다 COT even
stronger,.
원문 의미: you can sample your 모델.
원문 의미: Several times, 보다 at the answers.
원문 의미: it generates, 그리고 그다음 do some
majority voting to select.
원문 의미: the 답 that was predicted most of
the times.
원문 의미: by a given LLM.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 what we call self-
consistency,입니다.
원문 의미: where 기본적으로, you sample responses
multiple times.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 parse the actual 답.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, you factor out the whole
reasoning.
그리고 그다음 try to target the 답.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 by majority voting, you can
come up.
to an 답 in a more robust way.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, do you 필요하다 to have
some benchmark.
to 알다 if it's better?
원문 의미: 그리고 yes, absolutely.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 the paper operates on top of
all the arithmetic.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 mathematical based ones.
그리고 I 생각하다 하나 tangential 문제 to yours.
원문 의미: is how can you locate the 답 그리고 그다음
do.
원문 의미: measure majority voting on it.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, you can put into the
컨텍스트.
원문 의미: some instruction that says, put the
actual 답 지난.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 그냥 extract the 지난.
원문 의미: People, I 생각하다, 사용하다 regex based
techniques, otherwise,.
원문 의미: to extract the 답.
원문 의미: Or you could even 생각하다 of using
some other LLM.
원문 의미: to extract the 답.
그래서 there is always a way to do it.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, to your 포인트, yes, we 필요하다
some benchmark.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 ground truth labels to
assert.
원문 의미: that this is indeed better.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the request here— 그래서 the 문제
is,.
is it ~할 예정입니다 to be sent to the 같은
request as 예시?
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, you sample it in
parallel.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, you ask your 모델 exactly
what Afshin 그냥.
원문 의미: mentioned.
원문 의미: You sample from the 확률분포 of BOS.
원문 의미: 그리고 whatever 토큰들 you had, the 다음
토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 you do that in several other
kind of branches.
원문 의미: 그리고 you do that, all of that, in
parallel.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you parse the 답 at the end
of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, the latency of this
process.
원문 의미: is equal, roughly, to the maximum
latency.
원문 의미: of either parallel generation.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you can do all of this in
parallel.
원문 의미: 그래서 none of these go into the 컨텍스트
of each other.
원문 의미: They're all done in parallel.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you get the final 답.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: All good?
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 that we have seen a few
prompting techniques,.
원문 의미: I 원하다 to cover together tricks that
people have come up.
with at 추론 time to 만들다 the generation as.
원문 의미: efficient as possible.
그리고 기본적으로, yeah, 그래서 in modern day 모델들,.
원문 의미: you have a lot of 파라미터들.
You 원하다 to generate a lot of 토큰들.
원문 의미: How do you do it the most
efficiently possible?
원문 의미: 그래서 I 원하다 us to divide this thought
process into 둘 parts.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what methods we
can come up with that.
원문 의미: 주다 us increased efficiency on an
exact level.
원문 의미: 그래서 you exactly do the 같은
computations.
원문 의미: as you were supposed to do, 하지만 in
a more efficient way.
원문 의미: 그리고 I put some hints as to what
kind of techniques.
우리는 explore.할 것입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's try to 보다 for techniques.
원문 의미: that avoid redundancies.
원문 의미: Let's try to 보다 what we could do to
manage.
원문 의미: the memory in the best way.
원문 의미: 그리고 also, let's try to 보다 if we can
reformulate.
원문 의미: the equations inside the LLM in a
way that could simplify.
원문 의미: the generation in practice.
그다음 there is a 둘째 category that we're.
~할 예정입니다 to explore as well.
그것은 ~할 예정입니다 to focus on what kind of
approximations입니다.
원문 의미: it might be fine to do, 그리고 get a
high quality.
답 at a lesser cost, 하지만 to be approximate.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have what kind of variations
we.
원문 의미: could do on the architecture?
원문 의미: Is there something we could do on
the embeddings.
원문 의미: to 만들다 them more efficient?
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 maybe on the 토큰 prediction
side,.
is there something we could do to 만들다 it
faster?
원문 의미: Does that sound good?
원문 의미: 그래서 we have approximately 22
minutes.
원문 의미: 우리는 try to go through all of them
here.할 것입니다.
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 I grouped the categories of
techniques.
원문 의미: into exact 그리고 approximate
하지만 실제로, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다.
원문 의미: at them in a grouped manner.
원문 의미: 첫째, looking at the attention
layer,.
원문 의미: seeing what kind of techniques we
could have there.
그리고 그다음 in a 둘째 부분, we're ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to 보다 at the output layer.
그리고 그다음 보다 what we can do at the level of
토큰 generation.
to 만들다 things as good as possible.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 시작하다 at the attention
level.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have seen that for every
토큰,.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 the current 토큰 to attend
to the previous ones.
원문 의미: in this masked self-attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say you generate your
시퀀스.
원문 의미: You are at a given 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say, you have generated a
cute teddy bear.
그리고 그다음 이제 you are at ease.
원문 의미: 이제 you have the query ease.
원문 의미: You will 컴퓨트 the key representation
그리고 the value.
원문 의미: representation of ease.
왜냐하면 of course, you have to do it.
It's your current 토큰.
원문 의미: 하지만 we 원하다 to have a way to reuse
the past computations we.
원문 의미: had done to 컴퓨트 the key
representation.
원문 의미: of the previous 토큰들 그리고 the value
원문 의미: of the previous 토큰들.
원문 의미: Does that 만들다 sense as a goal?
원문 의미: Does everyone agree?
OK.
그리고 more precisely, 기본적으로, we.
원문 의미: 원하다 to find a way for the key 그리고
value 행렬들 to be saved.
그리고 I'm not underlining the Q 부분.
원문 의미: here 왜냐하면 of course, the query
corresponding.
원문 의미: to the previous 토큰들 are not ~할
예정입니다.
원문 의미: to be of interest for the present
토큰.
그래서 it's like the key 그리고 value 부분.
OK.
그래서 there is this 개념 of KV cache, where.
원문 의미: the goal is to store this key 그리고
value.
원문 의미: 행렬들 somewhere, 그리고 reuse them
directly from the cache.
원문 의미: 그래서 what I 그냥 mentioned here, when.
you 원하다 to 컴퓨트 a given 토큰,.
원문 의미: you would reuse the key 그리고 the
value.
원문 의미: directly from the cache instead of
computing it again.
이것은 기본적으로, representation of what입니다.
원문 의미: we 그냥 mentioned here.
이해되나요?
OK.
원문 의미: Awesome.
원문 의미: 그래서 what else could we do?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
그래서 during 학습, do we do KV caching?
원문 의미: I would say during 학습, you have
this 개념.
원문 의미: of teacher forcing, where you put
all your inputs.
원문 의미: 그리고 pass it all together at once.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 개념 of KV caching doesn't
even come up.
원문 의미: Yeah.
하지만 great 하나.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah 그래서 the 문제 was, what is the
포인트 of all this?
원문 의미: We 원하다 to 그냥 reuse the computations
that.
원문 의미: were already done.
그리고 그다음 your 답 is yes.
원문 의미: Spot on.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 that we have seen that we
could cache these quantities.
원문 의미: 그래서 what else could we do?
그래서 is there something from 지난 week's 강의.
원문 의미: that we could reuse, maybe
something.
원문 의미: that reduces the amount of cache,
the key 그리고 value?
원문 의미: Do we have some techniques?
원문 의미: Sparse attention.
원문 의미: Yeah, that could be.
원문 의미: That could be, 하지만 not here.
원문 의미: Let's say you're attending to
everyone.
원문 의미: 그리고 you focus on the 번호 of keys 그리고
values.
원문 의미: Is there a way to reduce this 번호?
그래서 그냥 to 요약하다, we have here, I'm.
원문 의미: operating in the 컨텍스트 of multi-head
attention, which.
원문 의미: is you have your h heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have h 번호 of query
projections,.
원문 의미: h key projections, h value
projections.
원문 의미: These are any technique from 지난 주.
원문 의미: that we could reuse that could
reduce this 번호.
원문 의미: Yeah.
I heard it.
원문 의미: Group query attention.
원문 의미: Yeah, exactly.
원문 의미: 그래서 we had these 개념 of grouping
keys 그리고 values.
원문 의미: together, where 기본적으로 the general
formulation is called.
원문 의미: group query attention, where you
group these, 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: the external values h 그리고 1 denotes
respectively.
원문 의미: the full multi-head attention, 그리고
그다음 multi query attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 in modern day LLMs, a lot
of papers,.
원문 의미: they 사용하다 GQA, with some group that
is sensible value.
이것은 also something we can do.입니다.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 이제 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to go a little bit
into the hardware.
원문 의미: side of things.
원문 의미: 그래서 if we were to store the cache
for all these values in a naive.
원문 의미: way, at 추론 time.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say you receive—
그래서 let's say I'm an 추론 server,.
원문 의미: I receive queries from multiple
users.
그리고 let's say I receive a query 하나 그리고 I
receive a query 둘,.
원문 의미: a naive way of storing the key 그리고
value 행렬들 would.
원문 의미: be in reserving a portion of the
memory.
원문 의미: at the beginning that correspond to
the entire 컨텍스트 length,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you don't where you're ~할
예정입니다 to stop.
원문 의미: You're decoding 왜냐하면 you stop your
decoding.
원문 의미: when you hit the EOS 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have this whole
block.
원문 의미: of size 컨텍스트 length, maximum 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: length that could be reserved.
그래서 하나 observation is that it leads to a
lot of waste.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say if your 컨텍스트 length
is of size like 2k,.
원문 의미: you have 2k reserved for a given
request 2k there.
원문 의미: 그래서 at any given time, let's say,
you 원하다 to get more requests,.
원문 의미: you 원하다 to serve more requests.
원문 의미: Your memory will 매우 quickly not.
원문 의미: have enough space to accommodate
Does.
원문 의미: these constraints or this challenge
만들다 sense?
원문 의미: Yeah.
OK.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there is this paper that is
called PagedAttention.
원문 의미: 그리고 it defines several quantities.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is this reserved quantity
internal fragmentation.
원문 의미: 그리고 external fragmentation.
원문 의미: Internal fragmentation is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: the space that is being reserved by
the 모델.
원문 의미: to complete the request.
원문 의미: 그리고 the reserved spot is the subset
of it.
원문 의미: that corresponds to 토큰들 that were
실제로 being used.
그래서 it's the kind of space that's 실제로.
원문 의미: used internal fragmentation.
원문 의미: There is nothing in there, 하지만 it
was reserved.
원문 의미: 그리고 external fragmentation is the
memory management system.
원문 의미: that doesn't necessarily put 하나
block 하나 후에 another,.
원문 의미: 하지만 has its own way of allocating
memory blocks.
원문 의미: 그래서 it might leave some other gaps.
원문 의미: 그리고 they came up with a system
that.
원문 의미: is called a PagedAttention that is
powering.
원문 의미: 하나 추론 package called the vLLM that.
원문 의미: solves this issue by mapping, like
the generation process.
원문 의미: by blocks of fixed size.
원문 의미: 그래서 instead of allocating a whole
portion of the memory.
to 답 a given request, it breaks it down.
원문 의미: by smaller chunks.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 the paper takes like a
value of 16 for blocks.
원문 의미: 그래서 as you can 보다, let's say you
are in a generation process.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have used a given row, you.
원문 의미: would 그냥 시작하다 using another row
without wasting.
원문 의미: more space than that.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have some dictionary.
원문 의미: that maps 토큰 position indices to
기본적으로 their cache values.
그래서 there is a smart way of managing it.
원문 의미: 그리고 they 보여주다 that it reduces
fragmentation by quite a lot.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 이제 let's do something else with
this KV cache.
원문 의미: 그래서 we 그냥 saw that you have your
internal representation.
원문 의미: of your 토큰 그리고 you project it into
query, key, 그리고 value.
그리고 그다음 key 그리고 value is 실제로.
원문 의미: something that is of a 차원 that is
like non-negligible.
그리고 you 필요하다 to store each copies of it.
원문 의미: in each 트랜스포머 block.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have many of these 벡터들.
원문 의미: that you 필요하다 to keep track of.
원문 의미: 그리고 is there a way to 만들다 that
representation somehow more.
원문 의미: compact?
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 a topic that DeepSeek has
tried입니다.
to tackle in a 개념 called—
원문 의미: I 생각하다 it was called multi-latent
attention.
우리는 보다—할 것입니다.
그래서 let's 보다 at the vanilla 경우.
원문 의미: If you are in multi-head
attention,.
그다음 for a given representation of a 토큰,.
원문 의미: you have h projection 행렬들 that turn
it into a key.
원문 의미: Does everyone agree with that?
원문 의미: 그래서 the kind of self-attention
formula,.
원문 의미: you have a projection 행렬 wk for
keys,.
원문 의미: that will project the 토큰
representation into some key.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have h heads.
원문 의미: You have h such projections 그리고
you.
원문 의미: have h such resulting embeddings
that you.
원문 의미: 필요하다 to store in your cache.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you have that for keys, you
have that for values.
그것은 a lot of 벡터들 to store.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 these keys 그리고 values, they are
quite long as well.
그래서 let's 보다 if we can 만들다 it smaller.
원문 의미: What multi-latent attention does
is.
원문 의미: that it factorizes these projection
행렬.
원문 의미: into an intermediary space that is.
원문 의미: of lower 차원 than the space of keys.
원문 의미: You have a 첫째 transformation that.
원문 의미: reduces the 차원 그리고 그다음 another 하나
that.
원문 의미: decompresses it.
원문 의미: 이것은 the 첫째 operation that they입니다.
원문 의미: did in order to 만들다 the
representation more compact.
원문 의미: 하지만 they did something else that is
매우 smart.
원문 의미: They said that the compression 행렬.
원문 의미: could be shared across keys 그리고
values, which.
원문 의미: says for a given 토큰 representation,
the cache.
원문 의미: that you 필요하다 to store for keys 그리고
for values is the 같은.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you would have still 다른
행렬들.
원문 의미: here for the decompression 부분 to
실제로 배우다.
원문 의미: 다른 representations for a key 그리고
value.
원문 의미: 하지만 하나 simplification here has been
to share it.
원문 의미: for across keys 그리고 values.
원문 의미: 그리고 even better, share it across
the h heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 instead of having h such
embeddings, you have 그냥 하나.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you do that for key.
원문 의미: You do that for value.
원문 의미: 그래서 at the end of it, for every
트랜스포머 block,.
원문 의미: you have a single representation
per 토큰.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: 그래서 not only you have less things
to store.
원문 의미: The DeepSeek V2 paper also showed a
performance improvement.
원문 의미: that it's kind of credited some
regularization.
원문 의미: consequence of doing 그래서.
원문 의미: 그래서 it learns representations that
are maybe more useful.
원문 의미: 그리고 shared across keys 그리고 values.
원문 의미: 그래서 apparently there is also
performance benefits to it that.
원문 의미: is not 그냥 hardware based.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 we have seen some—
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, do you tune the low
rank 차원?
원문 의미: 그래서 the 차원 itself is a design
choice.
It's fixed.
그래서 the 문제 is, is it the 같은 lower.
원문 의미: 차원 for everyone.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 차원 size is fixed 그리고 is the
같은 for everyone.
I 생각하다.
하지만 it's a design choice.
원문 의미: You could have 다른 ones, 하지만 I 생각하다
in practice it.
might be the 같은 하나.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 we have less than 10
minutes.
원문 의미: We are ~할 예정입니다 to cover techniques
that operate at the output.
원문 의미: 토큰 level.
그리고 그다음 시작하다 with a 개념 called speculative
decoding.
그것은 a 매우 interesting method입니다.
원문 의미: that uses some smaller 모델 to help
the generation of a bigger.
원문 의미: 모델, 그리고 그다음 uses some scheme that.
원문 의미: makes the 분포 outputs match 하나 of
the target 하나.
그래서 it uses a combination of tricks.
of using a smaller 모델 to generate things,
그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: gates it with some mathematical
based properties.
to ensure we get a 분포 that.
원문 의미: looks the 하나 of the big 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 here's what is the lectures,
the mindset of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 그냥 come back to our
favorite 예시.
원문 의미: about teddy bears.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you do is that you ask a
smaller.
원문 의미: 모델, that the paper calls draft, to
generate 다음 words.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have my teddy bear.
원문 의미: What could be 다음 words?
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 하나 pass.
원문 의미: You find 토큰 is.
원문 의미: You fit 토큰 is here again.
원문 의미: You find cute 그리고 smart.
원문 의미: Since the LLM is small, this is
typically done faster than.
원문 의미: with the big LLM.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 once you have all of
these,.
원문 의미: you put the 토큰들 that are predicted
by the smaller LLM.
원문 의미: all as inputs to the target's LLM.
원문 의미: 그것은 like the bigger 모델, like the
one입니다.
원문 의미: that you 사용하다, to generate 확률.
원문 의미: distributions for each of them.
그리고 그다음 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that by
having.
원문 의미: some rule on the output 분포 of each.
원문 의미: of these 토큰들, you can simulate a
확률.
분포 of each 토큰 of each 다음 토큰 that.
원문 의미: looks 하나 of the target 모델들.
그래서 here's 기본적으로 how it goes.
그래서 it looks at the 확률 of the 토큰.
원문 의미: that the draft 모델 has predicted.
그래서 if the 확률 of the draft 모델.
원문 의미: is bigger than the 하나 of the draft
모델 in the draft 모델's.
원문 의미: output 분포, 그다음 you 그냥 accept the
토큰.
원문 의미: Otherwise, you have some acceptance
rejection mechanism.
원문 의미: that either accepts the 토큰 or
rejects it.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's say everything is
accepted.
원문 의미: 그다음 in a single pass, you are able
to advance.
원문 의미: by way more 토큰들.
그리고 그다음 if it fails, 그다음 기본적으로 you.
원문 의미: resume the process of generation
from that good 토큰 onwards.
원문 의미: with some adjustments on the 분포.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 문제 that you might ask from
all of this,.
원문 의미: this looks like a recipe.
원문 의미: Why is that matching the target 분포?
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 시작하다 from the law of
total 확률.
원문 의미: 그리고 write each term with these
quantities.
원문 의미: 그다음 you will find the target 분포 at
the end.
그래서 it's an exercise that I encourage you
to do.
원문 의미: 그리고 the paper that is attached to
the 슬라이드.
원문 의미: here demonstrates it in 그냥 a few
lines.
그래서 it's a 매우 간단한 proof.
그리고 I 생각하다 it's a 매우, 매우 interesting 하나.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: Yeah.
The 문제 is, is that rejection 샘플링?
원문 의미: 그래서 some of you might be familiar
with it already.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 하나 thing that I didn't say
is that.
원문 의미: why did we even put the 지난 토큰 here?
원문 의미: We put all the draft 토큰들, 하지만 also.
원문 의미: the 지난 하나 that was predicted 왜냐하면.
원문 의미: by doing a single forward pass with
all these draft 토큰들,.
원문 의미: you get for free the 확률분포 of the
토큰.
원문 의미: that comes 후에 that you can 그다음 그냥
sample from Qk plus 1.
그래서 그냥 to 주다 some summary of the
rationale.
원문 의미: Doing a single pass is as expensive
as doing.
하나 pass at a time, 왜냐하면 at 추론 time,.
원문 의미: you're memory bounds back.
원문 의미: In other words, computations are
not the limiting factor.
원문 의미: It's 기본적으로 the memory that will.
원문 의미: bottleneck your computation.
그래서 you 원하다 to do it on a smaller 모델.
그리고 그다음 on the big 모델, you 원하다.
to 컴퓨트 all of these 확률 distributions.
원문 의미: at once.
이해되나요?
OK.
좋습니다.
그리고 그다음 I 원하다 to talk about 하나 지난
technique.
원문 의미: 그것은 called multi-토큰 prediction.입니다.
원문 의미: It's the 같은— 그래서 by the way, this
previous technique.
원문 의미: was called speculative decoding.
그리고 그다음 this 하나 is 기본적으로 doing the 같은.
그래서 it's doing slightly a 다른 thing.
하지만 the draft 모델 is embedded in the 같은
모델,.
원문 의미: which is 매우 powerful.
그래서 기본적으로, it's a 모델 that attaches
multiple heads.
원문 의미: on top of the representation of the
지난 decoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 the process here is that at 학습
time,.
it doesn't do 다음 word prediction.
원문 의미: It does multi word prediction.
원문 의미: 그리고 at test time, the draft 모델 is
all your heads.
그리고 your main 모델 is 그냥 the 첫째 head.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have all your draft 토큰들.
원문 의미: that you 그다음 feed back to the 첫째
head.
그리고 그다음 do acceptance rejection.
원문 의미: 그래서 the paper does it in a greedy
way.
그래서 it doesn't do it with this formula.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 since the architecture 그리고 그다음
the objective function.
원문 의미: has changed, you don't have this
nice property of finding again,.
the 다음 토큰 predictions 분포.
원문 의미: 하지만 you have a slight variation of
it.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 like the interesting notes out
of the multi.
원문 의미: 토큰 prediction is the change in
objective function.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 둘째, the fact that the draft
모델 그리고 the target.
모델 are 기본적으로 embedded in the 같은 하나.
원문 의미: 그래서 don't have to separate the 둘.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah.
그래서 you do 기억하다 this 슬라이드?
원문 의미: We have explored techniques that
can.
원문 의미: remedy each of these aspects.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
원문 의미: I highly recommend taking a 보다 at
the associated papers.
원문 의미: as well.
원문 의미: 그리고 with that, thank you 매우 much.