좋습니다.
여러분 안녕하세요.
Welcome to 강의 2 of CME 295.
시작하기 전에, I 원했습니다 to 주다 you a heads.
원문 의미: up about 둘 logistical things.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is with Shervine, we
reviewed.
the recording of 강의 1.
원문 의미: 그리고 we couldn't help 하지만 notice
that the audio was suboptimal.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we're doing for this 강의.
원문 의미: is to have another setup.
하지만 그다음 하나 issue is my voice will not.
원문 의미: be propagated in the room.
그래서 I guess I have 하나 문제.
원문 의미: 다들 제 목소리가 매우 well, even from the
back 들리나요?
네, 좋습니다.
좋습니다.
그래서 that's 포인트 번호 1.
두 번째 포인트는 about the 기말고사.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 기말고사 right 이제 has a
placeholder date.
원문 의미: for Wednesday, I 생각하다, December the
10th.
하지만 그냥 a heads up that we're trying.
to 보다 if there is a way to 이동하다 that to
earlier in the 주.
원문 의미: 그래서 we'll let when that's
finalized.
원문 의미: 하지만 for 이제, this is still TBD.
하지만 we'll 만들다 sure to let you 알다.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that aside, let's go into
today's topic.
하지만 전에 we do that, as always, what we will
do.
원문 의미: is we'll 그냥 quickly 요약하다 what we
saw in the previous episodes.
기억하신다면, 강의 1 was all.
원문 의미: about introducing the 개념 of self-
attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 if you 기억하다, what self-
원문 의미: is that each 토큰 is attending to all
other 토큰들.
원문 의미: in the 시퀀스 through this mechanism
of attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have these notations of
queries, keys, 그리고 values.
원문 의미: 그래서 here the 아이디어 is that the
query.
is ~할 예정입니다 to ask which other 토큰들 are.
원문 의미: most similar to itself by comparing
query 그리고 key.
그리고 그다음 once that's done, 기본적으로 we.
원문 의미: will be taking the associated
value.
원문 의미: 그래서 we saw that the self-attention
메커니즘 can.
원문 의미: be expressed with this formula, 그래서
softmax.
원문 의미: of query times key transpose over
square root.
원문 의미: of dk times v. 그래서 I hope this
formula is familiar for you.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 알다 that this formula is
highly optimized.
원문 의미: These are big 행렬 multiplications,
or hardware,.
is 매우 capable of doing, it's 매우 optimized
in doing that.
원문 의미: 그리고 all of that to say that we
also.
원문 의미: introduced the architecture of the
트랜스포머, which.
원문 의미: you can 보다 on the right.
그래서 here, if you 기억하다, the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: is composed of 둘 main components.
원문 의미: 그래서 the encoder on the left side
그리고 the decoder.
원문 의미: on the right side.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 트랜스포머 was initially.
원문 의미: introduced in the 컨텍스트 of machine
translation.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of the left side.
원문 의미: as processing the input text in the
source language,.
원문 의미: say English.
원문 의미: 그리고 the right side is responsible
for decoding.
원문 의미: the translation in a target
language, let's say in French.
원문 의미: 그리고 this multi-head attention
layer.
원문 의미: is where the self-attention 메커니즘
happens.
그리고 I 기억하다 there was a lot of 문제들.
원문 의미: regarding— it's called multi-head
attention layer.
원문 의미: 그래서 there are several heads.
원문 의미: What does that correspond to?
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 트랜스포머 paper, which is
the "Attention is All.
원문 의미: You 필요하다" paper, you have this
figure,.
원문 의미: which 실제로 represents each of these
heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 you can 생각하다 of each head as an
opportunity for the 모델.
원문 의미: to 배우다 하나 way of projecting the
input into being.
원문 의미: a query, a key, or a value.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 being a bit more clear, 그래서
for instance,.
원문 의미: for the query 그리고 the key, 그래서 this
is like each head.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 번호 of these little boxes.
is 기본적으로 the 번호 of heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 to better visualize 그리고
understand what this means,.
I also 원했습니다 to 보여주다 I guess what.
원문 의미: is being shown in the paper, which
is a way to interpret what.
원문 의미: each of these heads do.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have this 개념 called
attention map, which 기본적으로.
원문 의미: tries to represent the value of
each of these query,.
원문 의미: dot product query.
그래서 in this 예시, what we're interested in.
원문 의미: is to 보다 which other 토큰 is being
most similar to 토큰 its.
그리고 그래서 what we do is we 가지다 a 보다 at the
quantities,.
원문 의미: the query that is representing
its,.
원문 의미: dot product, all other keys.
원문 의미: 그리고 we 보다 at what are the keys are.
원문 의미: leading to a high value of the dot
product query times key.
원문 의미: 그리고 when you do that, 기본적으로 what
you 보다.
원문 의미: or what the paper sees is you have
these 둘 words, 그래서.
원문 의미: application 그리고 law, which are
highlighted as being.
원문 의미: with the high-attention 가중치.
원문 의미: 그래서 attention 가중치 here being the
dot.
원문 의미: product of the query its, 그리고 the
key for each.
of these 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess there is also a way to
interpret those.
원문 의미: 그리고 here you can 보다 that the 토큰들
that.
원문 의미: are being highlighted are law 그리고
application, which.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 makes sense 왜냐하면 the 토큰 its.
원문 의미: is referring to law.
그래서 기본적으로, the 모델 needs to 배우다.
원문 의미: how to associate these words with
what happened 전에.
원문 의미: 그리고 its is also referring to
application,.
원문 의미: which is also another way of
explaining why that is the 경우.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 here what the authors chose
to do.
원문 의미: was to 보여주다 these values as a
function.
원문 의미: of these 다른 heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, on the left
side,.
원문 의미: these are the intensity for heads,.
원문 의미: for let's say the 첫째 heads.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 둘째 heads shows that the
intensity.
원문 의미: is 매우 high for law.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, long story short, these
heads may 배우다,.
원문 의미: I guess, 다른 ways of figuring out
what words matters.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when we're doing all
these computations,.
원문 의미: are they ~할 예정입니다 through 다른 MLPs.
The 답 is that we're ~할 예정입니다 to have 다른
projection.
원문 의미: 행렬들 for each of them.
원문 의미: 그래서 we had this detailed 예시 that
실제로 went through that.
원문 의미: where each head is ~할 예정입니다 to have
its own projection.
원문 의미: 그리고 in parallel, you're ~할 예정입니다 to
have that computation that's.
~할 예정입니다 to happen.
그래서 each head is ~할 예정입니다 to have 하나 결과
here, that is 그다음.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to be concatenated 그리고 그다음
projected once again when.
원문 의미: the output 행렬.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, long story short, it's
highly parallelized.
그리고 it's 기본적으로 그냥 like projections.
원문 의미: 그리고 here you have some 행렬
multiplication 그리고 softmax.
이해되나요?
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들 on this?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess this is 그냥 a way to
illustrate the conversation we.
원문 의미: had for 강의 1.
원문 의미: There was some 문제들 about these
attention.
원문 의미: heads, what they do.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess looking at the
attention maps.
원문 의미: is 하나 way of making sense of what
they mean.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: With that, I highly recommend that
you read the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: paper, 그래서 "Attention is All You
필요하다.".
그래서 it's a 매우 dense paper.
It's 그냥 a few pages long.
원문 의미: 하지만 I hope that what you've seen in
강의 1,.
원문 의미: you'll be able to digest the
content in a way that.
원문 의미: will 만들다 sense to you.
좋습니다.
그래서 with that, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 the
actual meat of what.
우리는 discuss 오늘.할 것입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 surprisingly, this 트랜스포머
architecture,.
which was introduced in 2017, is 실제로.
원문 의미: an architecture that has still
stayed relevant along the years.
원문 의미: 그리고 there are a few components that
have slightly changed.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 which ones they
are.
원문 의미: 그래서 there are some slight
variations.
하지만 overall, today's 모델들 are, we're.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 보다, all more or less
based on the initial 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: architecture.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to try to divide the 수업
in 둘 parts.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is what I'm ~할 예정입니다 to
cover,.
원문 의미: which is what are the parts of the
트랜스포머 that.
원문 의미: are 중요한 그리고 that had some
variation.
그리고 in the 둘째 부분, Shervine is ~할 예정입니다 to
talk about, I guess,.
원문 의미: the nomenclature of today's 모델들.
원문 의미: 그리고 how they relate to the original
트랜스포머.
좋습니다.
OK, 그래서 let's 시작하다 with the 첫째 중요한 개념
that's.
원문 의미: in this architecture.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 the position embedding.입니다.
기억하신다면, here we're letting 토큰들 interact.
원문 의미: with all other 토큰들 in a direct
fashion.
원문 의미: 그래서 they have direct links.
원문 의미: 하지만 contrary to things like RNNs,.
원문 의미: where you have a sequential
dependency where.
원문 의미: you process each 토큰 하나 at a time,.
원문 의미: here you're 기본적으로 losing this 아이디어
of a 토큰 being.
원문 의미: processed 전에 another 하나.
원문 의미: 그래서 you lose this position
information.
그래서 as a 결과 of that, we 필요하다 to somehow
quantify 토큰들.
원문 의미: at each position 그리고 try to inject
that information when.
원문 의미: the 트랜스포머 is processing the inputs.
그래서 how are we ~할 예정입니다 to do that?
원문 의미: 그래서 the original 트랜스포머 paper
authors,.
원문 의미: they chose to have a dedicated
embedding.
원문 의미: 그리고 when I say dedicated, what that
means is each position.
원문 의미: has 하나 embedding.
원문 의미: 그래서 position 1 has 하나 embedding,
position 2.
원문 의미: has 하나 embedding, et cetera, et
cetera.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they chose to do is to add
that embedding.
원문 의미: to the input-토큰 embedding.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if I say a cute
teddy bear is reading,.
원문 의미: which is position 번호 1,
representing.
원문 의미: the 토큰 a, plus the embedding
representing the 첫째 position.
원문 의미: Yeah.
It's a great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, are the position
embeddings.
원문 의미: learned or static?
원문 의미: Both, as in the authors have tried
both.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what the 둘째 하나
is.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess here let's suppose that
they are learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 what does that mean?
그래서 that means that 기본적으로 you 필요하다 to 배우다.
원문 의미: embeddings for each position.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 문제 with this approach.
원문 의미: is that you're 매우 much dependent on
what.
is in your 학습 set.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, like here, if you
have somehow a text.
원문 의미: that always has something that is
happening at position 번호.
원문 의미: 2, your learned embeddings will
have that bias kind of learned.
그래서 that's 하나 limitation of that.
원문 의미: 둘째 limitation is you can only 배우다
positions up.
원문 의미: to the max 번호 of position that is
in your 학습 set.
그래서 let's suppose you 학습하다 your 트랜스포머 on
시퀀스들.
원문 의미: that are up to, let's say, 512,
let's say.
원문 의미: You can only 배우다 position
embeddings up to that position.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, I guess, how do you
parameterize that?
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess what you do is you
have.
원문 의미: a placeholder of a learnable
position embedding,.
원문 의미: let's say between position 1 그리고
512.
그리고 기본적으로, when you do your 학습,.
원문 의미: you're 그냥 letting these 가중치.
원문 의미: be learned through the regular
gradient.
원문 의미: descent, all these things.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, 그래서 this is like the 첫째
method.
원문 의미: 하지만 as I was mentioning, it has its
limitations,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you can only 배우다 embeddings of
positions.
원문 의미: up to the max position that is
present in the 학습 set.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, if you have at 추론
time.
원문 의미: a position that is beyond the
position that.
원문 의미: was in the 학습 set, well, you have
not learned that.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to find a way to infer
the value.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's the 둘째 limitation.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, 하지만 on the pro side, I
guess you're 그냥.
원문 의미: letting your 모델 배우다.
그리고 we've seen that the 경사하강법.
원문 의미: does wonders when it comes to 그냥
learning from the 데이터.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
원문 의미: 그리고 for these reasons, these
methods.
원문 의미: was something that the authors said
that was performing well,.
원문 의미: along with the 둘째 method, which is
다른,.
원문 의미: which is around having an
arbitrary.
원문 의미: formula for each 차원 corresponding.
원문 의미: to a position embedding.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that 이제.
원문 의미: 그래서 첫째 method was you have 하나
embedding per position,.
그리고 you 그냥 배우다 that.
원문 의미: 둘째 method is you have 하나 embedding
per position,.
하지만 you're not ~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 that.
원문 의미: You're ~할 예정입니다 to have something
that is predetermined.
that you're ~할 예정입니다 to 사용하다.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that what the
authors choose.
원문 의미: was a formulation using sine 그리고
cosine.
원문 의미: 그래서 it can feel weird, why did they
choose this.
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 why that makes
sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 here is for a given
position, let's say m,.
have a 벡터 of size d 모델.
그래서 d needs to match the 차원.
of your 토큰 embeddings, 왜냐하면 of course
you're.
원문 의미: adding them.
그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is, for
every index.
원문 의미: you're ~할 예정입니다 to 컴퓨트 the
corresponding value with respect.
원문 의미: to these formulas.
원문 의미: 그래서 what are these formulas?
그래서 it's 기본적으로 sine of something times m.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what that
something means.
그리고 그다음 the 둘째 하나 is cosine of something
times m.
원문 의미: 그래서 who remembers trigonometry
formulas?
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Everyone.
원문 의미: 그래서 전에 we go into that, let's 그냥
simplify the notations.
원문 의미: Let's 그냥 assume that this big
quantity that you saw.
원문 의미: is 실제로 something like omega.
그래서 let's suppose it's omega as a function
of i times m.
원문 의미: 그리고 you note omega i as being this
quantity,.
그래서 10,000 to the power of minus 2i over d
모델.
원문 의미: Let's suppose you construct your
embeddings to have this way.
그다음, I guess I 원하다 us to 생각하다 about why
that would 만들다 sense.
왜냐하면 if you 생각하다 about it, what you 원하다.
원문 의미: is to represent positions in a way.
원문 의미: that reflects the following fact—
원문 의미: words that are close together are.
원문 의미: likely to be more relevant, as
opposed to words.
원문 의미: that are further together.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you have 둘 words that are
like 그냥 하나 position apart.
원문 의미: versus 10,000 position apart, what
you 원하다 is that the 하나.
원문 의미: 그것은 하나 position apart is more
similar than the other 하나.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 보다 if the formula makes
sense.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have 둘
position embeddings, 그래서 하나.
at position m 그리고 the other 하나 at position
n.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's suppose you 컴퓨트 in all
the values.
원문 의미: from this predetermined formula.
원문 의미: Well, it turns out, if you 기억하다.
원문 의미: your trigonometry formulas, 그래서
cosine of a minus b.
원문 의미: is equal to cosine of a cosine of
b, plus sine a sine b.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: Well, turns out that if you express
cosine of omega i,.
원문 의미: factor of m minus n, this is
something that you obtain.
원문 의미: It's 그냥 the identity that I
mentioned.
원문 의미: Well, it 그냥 turns out that this
quantity.
원문 의미: is 그냥 하나 component that appears.
원문 의미: when you do the dot product of
these 둘 position embeddings.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 기본적으로 here, when you do.
원문 의미: the dot product of position m 그리고
position n, what you do.
원문 의미: is you 가지다 the 첫째 position, you
multiply them,.
원문 의미: 그다음 you plus the 둘째 position,.
원문 의미: you multiply them, et cetera, et
cetera.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you come here, it's sign of
this times sine of this,.
원문 의미: plus cosine of this times cosine of
this,.
원문 의미: which is 그냥 this quantity.
원문 의미: 그래서 at the end of the day, what you
realize.
원문 의미: is that when you perform a dot
product of these embeddings,.
원문 의미: you end up with a sum of cosine
that.
원문 의미: are a function of the relative
distance between m 그리고 n.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: What do you mean by pair, by the
way?
원문 의미: Exactly, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, 그래서 the closer they
are,.
원문 의미: the more similar they are.
그래서 that's the 직관, that 기본적으로.
원문 의미: this way of formulating the
embeddings.
원문 의미: is trying to approximate or it's
trying to mimic.
원문 의미: 그래서 with that, you 기본적으로 obtain a
dot product.
그것은 그냥 a function of m 그리고 n, the relative
distance입니다.
원문 의미: between them, 실제로.
원문 의미: 그리고 그냥 as a reminder, 그래서 why do I
care about the dot product?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you 기억하다, in the embedding
world.
원문 의미: when we try to quantify the
similarity between 둘.
원문 의미: embeddings, what we do is
typically.
원문 의미: something that is involving the dot
product of these 둘.
원문 의미: 그래서 you typically have the cosine
similarity.
원문 의미: The cosine similarity is 그냥 dot
product.
원문 의미: over the norm of each embedding.
그래서 which is 기본적으로 a dot product.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why we care about the
dot product.
그리고 here we 보다, great, it's a function.
원문 의미: of the relative distance between
the 둘.
그래서 in particular, again, if you 기억하다.
your trigonometry 수업, cosine of 0 is 1.
원문 의미: 그리고 the higher this 번호, the lower
the value.
of cosine of this 번호.
Of course, it's periodic, 그래서 what I'm
saying.
원문 의미: is not necessarily true.
원문 의미: Past pi, 그냥 goes the other way.
하지만 I guess what I'm trying to say is for
m equal to n,.
you have 기본적으로 a sum of cosine of 0.
원문 의미: 그리고 it is the value at which this
quantity is maximum.
원문 의미: 그래서 when m is equal to n, this
원문 의미: Which means 기본적으로 if you're looking
at the position itself,.
원문 의미: it's the most similar.
기본적으로, it matches our 직관.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 이제 when you plot the values
of the embeddings,.
원문 의미: 이것은 what you obtain.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 here in this graph on the
y-axis,.
원문 의미: I'm 기본적으로 representing all the
embeddings.
원문 의미: for each of the, let's say, 50
positions.
그리고 on the x-axis, it's 기본적으로.
원문 의미: values along a given 벡터 across
several 차원들.
of a 벡터.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 가지다, let's say, the 첫째
row,.
you're looking at the 첫째 or 번호 0
position,.
원문 의미: depending on how you index your 벡터.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're looking at all the
values of the position 0.
원문 의미: embedding.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you 보다 that for low 차원들,.
원문 의미: this value goes up 그리고 down 매우
frequently.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's more high frequency.
그리고 when the 차원 is high, it 기본적으로.
원문 의미: takes a lot of time for the value
to go up 그리고 down.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 more low frequency.
원문 의미: 그래서 this relates to this omega i
that I mentioned, this omega i.
원문 의미: 그래서 omega i is 매우 high for low
values of i,.
원문 의미: which is the 차원.
그리고 it's 매우 low for high values of i.
그래서 this 기본적으로 그냥 determines.
원문 의미: how quickly your cosine 그리고 sine
기본적으로 vary.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 이것은 what the original authors have
tried.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 what they said, what
they.
원문 의미: noted was that using these methods.
원문 의미: leads to comparable results
compared to the learned 하나.
원문 의미: 하지만 here we have a big advantage,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 it can extend to any 시퀀스
length, not 그냥.
원문 의미: a 시퀀스 length that you saw at 학습
time.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 하나 of the reasons why this
may be입니다.
원문 의미: something that is preferable.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, this is the 직관 그리고 this.
원문 의미: is what the authors chose.
이제, fast forward to 2025.
원문 의미: I guess you may ask me, are we
still using that?
그리고 the 답 is kind of.
그래서 we're still using this 아이디어 of we 원하다
far—
원문 의미: I guess, 토큰들 to be less similar
than closer 토큰들.
원문 의미: 하지만 we're not injecting the
embedding like they did.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 why.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 if you 기억하다, what you care
about.
원문 의미: is determining how similar 토큰들.
원문 의미: are in the self-attention
computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 where does the self-attention
원문 의미: happen?
원문 의미: In the attention layer.
원문 의미: 하지만 here, what did I say?
원문 의미: I said, let's 컴퓨트 these embeddings.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's add them here.
하지만 실제로 what we 원하다 is to reflect this
similarity.
원문 의미: in the attention layer.
Do you have a 문제?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this 첫째 method, yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, is it added to the
input feature.
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: Yes, 그냥 add.
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah.
하지만 the 문제 is, we mostly 원하다 these,.
원문 의미: I guess, 직관 to hold true in the
multi-head attention.
원문 의미: layer.
이것은 하나 of the reasons why입니다.
원문 의미: people have tried 다른 variations,
그리고 in particular.
원문 의미: have these position embeddings
intervene directly.
원문 의미: in the attention layer, as opposed
to the input.
왜냐하면 기본적으로 when you do it at the input—
원문 의미: 그냥 here, fair, OK—
it's ~할 예정입니다 to be roughly something
that.
is ~할 예정입니다 to go into this attention
layer,.
하지만 it's kind of indirect.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we 원하다 is to directly do
something about the attention.
원문 의미: formula that would, I guess,
reflect.
원문 의미: the fact that we 원하다 close 토큰들 to
be more similar,.
원문 의미: compared to further 토큰들.
그리고 the way we do that is, if you 기억하다,.
원문 의미: the self-attention layer is 기본적으로
the softmax of qk.
원문 의미: transpose over square root of d
times v.
그래서 what we 원하다 is to add a little
something.
원문 의미: inside that softmax, which is
기본적으로.
원문 의미: where you quantify how similar a 토큰
is to another 토큰.
원문 의미: You 원하다 to add a little something.
원문 의미: to reflect the fact that some 토큰들,.
원문 의미: they're supposed to be more similar
compared to that 토큰,.
원문 의미: compared to others.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a few methods that have
tried.
원문 의미: to have some variation of that.
원문 의미: 그래서 for those of us who 알다 the T5
paper, what we're.
~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a little bit later, they.
원문 의미: have tried these relative position
bias.
원문 의미: by learning the bias term, which is
in the formula above.
원문 의미: 그래서 what they did was, let's
suppose.
원문 의미: you have a given distance between
the positions m 그리고 n.
원문 의미: 그래서 their 아이디어 was, let's 배우다 that.
원문 의미: Let's 기본적으로 bucketize all m minus n
into some buckets.
그리고 let's 그냥 have the 모델 배우다.
원문 의미: these quantities that are 그다음 ~할
예정입니다.
원문 의미: to be injected into softmax.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, does that pose a 문제.
원문 의미: that the bias is here with respect.
원문 의미: to the 확률 at the end?
왜냐하면 it has to sum to 1.
원문 의미: Well, you can do whatever you 원하다
inside the softmax,.
왜냐하면 the softmax is ~할 예정입니다 to normalize
it anyways.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of the bias as
being something that is maybe.
원문 의미: more negative for things that are
far apart, compared.
원문 의미: to things that are closer together.
그래서 T5 says, let's 배우다 them.
원문 의미: We have another message from, I
guess, this "학습하다 Short,.
원문 의미: Test Long" paper, which introduced
this method called.
원문 의미: ALiBi.
원문 의미: ALiBi stands for Attention with
linear bias, I believe.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they did was, say instead.
원문 의미: of learning those biases, let's
실제로.
원문 의미: have a deterministic formula,
which.
원문 의미: is as a function of the relative
difference between those 둘.
원문 의미: positions.
원문 의미: 그리고 they said that.
원문 의미: 그래서 they had some results.
원문 의미: 그래서 all these papers, they always
compare based on 하나 another.
to 보다 which 하나 is, I guess, more
performant.
하지만 the reality is is that in today's
모델들,.
원문 의미: most 모델들 실제로 사용하다 another kind of
position embedding.
원문 의미: method.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 it 이제.
원문 의미: 그래서 this method relies on rotating.
원문 의미: the query 그리고 the key 벡터 by some
angle.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess you can 생각하다 of it as,
you have your query,.
원문 의미: you have your key, let's suppose in
a 2D space.
그래서 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is rotate
your query.
원문 의미: by some angle that is a function of
its position.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to rotate the
key 벡터 by some angle that is.
원문 의미: a function of its position n.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess how do you do that, by
the way?
원문 의미: I wasn't supposed to 보여주다 this
thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have a 벡터, by
the way.
그리고 you 원하다 to rotate that 벡터,.
왜냐하면 I had the 답 on the 슬라이드.
원문 의미: 하지만 how would you go about this, I
guess,.
원문 의미: for people who 그냥 원하다 to talk about
this with 직관?
원문 의미: 그래서 who here has done, I don't 알다,
rotations in space?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그것은 correct, yeah.입니다.
원문 의미: 행렬 multiplication.
그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to 사용하다 a quantity
that's.
원문 의미: called rotation 행렬.
원문 의미: 그리고 the rotation 행렬 is expressed as
follows.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 a 2 by 2 행렬 in the 2D plane
that has.
원문 의미: cosine of this angle, minus sine of
this angle,.
원문 의미: sine of this angle, cosine of this
angle.
원문 의미: I'm looking at the time.
It's quite 간단한 to 그냥 보여주다 that it works,.
원문 의미: 하지만 we may run out of time.
Do you 원하다 me to quickly 보여주다 you.
원문 의미: that it's indeed a way to rotate
the 벡터?
OK.
그래서 here as a reminder what we're trying
to 보여주다 is that we can.
사용하다 a 행렬 multiplication to rotate a 벡터 in
2D space.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose we have the
following 벡터.
원문 의미: 그것은 something that you can quantify
with 둘 차원들,입니다.
let's say x 그리고 y.
원문 의미: You can express your 벡터 in 2D space
with this.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess this, if you note, are
the norm of the 벡터,.
원문 의미: 그리고 phi, the angle with respect to
the x-axis.
원문 의미: You can also write v as R with 벡터
cosine.
원문 의미: of phi 그리고 sine of phi.
원문 의미: Right?
원문 의미: 그래서 if you multiply the rotation
행렬.
원문 의미: with this phi, what you're ~할 예정입니다
to obtain.
원문 의미: is some multiplication of cosine
minus sine, sine 그리고 cosine.
원문 의미: of this 그리고 that.
원문 의미: 그리고 I will leave this exercise for
you.
원문 의미: 하지만 you can 보여주다 that rotation
times this v.
원문 의미: can be expressed as R of cosine of
theta plus phi,.
원문 의미: 그리고 sine of theta plus phi.
이것은 a quick proof.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'll 그냥 leave you the
multiplication of the rotation.
행렬 그리고 v. 하지만 you will obtain.
원문 의미: these trigonometric identities that
will, I guess,.
원문 의미: lead you to this formula.
원문 의미: This 기본적으로 shows that if you
multiply.
this 행렬 그리고 this 벡터, you're 기본적으로
rotating.
원문 의미: the 벡터 by this angle.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, why do you 원하다 to do this?
It's a great 문제.
It's my 다음 슬라이드.
이것은 그냥 a little intro.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess here, 그냥 ~할 예정입니다 back
to this method, what.
we 원하다 to do is to quantify the similarity
between 토큰들,.
원문 의미: 그리고 have close 토큰들 be more similar
compared.
원문 의미: to 토큰들 that are more afar.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 that we had with the
previous methods was—
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 첫째 method, this learned
embedding,.
원문 의미: you always had this overfitting
issue.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 기본적으로 when you 배우다 these
biases,.
원문 의미: it always depends on which 학습 set
you have.
원문 의미: 그래서 maybe your 데이터셋 is in a way
that, let's say,.
원문 의미: 토큰들 that are close are similar, 하지만
in a 다른 way.
원문 의미: compared to what you 보다 at 추론 time.
원문 의미: 그리고 this ALiBi method, it didn't
have that learnable component,.
하지만 it was quite restrictive, 왜냐하면 it's.
원문 의미: a 매우 간단한 formula 후에 all, 그냥 the
relative difference.
between n 그리고 m.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess people have tried 다른
ways of coming up.
원문 의미: with something that tells you that,
I guess, an embedding that.
원문 의미: reflects the fact that you 원하다
further positions to be less.
원문 의미: similar than closer ones.
그래서 in this method, we're ~할 예정입니다 back.
원문 의미: to the sine 그리고 cosine world from
what.
원문 의미: the author had proposed.
원문 의미: 그리고 생각하다 about similarity from the
lens.
원문 의미: of cosine 그리고 sine functions.
이것은 a little intro.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 their method is called RoPE.
그래서 I'm not sure if you've heard of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 it stands for Rotary Position
embeddings.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that this method—
그래서.
원문 의미: why do we care about this method?
원문 의미: 그래서 this method has 둘 great things.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 하나 is that if you rotate
the query 그리고 the key,.
원문 의미: you will end up with a quantity
that.
원문 의미: will be a function of the relative
distance.
원문 의미: between the 둘.
그것은 ~할 예정입니다 to be 매우 nice, 그리고 that's입니다.
원문 의미: why I wrote this thing on the
blackboard.
원문 의미: Not sure if you can 보다, by the
way,.
원문 의미: 하지만 we won't have time to go into
the mathematical detail.
원문 의미: 하지만 if you 원하다 to 그냥 express these
things at home,.
이것은 그냥 the foundation.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 in particular, if you 기억하다
your attention formula,.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have query times key
transpose.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you rotate the query by an
angle m.
그리고 the key by an angle n, what you're ~할
예정입니다 to end up.
원문 의미: is a formula that has the rotation
행렬 of angle theta.
그리고, I guess, n minus m.
그리고 이것은 great 왜냐하면 this is입니다.
원문 의미: a function of the relative distance
between these 둘.
원문 의미: positions.
원문 의미: OK, 그래서 why do I talk about this in
detail?
원문 의미: Well, it turns out that most 모델들
these days,.
they 사용하다 RoPE, which is why it's 중요한.
원문 의미: 그리고 I would say another thing, it's
maybe a little bit hard.
원문 의미: to get the 직관 as to why that works.
원문 의미: 하지만 hopefully, the explanation that
I gave regarding the sine.
원문 의미: 그리고 cosine at the 매우 beginning can
help you 그냥.
원문 의미: build that 직관.
원문 의미: 그리고 speaking of that, it turns out.
원문 의미: that the upper bound of the
attention 가중치 given.
원문 의미: by the query 그리고 the key is such
that we.
원문 의미: observe a long-term decay.
원문 의미: Meaning that as n minus m is
large,.
원문 의미: we do 보다 the upper bound that gets
smaller 그리고 smaller.
원문 의미: Well, you 보다 these little
oscillations,.
원문 의미: it's not perfect either.
원문 의미: 하지만 we do have some mathematical,.
원문 의미: I guess, results as to 그냥 the upper
bounds.
원문 의미: decaying over the long-term.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 on this?
원문 의미: Yeah, yeah.
원문 의미: Exactly, yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is the relative
distance.
원문 의미: is captured in the rotation 행렬—
원문 의미: 그리고 yes, yes.
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
It's a great 문제.
그래서 the 문제 is, what is theta?
그래서 theta is 실제로 fixed.
원문 의미: 그래서 do you 기억하다 this omega that I
talked about here?
원문 의미: Here.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 some function of i 그리고 d.
원문 의미: I 실제로 pass it quite quickly.
원문 의미: 하지만 what I showed you is in the 2D
space.
하지만 here we're in a d-dimensional space,.
원문 의미: which is greater than 2.
그래서 I glossed it 매우 quickly.
원문 의미: 하지만 the way you extend this method
is by having these 2D.
원문 의미: space by block.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the theta is a function of
typically something.
원문 의미: that you fix, 하지만 a function of i,
which is the 차원.
It's 기본적으로 between 1 그리고 d over 2.
It's a function of that, 그리고 it's a
function of d as well.
원문 의미: You will 보다 this theta as being
roughly equal to omega i, 그냥.
원문 의미: this 하나, more or less, more or
less.
원문 의미: Sorry?
Oh, 그래서 the 문제 is, 그래서 that it has the 같은
차원.
원문 의미: as the latent 차원?
원문 의미: 그래서, well, here you have a product
of 행렬들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to have the 차원들 match.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess your 답— yeah.
이해되나요?
I'll 가지다 that as a yes.
그래서 I spent a bunch of time on this,.
왜냐하면 I 생각하다 this is 실제로 quite 중요한.
A lot of 모델들 사용하다 this.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, I guess the 직관 is not
super obvious.
원문 의미: 그래서 I hope this was helpful.
원문 의미: 그래서 this was position embeddings.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is about, how do
you obtain this curve?
이것은 실제로 a curve that I believe입니다.
원문 의미: is shown mathematically.
그래서 it's kind of complicated.
원문 의미: We're not ~할 예정입니다 to write down
the formula.
하지만 if you're interested, 그래서 in this
paper,.
원문 의미: in the RoFormer paper, there's an
appendix.
원문 의미: where they 보여주다 mathematically that
it is.
원문 의미: upper bounded by some quantity.
그리고 이것은 what this is showing.입니다.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 문제.
좋습니다.
그래서, position embeddings is 하나 부분.
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머 that has changed a
little bit.
원문 의미: 그리고 we've seen how that changed,
그리고 why.
그래서 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 another
component.
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머 that has also a little
bit changed.
원문 의미: 그리고 that component is the layer
정규화.
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, the 트랜스포머 architecture,.
원문 의미: which is composed, again, of
encoder,.
원문 의미: decoder, 그리고 그다음 you have the
components inside.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have these boxes that say
add 그리고 norm.
원문 의미: 그래서 what do they mean?
그래서 기본적으로, here, what we do is we 가지다 the
input, as well as.
원문 의미: the output of this sublayer.
원문 의미: We add them together, 그리고 그다음 we
normalize.
원문 의미: 이것은 a little trick that the authors
do.입니다.
그리고 it is shown in practice to improve
convergence 그리고 그냥.
원문 의미: 만들다 the convergence be quicker.
아이디어는 as follows—입니다.
원문 의미: if you have a 벡터, sometimes the
components of the 벡터.
원문 의미: can be super large, sometimes they
can be super small.
원문 의미: The 아이디어 here is to normalize the
components of your 벡터.
원문 의미: within some range, some normalized
range.
그래서 the way you're ~할 예정입니다 to do that is
you're.
~할 예정입니다 to 가지다 your 벡터, 그리고 그다음 subtract
it.
원문 의미: by the computed mean, which is
기본적으로.
원문 의미: the sum of its components, 그리고
normalize it by 기본적으로.
원문 의미: its standard deviation.
그리고 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is you're.
~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 둘 quantities—
원문 의미: 하나, gamma, which is ~할 예정입니다 to be
the rescaling factor,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 beta, which is another term
as well that you 배우다.
그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to let these 둘
quantities be.
원문 의미: learned by your 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 in practice, as I
mentioned, 그래서 what this does.
원문 의미: is it helps with 학습 stability.
원문 의미: 그리고 with convergence time.
원문 의미: 그래서 this was a technique that was
used in the original 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: paper.
원문 의미: I 그냥 원하다 to call out that there
has.
원문 의미: been some changes since 그다음.
원문 의미: 그래서 we went from normalizing the
input.
원문 의미: plus the output of the sublayer, to
having a sum of the input.
원문 의미: 그리고 the sublayer of the normalized
input.
원문 의미: 그래서 in other words, what we've
done.
원문 의미: is to change where the 정규화 is
located.
원문 의미: 그래서 here in the 트랜스포머 paper,.
원문 의미: it was what we 이제 call a post-norm
version.
원문 의미: 그리고 nowadays, we 사용하다 a pre-norm
version,.
원문 의미: which 기본적으로 consists of having the
LayerNorm right.
원문 의미: 전에 the 벡터 goes into the sublayer.
원문 의미: 그리고 sublayer here can be either the
attention layer or the FFN.
원문 의미: 하지만 not only that, there is also
another change.
원문 의미: 그래서 nowadays, people, they do not
사용하다 LayerNorm.
원문 의미: They 사용하다 something else called
RMSNorm—
원문 의미: RMS, Root Mean Square, 정규화,.
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 a variation of what
you've seen 전에.
원문 의미: 그래서 instead of computing this,
기본적으로 what people do.
원문 의미: is they 그냥 normalize x by the root.
원문 의미: mean square of the components of
x,.
원문 의미: 그리고 they 배우다 gamma, only gamma.
원문 의미: 그래서 why do they do that?
원문 의미: 기본적으로, they 보여주다 that the
convergence properties,.
원문 의미: they're 기본적으로 comparable.
원문 의미: 하지만 here you have fewer 파라미터들 to
배우다.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 quicker.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Good 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what is the 직관
behind normalizing?
그래서 the 직관 is that, if you 보다 at your 모델,.
원문 의미: you have several layers.
원문 의미: In some layers your 벡터—
원문 의미: your activation, to be more
precise—
원문 의미: 그래서 do you 알다 the 벡터 that you.
원문 의미: 보다 that goes from here to here is
기본적으로 called activation.
원문 의미: Sometimes the activation has
extreme values.
in 하나 부분 of its component, sometimes in
another 부분.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 모델 is typically having.
원문 의미: trouble in learning the 가중치 in each
of these layers.
원문 의미: if these activations, they vary too
much.
원문 의미: 아이디어는 to bring the values of the
components입니다.
원문 의미: of the activation to some range
that is not.
원문 의미: too far off in some direction.
그래서 in 경우 you're interested, there.
원문 의미: is this key word, internal
covariate shift,.
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 the term that is
given to the phenomenon.
원문 의미: that I'm describing here.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, that's the 직관.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Oh, great, great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 문제 is, what is the difference
between this.
그리고 batch 정규화?
그래서 batch 정규화 is 정규화.
원문 의미: across the other 차원, which.
원문 의미: is the 차원 of the batch.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose you have a bunch
of 벡터들.
원문 의미: What you do is you normalize each
component with respect.
원문 의미: to all the other components for the
같은 차원,.
하지만 of the other 벡터들.
그래서 you can 생각하다 of it as 그냥 another way
of normalizing.
원문 의미: 하지만 that being said, when it comes.
to these 트랜스포머-based 모델들,.
원문 의미: typically people 사용하다 LayerNorm,
probably.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 empirically it works better.
원문 의미: 하지만 also 왜냐하면 BatchNorm, you're.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 also dependent on the batch.
그리고 it can 소개하다, I guess, differences
between 학습.
그리고 그다음 추론.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's 기본적으로 the reason why.
원문 의미: Cool, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 we've seen position embeddings.
We've seen layer 정규화.
그래서 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a 셋째 중요한
component.
원문 의미: of the 트랜스포머, which is the
attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 in particular, I guess there is
something.
I've not 정말 emphasized.
원문 의미: 하지만 when you do self-attention,
you're.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 letting every 토큰 interact
with all other 토큰들.
그래서 when you 보다 at, let's, say a 행렬.
원문 의미: that shows all the interactions,
그래서 you.
원문 의미: have n, the 시퀀스 length.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 시퀀스 length, you 기본적으로.
원문 의미: have o of n squared complexity,
which is a lot, especially.
원문 의미: as n grows longer.
원문 의미: 그래서 people have tried to
approximate this o of n squared.
원문 의미: into something that is a little bit
more tractable,.
원문 의미: 하지만 does not lose the performance.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is this paper in 2020
that came out, "LongFormer.".
원문 의미: 그래서 what it did was 그냥 try 다른
versions.
원문 의미: of the attention by restricting the
window at which it operates.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, instead of letting each
토큰 interact with everyone,.
원문 의미: each 토큰 only interacts with its
neighborhood.
원문 의미: Yeah.
Oh, again, a great 문제.
그래서 문제 is, do you do that 후에 the attention
행렬.
원문 의미: computation?
원문 의미: You mean the softmax, right,
softmax?
원문 의미: 그래서 you raise a great 포인트, which.
원문 의미: is, if you do the softmax of
everything,.
원문 의미: why would you do this?
그래서 in practice there is a bunch of
implementations.
원문 의미: that does a clever—
그래서 it's called tiling—
원문 의미: a bunch of clever operations that.
원문 의미: do not involve this huge 행렬
operation.
원문 의미: that you 보다 in the softmax.
원문 의미: Again, I guess, like against the
softmax of qk transpose over d.
원문 의미: You're not ~할 예정입니다 to 컴퓨트 the
whole thing.
원문 의미: You're ~할 예정입니다 to have some
cleverness in how.
원문 의미: you 컴퓨트 that, 기본적으로.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is, can it be
something that's.
원문 의미: comparable to convolutions?
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in a 둘째.
원문 의미: 하지만 you have some similarities with
the vision world.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in a 둘째.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 nowadays when you have local
attention like this, like this,.
원문 의미: people 사용하다 the term sliding window
attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 when they 사용하다 that term, they
mean.
원문 의미: this, which is 기본적으로 그냥 restricting
the attention.
to neighboring 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 nowadays what people do is in
some layers.
원문 의미: they will have local attention.
원문 의미: In some others, they will have
global attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 they interleave these layers.
원문 의미: 그래서 depending on the 모델, they
typically.
원문 의미: try 다른 combinations.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's not a set recipe.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's typically something that
is used nowadays.
원문 의미: 그래서 the window here, I mean, for,
illustrative, purposes,.
원문 의미: the window is super small in my
illustration.
원문 의미: 하지만 I guess nowadays with the 시퀀스
lengths.
원문 의미: that can be 매우 big, you can 생각하다 of
this window as being,.
원문 의미: o of several, thousands.
그리고 그냥 to 주다 you another 예시.
원문 의미: 그래서 back to the convolution
comparison that you mentioned.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some architectures.
그리고 here I'm ~할 예정입니다 to 가지다 the 예시 of a
mistral that.
원문 의미: has these sliding window attention
at every layer.
하지만 그다음 when you 생각하다 about it,.
원문 의미: the 토큰 here can attend up to the 토큰
here,.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the 토큰 here can attend up.
원문 의미: to the 토큰 here, et cetera, et
cetera.
그래서 I guess, if you 생각하다 about it,.
it's similar to the 아이디어 of the receptive.
원문 의미: field in computer vision.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if you're familiar
or from the computer.
원문 의미: vision world.
원문 의미: 하지만 if you are, what this means is
그냥 taking 하나 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 trying to 생각하다 what other 토큰들
has.
원문 의미: this 토큰 effectively interacted
with,.
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 the 문제 that people
also sometimes ask.
원문 의미: When they do convolution, they're.
원문 의미: like, OK, 그래서 this value, what are
the values.
did it 실제로 보다?
원문 의미: 그래서 you can also 생각하다 it this way.
OK, 그래서 첫째 variation is, instead.
원문 의미: of doing the full n by n
attention,.
원문 의미: people sometimes do local
attention.
원문 의미: The 둘째 variation that is orthogonal
to all of this.
원문 의미: is to not have 하나 projection 행렬 per
head,.
원문 의미: 하지만 to share projection 행렬들 across
heads.
원문 의미: 그래서 here the 아이디어 is you have,
let's say, h heads.
아이디어는 you're ~할 예정입니다 to have some 번호 of
projection입니다.
원문 의미: 행렬들 for the query.
하지만 그다음 what you're ~할 예정입니다 to do is.
원문 의미: to group the projection 행렬들 for the
key 그리고 the value.
원문 의미: that you're ~할 예정입니다 to share
across several heads.
원문 의미: 이제 you may ask, why do you share
projection 행렬들.
원문 의미: for the keys 그리고 the values, 하지만
not for the queries?
원문 의미: Is this the 문제 that you're
wondering?
원문 의미: Well here, I guess, people do
things to 그냥 try out.
원문 의미: if something works or not.
원문 의미: I guess here you can intuitively
생각하다.
원문 의미: that the query is 기본적으로 wondering
if something.
원문 의미: is similar to another thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess you can ask yourself
this 문제 in 다른 ways.
원문 의미: 그래서 it may 만들다 sense to keep that
diversity.
원문 의미: 하지만 하나 of the core reasons why we
choose to group projection.
원문 의미: 행렬들 for the keys 그리고 the values.
원문 의미: 그리고 not the query is 왜냐하면, when you
decode,.
원문 의미: you perform attention between the
current word 그리고 all.
원문 의미: the words 전에.
원문 의미: 그래서 in other words, every time you
generate a new word,.
원문 의미: you're ~할 예정입니다 to attend that word
to all the words 전에.
원문 의미: 그래서 the keys 그리고 the values,
they're ~할 예정입니다 to come up a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 every time you 원하다 to decode
something,.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to attend to all other
things, again 그리고 again.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 in, I 생각하다,.
원문 의미: 다음, 강의 there's something called.
원문 의미: the KV cache, which 기본적으로 saves the
values of the keys.
원문 의미: 그리고 values.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 thing that we 원하다 is for
that cache.
원문 의미: to not become too big.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you share projection 행렬들
across heads,.
원문 의미: 그냥 allows you to save a little bit
of space,.
원문 의미: a little bit of memory.
원문 의미: 그것은 the why.입니다.
원문 의미: Does that roughly 만들다 sense?
네, 좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 speaking of that, there are
some variations as to, I guess,.
원문 의미: 그냥 how many projection 행렬들 to
share.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the extreme 예시 where.
원문 의미: all h heads, they all share the 같은
projection.
행렬들 for v 그리고 k.
원문 의미: 그리고 in that 경우, this method is
called.
원문 의미: MQA, Multi-query Attention.
원문 의미: You have the in-between 경우 where
you share g,.
where g is the 번호 of groups g projection
행렬들 for v.
그리고 k.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have groups of size,
let's say, h over g.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나 is called Group query
Attention, GQA.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have the 경우 that you
are 매우 familiar.
원문 의미: with from the 트랜스포머, which is.
원문 의미: every head has its own query
projection, key projection,.
원문 의미: 그리고 value projection 행렬들.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 the standard, multi-head
attention.입니다.
좋습니다.
그래서 I'm, ~할 예정입니다 to 그냥 가지다 a pause to 보다
if what I mentioned.
원문 의미: makes sense.
저는 soon transition it to Shervine.할 것입니다.
하지만 전에 I do, I 그냥 원하다 to 만들다 sure that
what I discussed.
원문 의미: is making sense, roughly.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we apply this.
원문 의미: to self-attention 그리고 cross-
attention?
I don't 원하다 to spoil the 보여주다.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about something
later on.
하지만 where is my trans?
그래서 if you 가지다 a 보다 at the 트랜스포머
architecture,.
원문 의미: 우리는 보다 soon that what we care about
most할 것입니다.
is what is in the decoder, 왜냐하면 we 실제로.
원문 의미: forego of the encoder in nowadays'
모델들.
원문 의미: We have not seen this yet, 하지만 I'm
그냥 telling you.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 this typically comes into
play.
원문 의미: for the masked self-attention in
the decoder.
원문 의미: 하지만 this technique can be applied
in all attention layers.
하지만 I guess what I'm telling you is.
원문 의미: modern LLMs, their decoder only 모델들
which 기본적으로 only.
원문 의미: have the decoder 부분 of the 트랜스포머.
우리는 보다 this in a 둘째, which할 것입니다.
원문 의미: is the masked self-attention.
그래서 I'm not ~할 예정입니다 to say too much 왜냐하면
Shervine.
is ~할 예정입니다 to cover that.
하지만 yeah, 그냥 a quick peek of what we're ~할
예정입니다 to 보다.
원문 의미: Cool, yeah.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when do you 알다 which
하나 you should 사용하다?
원문 의미: I would say the choice is always
driven by a few factors.
원문 의미: 하나 is how well it performs.
원문 의미: 둘째 is how much do you care about
things like latency costs.
그리고 그래서 it 정말 depends how big is your 모델,.
원문 의미: how much you 원하다 to save on, let's
say, 컴퓨트,.
원문 의미: how is your input length, for
instance.
원문 의미: if you have a shorter input length.
그래서 here what we 원하다 to do is to avoid.
원문 의미: having to do all these things for
the whole o of n squared.
원문 의미: thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 I guess all of these come into
play.
그래서 I would say it's not straightforward
as.
원문 의미: to what the 답 should be.
하지만 I would say a lot of recent 모델들,.
원문 의미: they tend to share projection 행렬들.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, I would say GQA is
what you would 보다.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's not necessarily the 경우 for
all 모델들.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: We're running out of time.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to have Shervine here for
the 둘째 부분.
감사합니다.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: Thank you, Afshine.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to continue this
강의 with some deeper dive.
원문 의미: into the kinds of 모델들 that we have.
원문 의미: in the 트랜스포머 landscape.
그리고 그다음 we're ~할 예정입니다 to do a deep dive.
원문 의미: into 하나 specific architecture that.
원문 의미: is 매우 useful for classification
settings.
그래서 첫째, we're ~할 예정입니다 to come back to the
architecture.
원문 의미: that we saw together 지난 time, 그래서.
원문 의미: this traditional encoder/decoder
architecture.
원문 의미: where you have both components.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you have the original 트랜스포머
paper from 2017.
원문 의미: that had this architecture.
원문 의미: 하지만 also later on, you 보다 more
architectures.
원문 의미: that built on top of it.
원문 의미: 그래서 here we talk about the T5
family of 모델들.
그래서 T5 is a paper that's an abbreviation
of multiple Ts.
그래서 the 첫째 하나 is transfer, 그리고 그다음 it's
text-to-text,.
트랜스포머.
원문 의미: 이것은 where the T5 naming comes
from.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 it's derived into multiple
versions.
원문 의미: 그래서 the T5 is like the vanilla
paper.
그리고 그다음 it had mT5.
원문 의미: m stands for multilingual where
there.
원문 의미: was some more work on the 데이터 it
was 학습된 on,.
원문 의미: as well as the 어휘집 that it was
computed over.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have ByT5, which is
some.
원문 의미: of tokenizer-free method of all of
this where you forego.
원문 의미: of the fact of tokenizing.
원문 의미: 그리고 instead of that, you 기본적으로.
원문 의미: operate at the byte level.
그래서 By is like byte.
그리고 기본적으로, you have a 어휘집 size.
원문 의미: 그것은 much smaller.입니다.
그래서 instead of having an o of 30k,.
원문 의미: you have 2 to the power of 8.
그래서 a byte is 8 bits.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you can represent every
character into bytes.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what they do.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 그다음 하나 thing I 원하다 to mention.
원문 의미: regarding the T5 family is that the
objective function changes.
원문 의미: a bit with what the original 트랜스포머
did.
그래서 the original 트랜스포머 did 다음 토큰 예측.
원문 의미: for the 학습 task.
원문 의미: 하지만 the T5 family, what they did
is.
원문 의미: that they operated on the so-called
span corruption task.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 you would have your
sentence.
원문 의미: as an input to the encoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 instead of putting everything
to the encoder,.
원문 의미: you would leave blanks.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 what we call span
corruption.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the span corruption could
be.
하나 or multiple 토큰들 missing.
그래서 if I 원하다 to 주다 an 예시, 그래서 for 예시,.
원문 의미: my teddy bear is cute 그리고 reading.
원문 의미: 그래서 you could have my teddy bear
span corrupted, 그리고 is reading.
원문 의미: 그래서 that could be 하나 potential
encoder input.
그리고 그다음 you could have up to n—
원문 의미: I mean, n is the parameterization.
원문 의미: of the 번호 of spans that are
corrupted.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would have n such 토큰들 here.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the T5 families calls them
sentinel 토큰들.
그래서 if you 보다 sentinel 토큰들, they.
원문 의미: represent a span of corrupted 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have them here in the
encoder.
그리고 그다음 the decoder's work is to find.
원문 의미: each of these spans in series.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 시작하다 with a 토큰 that
denotes.
원문 의미: the 첫째 corrupted span.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 시작하다 the decoding
process.
원문 의미: until it hits a prediction that
predicts the 다음 sentinel 토큰.
원문 의미: up to the n plus 1, 1, where the
토큰들 that are decoded.
원문 의미: between 둘 consecutive sentinel 토큰들.
원문 의미: corresponds to the corrupted spans
that are recovered.
그래서 these parentheses is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: a shift from the 다음 토큰 예측 objective
function.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, can you elaborate
with the decoding.
원문 의미: process?
원문 의미: 그래서 what you said regarding the
reconstruction is exactly right.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have sentinel 토큰들 that
denote some missing text.
원문 의미: 그래서 what you 원하다 to decode is that
missing text.
원문 의미: 그래서 the decoder output will be
exactly.
원문 의미: like each span reconstructed.
그리고 그다음 if you 원하다 to 알다 how 학습 works,.
원문 의미: you do a teacher-forcing mechanism.
원문 의미: where you input everything in the
decoder,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 try to reconstruct
everything at once.
원문 의미: 그래서 any other 문제들?
좋습니다.
그리고 그다음 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
another 수업.
원문 의미: of 트랜스포머 where 기본적으로 you have this
encoder/decoder.
원문 의미: structure, where you 그냥 forget
about the decoder 그리고 그다음 그냥.
원문 의미: deal with the encoder.
원문 의미: 그래서 you might tell me, OK, hey, you
cannot do generation with.
원문 의미: this.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 I would respond to you,
yes, that's exactly the 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 it has encoder representations.
원문 의미: that can be used for tasks that
might be more.
원문 의미: geared towards classification.
원문 의미: 그래서 sentiment extraction, 토큰
classification,.
원문 의미: all of these things that used to be
done with specific language.
원문 의미: 모델들, they can be done with the
encoder.
부분 of the 트랜스포머.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to dive deeper a bit
later.
원문 의미: into a three-key encoder only 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 BERT, which is like the central
하나,.
원문 의미: I would say in this landscape, 그리고
그다음.
원문 의미: 둘 other architectures, DistilBERT
그리고 RoBERTa,.
원문 의미: that are investigating on axis of
improvements.
그래서 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be good to 보다.
그래서 OK, great.
그리고 그다음 there is 하나 지난 수업.
그래서 as Afshine 그냥 mentioned, 둘 days.
원문 의미: LLMs, they remove the encoder 부분
altogether.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 when you have no encoder,.
원문 의미: you don't have your encoder
embeddings.
원문 의미: at the end of your stacked
encoders.
원문 의미: that could be fed to the cross-
attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 this module disappears
altogether.
원문 의미: 그래서 each decoder that is stacked
그냥.
원문 의미: has masked self-attention 그리고 an
FFN as 부분 of it.
원문 의미: 그리고 yeah, that's 기본적으로 something.
원문 의미: that has caught up since 그다음.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 when you 보다 at the popularity
of each.
원문 의미: of these 모델들, 그래서 you used to have.
원문 의미: these 트랜스포머-like architecture that
was popular.
원문 의미: towards the beginning, where the
main hypothesis was.
원문 의미: that the encoder 부분 is 매우 useful
for getting.
원문 의미: to the decoder's representation.
원문 의미: 하지만 as time went, people realized.
원문 의미: that your 컴퓨트 budget could be best
invested.
원문 의미: in the decoder only.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there has been more
investment into the kind.
원문 의미: of tasks that is, I would say,
easiest to scale up.
원문 의미: 그리고 generalize— next-word
prediction—
원문 의미: as opposed to the task I 그냥
mentioned for T5,.
원문 의미: which might be more bespoke.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to corrupt things.
그래서 it's more complex.
원문 의미: Whereas next-word prediction is, I
would say,.
원문 의미: the simplest thing you can do.
그리고 it proved to be wonders 그리고 well-
aligned.
원문 의미: with the task of being a helpful
kind of chatbot,.
원문 의미: which is like 둘 days' applications
mainly.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the decoder-only
architectures— 그래서 I'm not.
~할 예정입니다 to talk about them 오늘.
하지만 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be the central 부분 of
the 다음 lectures.
원문 의미: when we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
LLMs more 그리고 more.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 we can dive deep, as
promised,.
원문 의미: into encoder-only architectures 그리고
with BERT.
그래서 첫째 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 by seeing
what does BERT mean.
원문 의미: 그래서 BERT, it's an acronym that
denotes Bidirectional encoder.
원문 의미: Representations from 트랜스포머.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 together how.
원문 의미: does each section of this acronym,
what does it.
원문 의미: correspond to?
그래서 let's 그냥 시작하다 with the encoder 부분,.
원문 의미: which is the easiest to grasp.
그래서 as we said, we 그냥 dropped the decoder.
그래서 this encoder from 트랜스포머 is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: exactly what it means.
원문 의미: 이제 on the other 부분, 그래서 why do we
talk about bidirectionality?
그래서 it's a way, 그래서 the paper's 결과 is
remarkable,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 we are able from a given
input.
원문 의미: to get output representations that
have attended to everything.
원문 의미: for each 토큰.
그리고 이것은 the 경우.입니다.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 since we only have the
encoder,.
원문 의미: we have this self-attention layer.
원문 의미: that truly attends to every other
토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 in contrast with the masked
self-attention입니다.
원문 의미: that you have where we said that
the mask is making the attention.
원문 의미: mechanism causal.
원문 의미: 그래서 every 토큰 can attend to itself
그리고 to the 토큰들.
전에 it.
원문 의미: 그리고 this is, by the way, something.
원문 의미: that the authors discuss a lot in
the paper,.
원문 의미: saying that GPT came out, GPT
they're not truly bidirectional.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 these encodings that can be
used for classification.
원문 의미: tasks, they truly are.
질문 있나요?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yep, that's right.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, when you don't have
the mask,.
원문 의미: each 토큰 can attend to each other.
원문 의미: 그것은 exactly right.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the mask is exactly there.
원문 의미: to prevent links from 토큰들 to those
that come 후에 them.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그래서 I 그냥 원하다 to put this paper in 컨텍스트.
원문 의미: 그리고 the field of NLP was booming
back 그다음.
원문 의미: 그래서 you had another landmark paper.
원문 의미: that 같은 year, which was called
ELMo,.
원문 의미: 그래서 embeddings from 언어모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 I would say that the timing of
that paper.
원문 의미: was a bit unfortunate, 왜냐하면 it
truly.
원문 의미: had new insights of also building.
원문 의미: bidirectional representations.
원문 의미: 하지만 it 그냥 turns out that it came
the 같은 year.
원문 의미: as the 트랜스포머, as the kind of 트랜스포머-
based 같은 line.
원문 의미: of work.
그래서 it got a bit masked by it.
원문 의미: 그래서 ELMo, 그냥 to 주다 the main lines,.
원문 의미: it was based on a bidirectional
LSTM.
원문 의미: where you had multiple layers,
each.
원문 의미: stacked on top of each other.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 you were able to build.
원문 의미: a bidirectional representation for
each word,.
원문 의미: thanks to this architecture.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 why didn't it become as
popular as BERT?
원문 의미: It's 왜냐하면 you had the 같은 downsides.
as the previous 모델들, where 기본적으로 it's.
원문 의미: hard to scale 왜냐하면 of this
recurrence.
원문 의미: 그리고 I 생각하다 a lot of you, when you
생각하다 about ELMo 그리고 BERT,.
원문 의미: you don't 생각하다 about these papers
at 첫째,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 they are characters in Sesame
Street.
원문 의미: 그리고 I grew up in a place where I
did not.
원문 의미: 알다 about Sesame Street.
원문 의미: 그래서 for me, ELMo 그리고 BERT is like
paper names.
하지만 it might be what represents to you at
첫째.
원문 의미: 그래서 I thought that was quite funny.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 researchers, they are
generally quite playful.
원문 의미: They try to fit their acronyms into
themes.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 보다 at paper names, you
will get entertained.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 to dive deeper into what I
mentioned.
원문 의미: to be the goal of encoder-only
모델들,.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have your set of 토큰들 as
input.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal here is to perform
tasks.
원문 의미: that might be focused on
projecting.
원문 의미: some representation somewhere, 그래서
typically classification.
원문 의미: tasks.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, the way BERT works is 매우
specific.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 둘 kinds of 토큰들 that
you.
원문 의미: will 보다 are structural here.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 첫째 the CLS 토큰, which
stands for classification.
그리고 it's 기본적으로 a placeholder 토큰.
원문 의미: 그것은 put at the beginning of the 시퀀스
that will 그다음,입니다.
원문 의미: at the end of the whole attention.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 projection 그리고 the whole
encoder mechanism,.
원문 의미: be projected into an embedding that
we can 그다음.
원문 의미: 사용하다 for classification.
원문 의미: 그래서 CLS is 그냥 some kind of
placeholder.
원문 의미: that will carry the bidirectional
information.
원문 의미: of your whole input.
원문 의미: 그리고 another 토큰 that might be useful
to 보다 is this SEP 토큰.
그래서 it's like separator.
그리고 그다음 you will 보다 매우 soon we're.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 the objective
functions that it operates on.
원문 의미: It aims at separating 둘 sentences.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 이것은 the 매우 high level.입니다.
그리고 그다음 그래서 하나 thing that is 매우
interesting.
원문 의미: to 보다 with this 모델 is that you have
this 개념.
원문 의미: of multi-stage 학습.
그래서 you don't 학습하다 the 모델 in 하나 shot.
원문 의미: You do it in multiple stages.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 stage is aimed at being
aligned.
원문 의미: with the task of interest.
그리고 그래서 this is what we call 사전학습.
그리고 this 사전학습, we will 보다 in detail,.
원문 의미: is done with 둘 objective functions
that are respectively.
원문 의미: MLM 그리고 NSP.
원문 의미: 그래서 MLM stands for Masked 언어모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 NSP is the 다음 Sentence
Prediction.
그래서 masked 언어모델, it's a way.
원문 의미: for the 모델 to 배우다 the internal
structure.
원문 의미: of the inputs.
그리고 그다음 NSP, it might be seen as a way.
원문 의미: to 보다 if the ordering of sentences
makes sense.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go a bit deeper into
each,.
하지만 it's a combination of objective
function.
원문 의미: that the authors assumed to be
helpful for learning.
원문 의미: general embeddings of high quality.
OK.
그래서 the 둘째 thing that I 원하다 to mention.
원문 의미: is that, once you have all of
this,.
원문 의미: you have a further stage where you
keep the embeddings that you.
원문 의미: have learned.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you attach to it some other
network, like typically.
원문 의미: a linear projection, to 그다음 fine
tune.
원문 의미: the embeddings that you have
learned into some target task.
이것은 what we call 파인튜닝.입니다.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
그래서 the 문제 is, do we still have 그냥 an
encoder here?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 a next-sentence prediction.
원문 의미: could be seen as a decoder task.
그래서 실제로 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to go in detail.
원문 의미: The next-sentence prediction task.
is 실제로 us putting 둘 sentences, 하나 후에 the
other,.
원문 의미: 그리고 predicting whether they are
truly consecutive.
그래서 it's a classification task.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 포인트.
그리고 yeah, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that in
detail 매우 soon.
그래서 전에 we 보다 that in detail, I'm.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to discuss the pros 그리고
cons that this method usually.
원문 의미: has.
원문 의미: 그래서 regarding on the pro side, this
사전학습 mechanism.
원문 의미: can be done on fairly unlabeled
데이터.
원문 의미: 그래서 you still have this next-
sentence prediction task.
원문 의미: 하지만 this is something that you
control,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you 알다 which sentences follow
each other.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's something that you 알다 it's
self-supervised.
그리고 the masked 언어모델 task, we're.
~할 예정입니다 to 보다 how it consists.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's also something that is
unsupervised.
이것은 a 매우 interesting way입니다.
원문 의미: to 배우다 interesting embeddings out
of unlabeled 데이터.
그리고 그다음 in practice is that we 보다.
원문 의미: that these unlabeled 데이터 leads to
helpful representations being.
원문 의미: learned.
그리고 그다음 you 필요하다 매우 little 데이터 to build on
top of it.
그래서 at the 파인튜닝 stage, you 그냥.
원문 의미: 시작하다 from these 매우 nice embeddings.
원문 의미: that you have learned, 그리고 you 그냥
have a few 가중치 to tune.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 this usually leads to a
performance that exceeds.
원문 의미: state of the art back 그다음.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 regarding the downsides,.
원문 의미: we have of course all the text
generation.
원문 의미: tasks that are out of reach 왜냐하면 we
don't have a decoder.
원문 의미: 그리고 also, we can 보다 these 둘 stage
process 그리고 the fact.
원문 의미: that we 필요하다 to further tune
embeddings.
원문 의미: as something that can be over
hurdled.
원문 의미: 그래서 it might be, when you compare
this kind of methodology.
원문 의미: with respect to more traditional
methods, that can be 하나 shot.
원문 의미: This could be seen as a downside.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 I have some names regarding
variants here.
원문 의미: 우리는 dive deep into 둘 of them a bit
later on.할 것입니다.
OK.
그래서 I 원하다 us to focus on the original
트랜스포머.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go step by step into
what happened to it,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 how we get the BERT
architecture.
이것은 what we had in the original 트랜스포머
paper입니다.
that we saw 지난 주.
원문 의미: 그리고 what BERT did is extract the
encoder 부분 of it.
원문 의미: 그리고 attach 기본적으로 these new
objective functions that I 그냥.
원문 의미: mentioned, alongside some new set
of tricks when it.
원문 의미: comes to representing 토큰들.
그래서 I 생각하다 we're ~할 예정입니다 to go through
them 하나 by 하나.
그래서 첫째 of all, 하나 interesting note.
원문 의미: is that it uses a specific
tokenizer called WordPiece.
그래서 you can 보다 it as a tokenizer that.
원문 의미: learns on your 학습 set, based on
merge rules that.
원문 의미: maximize the likelihood.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, you have some huge 학습
set,.
원문 의미: 그리고 you 학습하다 a tokenizer that
merges atomic 토큰들 together.
원문 의미: to build your target 어휘집.
그리고 some order of magnitude, I mentioned o
of 30k.
그래서 it's typically, I 생각하다 this is the
size.
원문 의미: that they chose in this paper.
원문 의미: 그리고 in general, like 어휘집 sizes in
these sorts of paper.
원문 의미: are in the order of magnitude of 10
to the power of 4,.
원문 의미: 10 to the power of 5, except for
our 토큰-free method.
원문 의미: that we saw, like ByT5, which is
like this 매우.
restricted set of 토큰들, like 2 to the power
of 8, which is 256.
원문 의미: Apart from this specific 경우, you
always.
원문 의미: have this order of magnitude.
그리고 기본적으로, we are ~할 예정입니다 to 만들다 사용하다 of
the 토큰들.
원문 의미: that I mentioned.
원문 의미: Like at the beginning, 그래서 you have
the CLS 토큰.
그것은 ~할 예정입니다 to carry the bidirectional
representation입니다.
원문 의미: of all your 시퀀스.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have SEP 토큰들 to
separate.
원문 의미: the 둘 sentences towards the next-
sentence prediction task.
원문 의미: 그리고 there is something that I
haven't talked about 그냥 yet.
그래서 I 생각하다 maybe we can talk about it.
원문 의미: at the time of the deep dive.
원문 의미: 그래서 in order to have this masked
언어모델 task,.
그래서 of course you 필요하다 to mask some 토큰들.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 the technique
that is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: applying these sorts of mask 그리고
where 그리고 at which frequency.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 with respect to
the output what.
원문 의미: is ~할 예정입니다 to be our task based on
the resulting representation.
그래서 I'm 그냥 ~할 예정입니다 to pass quickly on it
here,.
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to come back 매우 soon.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 big piece of news regarding
your input.
원문 의미: embeddings—
원문 의미: 그래서 what stays the 같은?
원문 의미: 그래서 you still have these huge
dictionary lookup.
of embeddings for each 토큰 that you're ~할
예정입니다 to 배우다.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to additively
add the positional encoding.
that we saw at 지난 강의.
원문 의미: 그리고 Afshine talked about earlier in
this 강의,.
원문 의미: which can either be hard-coded or
learned.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 the authors here 그냥 used a
hard-coded version here,.
원문 의미: 하지만 I'm not too sure.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's roughly the 같은 performance
usually.
원문 의미: 하지만 there is something new.
원문 의미: There is the introduction of a new
kind.
원문 의미: of encoding called segment encoding
that is ~할 예정입니다 to still.
원문 의미: be additively added to 토큰들, with
the exception that we 그냥.
원문 의미: have 둘 possible encodings there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have segment A that
represents the 첫째 sentence,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 segment B that represents
the 둘째 sentence.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's supposed to help with the
NSP task.
원문 의미: to represent what could be features
that can helpfully.
원문 의미: represent a sentence that precedes
another 하나.
원문 의미: 그래서 at least that was the
hypothesis.
원문 의미: admitted by the authors.
우리는 보다 it has been challenged later on.할
것입니다.
원문 의미: 하지만 this is 하나 of the key concepts.
원문 의미: that was introduced here.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 그래서 far?
원문 의미: Yep.
Yep, 그래서 a great 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what does segment
encoding do at all?
그래서 it's 기본적으로 something that is learned.
그래서 you have 둘 indices, 둘 기본적으로.
원문 의미: embeddings that you can 배우다.
원문 의미: You 그냥 additively add them,
segment.
A for 토큰들 in the 첫째 부분 of the sentence,.
그리고 그다음 segment B in the 둘째 부분.
그리고 you 그냥 배우다 it with 경사하강법.
원문 의미: 그래서 you do nothing with it.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 there was another 문제 here?
원문 의미: Yeah.
그것은 right.입니다.
그래서 the 문제 is, is every 토큰 in the 같은
sentence.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to have the 같은 segment
encoding?
원문 의미: Yes, yeah.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
그래서 I'm seeing I might 필요하다 to speed up a
tiny bit.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, the 둘째 thing that I 원하다
to highlight here.
is that we 가지다 the encoder 부분 of the
트랜스포머.
원문 의미: 그리고 nothing new here.
It's 그냥 the 같은.
원문 의미: We have self-attention, followed by
these FFN.
원문 의미: 이것은 where you're ~할 예정입니다 to get
your bidirectional nature입니다.
원문 의미: of your encodings.
그리고 그다음 기본적으로 we're assuming.
원문 의미: that 학습 both MLM 그리고 NSP on it.
is ~할 예정입니다 to help us 배우다 helpful
projection.
원문 의미: 행렬들 in this encoder that can be
suited.
원문 의미: for any classification task.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 as promised, I talked about
detailing more about what.
원문 의미: this MLM task was ~할 예정입니다 to do.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you 보다 at the input,
you're.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to 기본적으로 have your input
sentence,.
원문 의미: 그리고 replace at random some 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 it will be replaced either with
the 토큰 mask.
그래서 it's in 80% of the time.
원문 의미: In 10% of the time, the 토큰들
selected.
원문 의미: for this MLM objective function are
not.
~할 예정입니다 to be replaced at all.
그래서 we're 그냥 saying, it's the 같은 토큰,.
그냥 predict the 같은 토큰.
그리고 그다음 10% of the time, it's ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to be changed to some random other
word.
원문 의미: 그래서 at the end of it, you have the
subset.
of 토큰들 you're ~할 예정입니다 to perform your MLM
task on.
그리고 그다음 this is how it's composed.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 그래서 기본적으로 the 직관 here.
원문 의미: is that when you 원하다 to predict
what a 토큰 is,.
you 필요하다 to 알다 about its 컨텍스트.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to force the 모델.
원문 의미: to 배우다 about what surrounds it,
left 그리고 right.
원문 의미: 이것은 the bidirectional property of
this architecture입니다.
원문 의미: put into action.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about the
next-sentence.
원문 의미: prediction task where 기본적으로 the
process here.
is to select 둘 sentences from a given
말뭉치,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 present them side by side
in order 50% of the time,.
원문 의미: 그리고 in some random order the other
부분 of the time.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal is for some
classification head.
원문 의미: on top of the CLS 토큰 to determine
whether A 그리고 B are.
원문 의미: consecutive.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's all it does.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 the assumption is that it
also helps.
원문 의미: 배우다 some useful embeddings.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 here I'm ~할 예정입니다 to present
the notation that.
원문 의미: is used in the paper.
원문 의미: 그래서 the paper is something I
recommend reading.
원문 의미: It's a 매우 nice read, alongside the
"Attention is All You 필요하다.".
원문 의미: I would say it's a landmark paper.
I 생각하다 it has a 170k citations, something
정말 impressive.
그리고 기본적으로 what we called n in the original
트랜스포머.
원문 의미: paper is 이제 called L. H, that was
called d 모델,.
원문 의미: is the 차원 of our embeddings.
그리고 A is the 번호 of attention heads,.
원문 의미: which was called the little h.
원문 의미: 그래서 here I'm 그냥 showing these new
notations for information,.
원문 의미: 그냥 to 주다 you the mapping.
원문 의미: 하지만 of course, together with
Afshine,.
원문 의미: 우리는 stay consistent with the
original notations we할 것입니다.
원문 의미: had, 그래서 그냥 like for information.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 interesting note is that
you.
원문 의미: will 보다 that the BERT 모델, when.
원문 의미: you 보다 at some repository of 모델들
such as Hugging Face,.
원문 의미: 그래서 usually it's given in several
versions.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 보다 sometimes like 경우,
uncased.
원문 의미: 그래서 this denotes what kind of
preprocessing.
원문 의미: was done to the 데이터, whether you
only.
원문 의미: have lowercase words in there or
whether casing matters.
원문 의미: 그래서 based on your task of
interest,.
원문 의미: it might be 하나 thing you 원하다 to
choose from.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 I 주다 some orders of magnitude.
원문 의미: from the paper on what values were
chosen for each of these.
그래서 if I 기억하다 correctly, I 생각하다.
원문 의미: the original 트랜스포머 had 12 stacked
encoders 그리고 decoders.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 some numbers here were
taken from there.
그래서 yeah, order of magnitude is 100
million 파라미터들.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 그래서 far?
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 그다음 이제 we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
the 파인튜닝 stage.
where the goal is to 기본적으로 가지다.
원문 의미: whatever we have learned at 사전학습
stage,.
그리고 그다음 freeze those 가중치.
그리고 instead of 학습 again on those 같은 가중치,.
원문 의미: you have some classification linear
layer.
원문 의미: 그것은 put on top of either the CLS
토큰입니다.
or on top of 토큰들 of interest.
원문 의미: 그리고 you're ~할 예정입니다 to 배우다 about
the linear embeddings there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you're ~할 예정입니다 to have some
classification task.
원문 의미: 그래서 you could either freeze all
these pre-학습된 가중치.
그리고 그냥 학습하다 on these small 가중치.
원문 의미: Or you can 그냥 retrain the whole
thing.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 there is multiple
classification schemes.
원문 의미: 그리고 some of it will be influenced
by your willingness.
원문 의미: to retrain a lot of the network 그리고
how.
원문 의미: 다른 the classification task is with
respect.
원문 의미: to the original 사전학습 task.
원문 의미: OK, great.
그리고 그다음 그냥 to 주다 some 예시들 of what.
원문 의미: could be 파인튜닝 tasks for tasks of
interest,.
원문 의미: you can have a sentiment
extraction.
원문 의미: where you build a classification
layer on top of the CLS 토큰.
그리고 we 주다 some other 예시 문제 answering.
원문 의미: where 기본적으로 you are given some
input.
원문 의미: 그리고 the goal of the 모델 is to detect
beginning 그리고 end.
원문 의미: spans of the response.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 some objective function.
그것은 at the 토큰 level.입니다.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 I propose that we do some
deep dive.
원문 의미: into 하나 specific 예시.
원문 의미: Our favorite 예시, this teddy bear is
그래서 cute.
원문 의미: Let's 그냥 보다 how BERT works in
practice.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 what you would do in an
uncased setting.
원문 의미: is 가지다 the sentence, pre-process
it, 그냥.
원문 의미: put everything lowercase.
원문 의미: 그다음 you apply the WordPiece
algorithm.
원문 의미: on whatever tokenization mechanism
that your tokenizer.
원문 의미: has learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시 here, apparently it had
all these merge rules.
이것은 the 토큰들 that appear in the 어휘집.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 as I promised, we add the
CLS 토큰 at the beginning.
그리고 그다음 we add the SEP 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 you also have this PAD 토큰들.
원문 의미: that are 기본적으로 used to fill out the
시퀀스 until the end.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 when you 학습하다, you 학습하다 by
batch,.
그리고 그다음 batches are composed of 행렬들.
원문 의미: that have a fixed length.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 그냥 have this deep dive a
bit.
원문 의미: the 같은 as what we had in the 트랜스포머
deep dive 지난 time.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the embeddings that
are learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's some huge lookup table
between the index of each 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 the learned representation.
원문 의미: 그래서 you add to it the position
embedding of the 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 something that's new here—
원문 의미: the segment embedding.
그래서 exactly as we said, it's an embedding.
그것은 added to each 토큰.입니다.
그리고 the 같은 embedding is added to the 같은
토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 all the 토큰들 have the 같은 segment
A.
원문 의미: 그다음 some other embedding B is added
to all the 토큰들.
원문 의미: of the segment B. OK, great.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 you have, similarly as the
트랜스포머,.
원문 의미: something that is position-aware
그리고 컨텍스트-aware—
원문 의미: 그래서 not 컨텍스트-aware 그냥 yet, 하지만
segment-aware here.
원문 의미: OK, great.
원문 의미: 그리고 기본적으로 it goes through this
encoder architecture.
그리고 그다음 at the end of it, for the 경우.
원문 의미: of sentiment extraction, we do not.
원문 의미: care about the embeddings that are.
원문 의미: corresponding to each 토큰 that is
not the CLS 토큰.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 what we care about is the
output embedding of the CLS.
원문 의미: 토큰, where we plug a linear layer.
원문 의미: that will 배우다 some classification
task.
원문 의미: 그래서 any 문제 here?
원문 의미: 그래서 does the fact that we drop all
the output embeddings, apart.
원문 의미: from the CLS 토큰, 만들다 sense?
원문 의미: Yeah, yep.
원문 의미: Yeah, 그래서 the 문제 is, what does this
FFN, is that right?
원문 의미: What does this FFN correspond to?
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 you have a map between
the 차원.
원문 의미: of the output embedding 그리고 your
task of interest.
원문 의미: 그래서 it might be classification of
either positive or negative.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some hidden layer with
some length.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have typically 둘 행렬들.
원문 의미: to 배우다 the projection from 하나 to
that hidden layer, 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: the hidden layer to the output.
그리고 그다음 you 배우다 these 가중치 in order.
원문 의미: to do the classification task,
based on the embeddings.
원문 의미: that it has learned here.
원문 의미: Yeah, great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 that was the 문제 I was waiting
for.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, why do we throw away
all.
원문 의미: these other output embeddings?
그래서 we don't 필요하다 them here.
그래서 we are in a classification task.
원문 의미: We have put as convention to
operate on top of some 토큰,.
원문 의미: like the CLS 토큰.
그리고 그다음 the magic of this 토큰 is.
원문 의미: that all these self-attention 메커니즘들
that.
원문 의미: are in the encoder has mixed the
representation of each.
원문 의미: of the other 토큰들 in that
representation, such.
원문 의미: that the output embeddings, they
are 컨텍스트-aware.
그래서 기본적으로, it's an embedding that is.
원문 의미: geared towards classification.
그리고 이것은 what we say will be what we입니다.
원문 의미: plug in to that linear layer.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 when I say we throw out all
the other embeddings,.
it's 실제로 something that we do.
원문 의미: for the 경우 of classification.
하지만 if we do classification at the 토큰
level,.
원문 의미: 그다음 each of them may be used.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, when I say 문제
answering, if you 원하다.
to detect whether a given 토큰 is the
beginning of an 답,.
beginning of end of an 답, you.
원문 의미: would typically have 둘 FFNs that.
원문 의미: respectively predict the 시작하다 그리고
end of the 답.
원문 의미: 그리고 you would apply it on each of
these embeddings.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what is query, key,
그리고 value for CLS?
그래서 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be the 같은 process as
all the other 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 배우다 here a representation.
원문 의미: for the embedding, for the 토큰 CLS.
원문 의미: It gets projected to query.
원문 의미: It gets projected to key.
원문 의미: It gets projected to value.
원문 의미: It does all its attention
computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 at the end, you get this
embedding.
원문 의미: that 기본적으로 that has attended to all
the other ones.
그래서 it's like the 답 is, it's the 같은 as.
원문 의미: for the other 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서, yeah.
그래서 그냥 treat it as 하나 토큰, it could be any
토큰,.
그리고 it's the 같은.
원문 의미: OK, awesome.
그래서 I 보다 we have 다섯 more minutes.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to quickly go through the
end of it.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 thing that was great with
BERT,.
원문 의미: 그리고 it was also great with ELMo,
is.
원문 의미: that you have embeddings that are
contextual.
원문 의미: 그리고 here you can 보다 that it's 매우
easy.
원문 의미: to 배우다 any classification task that
you 원하다,.
원문 의미: based on these 배우다 embeddings.
원문 의미: 이것은 a flexibility that was greatly
appreciated here.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's widely used in the
industry.
원문 의미: 그래서 anything that comes with
sentiment detection.
원문 의미: or other classification-related
tasks,.
it's 매우 common to 사용하다 a BERT-like 모델
nowadays.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk a bit about its
limitations 이제.
원문 의미: 그래서 as you 보다 in the original
paper,.
I 생각하다 the 컨텍스트 length was of size 512.
원문 의미: 그래서 it was typically limited in
this early paper.
원문 의미: Afshine has mentioned of
techniques.
원문 의미: as to how we can further grow this
컨텍스트.
원문 의미: size without making the complexity
go completely,.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 like hike.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have some approximation
methods.
원문 의미: where you 컴퓨트 local attention, 그리고
그래서 on.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 사용하다 of these tricks
helps.
원문 의미: you grow the size of the 컨텍스트 while
staying.
원문 의미: within reasonable computation
requirement bounds.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about 둘 other
limitations.
that we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what other 모델들
try to remedy.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is 하나 where the latency
could be seen as high.
원문 의미: You have a still 110 million 파라미터들
for a BERT base,.
그래서 it's quite a lot.
원문 의미: Is there a way to 만들다 this smaller
그리고 faster?
그리고 그다음 the 둘째 하나 is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: you have these 둘 objective
functions of MLM 그리고 NSP.
원문 의미: Are those 둘 truly helpful?
원문 의미: Is there any way we can simplify
the 사전학습 process?
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 in a 둘째 how.
원문 의미: 그래서 첫째, regarding this 둘째
limitation that we had,.
원문 의미: this 기본적으로 sensitivity to cost.
원문 의미: 그래서 who here has heard of
distillation?
원문 의미: Good, few people.
그래서 I 그냥 원하다 to flash this quote.
원문 의미: from Hinton, Vinyals, 그리고 Jeff
Dean, which.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 has been informative.
그리고 it's a good mindset to have to 보다.
원문 의미: that the 분포 that is output by a
given 모델.
원문 의미: is 실제로 super helpful to 알다 what it
has learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 the soft targets contain almost
all the knowledge.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's some 강의 from them that
contain this quote.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로 they were at the origin
of the 개념.
원문 의미: of distillation later on.
원문 의미: 그리고 you quickly 보다 in practice that
기본적으로 learning.
원문 의미: the 분포 of a 모델 is more helpful than
directly.
원문 의미: learning the hard labels.
그래서 you have this 개념 of teacher 그리고 학생
모델들,.
원문 의미: where 기본적으로 the goal in
distillation.
is ~할 예정입니다 to be to map this output 분포 of
a smaller.
원문 의미: 모델 directly to your more complex
모델,.
원문 의미: rather than the hard labels.
원문 의미: 그리고 the objective function that
you.
원문 의미: 사용하다 for this to minimize this is
the KL divergence, which.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 says in a world that is
described by the teacher,.
원문 의미: the teacher T, how bad is it to 모델
with the 학생 S.
원문 의미: 그래서 it 기본적으로 tries to assess how
close the 학생.
분포 is ~할 예정입니다 to be to the world's T.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 interesting note that you
will 보다 here.
원문 의미: is that you find the cross-entropy
loss.
if your yT 분포 is 그냥 a hard label.
그래서 if you have 그냥 a 1 at 하나 position.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 0 everywhere else, you
have.
원문 의미: minus log of yS, which is 매우
interesting.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 what the DistilBERT folks
have done—
그래서 by the way, it's a 매우 clean paper,.
원문 의미: it's like 넷 pages, 하지만 super
impactful.
원문 의미: 그래서 it says that if you reduce the
번호 of layers by 2,.
원문 의미: you have a lot of gains 그리고 almost
the 같은 performance,.
원문 의미: which is 매우 remarkable.
원문 의미: 그리고 they 기본적으로 used distillation as
a way.
원문 의미: to retain that performance.
원문 의미: 그래서 this has been like the key,
alongside diminishing.
원문 의미: the 번호 of layers.
그리고 지난, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to talk about
RoBERTa.
원문 의미: That studied the fact that removing
the NSP objective.
원문 의미: function led to no decrease in
performance almost.
그래서 they 그냥 dropped it.
원문 의미: 그리고 they added some tricks, such as
dynamically doing.
원문 의미: the masking.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, for a given piece of
text,.
원문 의미: at each epoch, 그래서 every time you
보다 the 같은 kind of text,.
원문 의미: you would change the masking.
원문 의미: 그리고 they also had some 데이터
strategy.
원문 의미: where they saw that the 모델 was
vastly undertrained.
원문 의미: 그래서 they increased the diversity
그리고 the size of the 데이터 lot.
원문 의미: 그리고 they saw that benchmark
performance increased quite.
원문 의미: a bit on the 같은 benchmarks.
그리고 that's it for 오늘.
원문 의미: Thank you, everyone.
원문 의미: Have a great weekend.