좋습니다.
Hello, everyone, 그리고 welcome to 강의 4 of
CME 295.
원문 의미: 오늘은 Friday, October, the 17,입니다.
원문 의미: which means that the 중간고사 is 하나 주
away.
시작하기 전에, I'm 그냥 ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to go over some logistics to 만들다
sure we're all.
원문 의미: aligned on what to expect.
그래서 the 중간고사 will 가지다 place 다음 주 같은 time.
Instead of an hour 그리고 15 minutes,.
it will be an hour 그리고 30 minutes.
그래서 it's 3:30 to 5:00 in this classroom.
원문 의미: 그냥 like business as usual.
원문 의미: topics 측면에서는, the 중간고사 will.
be about lectures 1, 2, 그리고 3, which we
had,.
그리고 this 하나, which is 강의 4.
그래서 그냥 to 주다 you an overview of what.
원문 의미: you can expect in the 중간고사,
there's.
~할 예정입니다 to be some multi-choice 문제들
along.
원문 의미: with some free form 문제들, 하지만
they're mainly.
~할 예정입니다 to be about the things that we've
seen in 수업.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you watch the recordings, or
attend the lectures,.
그리고 그냥 go through the 슬라이드, 그리고 알다 the 중요한
formulas,.
I 생각하다 you'll be fine.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 알다 that you may have 문제들
until 다음 주,.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's why 후에 this 강의 with
Shervin,.
원문 의미: we will be holding office hours.
그래서 feel free to come to us 그리고 ask us any
문제들.
그리고 of course, we'll be fully available.
between 이제 그리고 다음 주.
그래서 in 경우 you have any 문제들,.
원문 의미: feel free to ping us on Ed.
그리고 yeah, we'll 만들다 sure to respond.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: I also 알다 that a 번호 of you are
auditing this 수업.
그래서 in 경우 you're still interested to 가지다.
원문 의미: the 중간고사 for some reason, maybe.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you have an upcoming
interview, 그냥 tell us,.
원문 의미: 그래서 that we can 그냥 expect the 번호 of
copies to print.
그래서 we'll be printing this on Monday.
원문 의미: 그래서 그냥 let us over the weekend in
경우 you're interested.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's for the 중간고사.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 둘째 piece of news is the
final.
원문 의미: 그래서 we said that we were working on
the dates.
원문 의미: 그래서 we 마지막으로 finalized the dates
which did not change.
그래서 it's Wednesday, December the 10.
OK.
그래서 a little bit late, 7:00 PM to 8:30 PM.
그래서 it's a slot that we have.
원문 의미: The location is 다른 from this 하나.
그래서 it's in this room.
원문 의미: 그리고 the final will only cover the
둘째 부분.
of the 수업, which is 기본적으로 lectures 5 to 9.
원문 의미: Any 문제들 on this?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Good 문제.
그래서 is it closed notes?
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, what is the format
of the multiple choice?
원문 의미: 그래서 you'll have— 그래서 we did not 끝내다
writing the 시험,.
하지만 it's ~할 예정입니다 to be something like you
have a 문제.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's say, you have 셋, 넷
possible answers.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 그냥 choose the 하나 that.
그것은 correct.입니다.
원문 의미: Something like this.
원문 의미: 그리고 you'll also have some free
form,.
원문 의미: like you'll have to 그냥 답 in your
own words.
원문 의미: Yeah.
감사합니다.
그래서 the 문제 is, are we allowed to 가지다
anything?
그래서 it's closed book.
그래서 no.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Nothing.
그냥 a pen.
원문 의미: Yeah.
문제 is no calculator.
원문 의미: You will not 필요하다 a calculator.
원문 의미: 하지만 speaking of the cheat sheets,.
그래서 I'm not sure if we mentioned, I 생각하다
we did,.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is a cheat sheet for this
하나,.
원문 의미: which we cannot bring to the 시험 하지만
you can 사용하다 그냥.
원문 의미: for your studying that's on the
웹사이트.
수업 웹사이트.
원문 의미: 그래서 Jess recommends looking at it.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 super clear for everyone?
원문 의미: 매우 cool.
원문 의미: Well, OK.
As always, we'll be starting the 수업.
원문 의미: 그냥 recapping what we saw in the
previous 강의.
기억하신다면, we 기본적으로 studied.
원문 의미: a new kind of architecture, which.
원문 의미: was called the mixture of experts,
which is such.
원문 의미: that if you have an input, what you
원하다.
원문 의미: is to not necessarily activate all
the 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you are in a setting where
you have multiple experts,.
원문 의미: 그리고 in the forward pass, you only
activate some of them.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's a sparse MOE.
원문 의미: You also have the dense MOE, which.
기본적으로 가중치 the outputs as a function.
원문 의미: of the output of the gate.
원문 의미: 그래서 we saw that this architecture
was used in LLMs,.
원문 의미: 그리고 it was mainly used to be able
to scale.
원문 의미: this LLMs without incurring an
expensive cost.
at 추론 time, 왜냐하면 you don't 원하다.
원문 의미: to activate all the 파라미터들.
원문 의미: The 둘째 thing that we saw was 그냥.
원문 의미: defining what an LLM was 그리고 in
particular,.
원문 의미: how you could decide on what the 다음
토큰 예측 is.
그래서 we saw 셋 methods.
원문 의미: 첫째 하나 was we called greedy
decoding,.
원문 의미: which was always taking the highest
probable 토큰.
원문 의미: The 둘째 method we saw was beam
search,.
원문 의미: where we kept track of the K most
probable 시퀀스들.
그리고 그다음 the 셋째 하나 was 샘플링.
원문 의미: 그래서 we're not doing the most
probable.
원문 의미: We're not keeping track of the
highest probable 시퀀스들.
원문 의미: What we do is we sample the 다음 토큰
with respect.
원문 의미: to the 분포 that we get as outputs.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 we saw there's this
hyperparameter that's.
원문 의미: called temperature that allows you.
원문 의미: to tweak how spiky you 원하다 your 분포
to like versus not.
원문 의미: 그리고 we also saw some 추론
optimization techniques,.
원문 의미: which are used in practice to avoid
having.
원문 의미: a big cost at decoding time.
그래서 I'm not ~할 예정입니다 to 그냥 mention
everything,.
원문 의미: 하지만 I would say KV cache, for
instance,.
is an 중요한 method.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, 그냥 recommend 그냥 knowing.
원문 의미: what it is along with the other
ones.
그리고 with that, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 강의
4.
그리고 실제로, I was 정말 looking forward to 오늘.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 강의 1, we saw what self-
attention.
원문 의미: was, what a 트랜스포머 was.
원문 의미: 둘째 강의, we saw some of the tricks.
원문 의미: that people 사용하다 오늘 그리고 some of the
variations.
원문 의미: from the 트랜스포머.
원문 의미: We introduced what an LLM was 지난
강의.
그리고 this 강의, we're 마지막으로 ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to 보다 how these LLMs are 학습된.
그래서 오늘, we're ~할 예정입니다 to focus on LLM 학습.
그리고 the 첫째 thing that I'm ~할 예정입니다 to say.
원문 의미: is if you've been in the ML field
for,.
원문 의미: let's say, more than a few years
이제, you.
원문 의미: may have noticed that
traditionally,.
원문 의미: if you had a task, what you would
do.
원문 의미: is 학습하다 a 모델 specifically for that
task.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's suppose 10 years ago,
let's suppose.
원문 의미: we had a task which was around
detecting spam.
원문 의미: You would 학습하다 a 모델 specifically to
detect spams.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would 학습하다 on the 학습 set,.
원문 의미: eval on the validation set, 그리고 그다음
test on the test set.
원문 의미: If you had another 사용하다 경우, let's
suppose sentiment.
원문 의미: extraction, you would 학습하다 a 모델
specifically for that.
그리고 그래서 on 그리고 그래서 forth.
원문 의미: 하지만 하나 could argue that these
tasks,.
원문 의미: they are not completely disjoint.
원문 의미: They're all involving 그냥
understanding the text.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 could argue we could find a
way.
원문 의미: to somehow leverage the knowledge
that we acquired.
원문 의미: during 학습 for, let's say, 하나 task.
원문 의미: 그리고 reuse that for another task.
원문 의미: 그래서 this method has a name.
원문 의미: It's been around for some time, 그리고
it's.
원문 의미: called transfer learning.
원문 의미: 그래서 the goal of transfer learning
is.
원문 의미: to not always 시작하다 from scratch if
you have a new task.
It's to 시작하다 with some pre-학습된 모델,.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what pre-학습된 is,
그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: tune it for your task instead of
starting from scratch.
원문 의미: Well, it's 기본적으로 the paradigm.
원문 의미: on which LLMs are 학습된.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 here is that all these
tasks,.
원문 의미: they involve understanding
language.
그래서 what we're ~할 예정입니다 to do is have what
we call a 사전학습.
원문 의미: stage, which involves 학습 your LLM
on vast amounts of 데이터.
원문 의미: to 그냥 understand what language,.
원문 의미: what code is 그리고 그다음 have a 둘째
stage of, quote unquote,.
원문 의미: "tuning.".
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 a little bit what
that tuning is.
하지만 in that 둘째 stage, we're ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to 가지다 our pre-학습된 모델 그리고 somehow
find a way to tune.
원문 의미: the 가중치 to adapt to a specific
task.
그래서 as an 예시, here, we would pre-학습하다 a
huge 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 suppose for spam detection.
원문 의미: We would somehow tune it for that
sentiment extraction, 같은.
We would tune it for that 그리고 그래서 on.
이것은 그냥 to 가지다 the 예시 from 전에.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 아이디어 here is in order to
obtain these 모델들,.
we're not ~할 예정입니다 to 시작하다 from scratch.
좋습니다.
그래서 이제, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 what 사전학습 is.
그래서 사전학습 is by far the most.
원문 의미: expensive both in terms of 컴퓨트,
cost,.
everything 부분 of the 학습.
원문 의미: 그래서 what it does is taking a huge
amount of 데이터.
그리고 학습 your LLM to 그냥 predict the 다음 토큰.
그리고 here, by 데이터, what I mean is 기본적으로
everything.
원문 의미: you can find.
그래서 it can be text in English.
원문 의미: It can be text in other languages.
원문 의미: It can be even code, can be code in
다른 languages,.
원문 의미: can be 기본적으로 the whole internet.
우리는 보다 some of the 데이터 sets할 것입니다.
원문 의미: that people 사용하다 for that, 하지만 you
can 생각하다 of this.
as 그냥 학습 your 모델 to try to predict
anything that's.
원문 의미: written.
원문 의미: 그리고 as I mentioned, the objective
here.
is to predict the 다음 토큰.
기억하신다면, our LLM is a text-to-text 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 most likely a decoder only 모델
in more than 90%.
원문 의미: of the cases.
원문 의미: 그래서 what it does is it takes some
input text,.
그리고 it tries to always predict the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: in an iterative basis.
원문 의미: 그래서 in terms of the 데이터 sets that
are used,.
원문 의미: you will 보다 the term Common Crawl a
lot on papers.
It's 기본적으로 a 데이터셋 composed of anything.
원문 의미: you can find on the internet.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 they have something like
셋 billion pages.
원문 의미: per month.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you go on their 웹사이트, they
have a huge archive.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's a bunch of other
websites.
원문 의미: as well that you can find in there.
원문 의미: 그래서 for instance, Wikipedia
articles, any social media.
원문 의미: as well, like Reddit.
원문 의미: 그리고 there are a lot of Reddit
conversations in those 데이터.
원문 의미: sets.
원문 의미: You have a lot of codes, 그리고 of
course, you.
원문 의미: have a bunch of places for that.
원문 의미: You have GitHub, you have Stack
Overflow, all these forums.
원문 의미: that talk about codes.
원문 의미: 그래서 all of this is meant for your
모델.
원문 의미: to 그냥 understand the structure of
the language 그리고 code.
그리고 in terms of size, 그래서 it's measured in
terms.
of 토큰들, 번호 of 토큰들.
그리고 하나 order of magnitude that I 원하다 you
to 기억하다.
원문 의미: is on the order of hundreds of
billions.
원문 의미: or even trillions or even tens of
trillions of 토큰들.
그래서 I'll 주다 you an 예시.
그래서 GPT-3 was 학습된 on 300 billion 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그리고 for instance, Llama 3, which
was.
원문 의미: I believe published 지난 year, was.
학습된 on 15 trillion 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 these are huge 데이터 sets.
그래서 전에 we go further, I 원하다 to 소개하다 둘
notations.
그리고 I 생각하다 하나 of them I introduced it 지난
강의.
원문 의미: The reason why I 원하다 to talk to you
about these notations.
원문 의미: is they're used everywhere to talk
about how.
원문 의미: much 컴퓨트 some 모델 needs.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 notation is FLOPs,
which.
원문 의미: stands for floating operations.
그리고 what it is it's a unit of 컴퓨트.
원문 의미: 그래서 the higher the FLOPs, the more
operations are involved.
왜냐하면 by definition, FLOPs is the 번호.
원문 의미: of operations that involve floating
포인트 numbers.
원문 의미: 그래서 floating 포인트 numbers, you can
생각하다 of them.
원문 의미: as 그냥 numbers with decimal points.
그래서 in terms of order of magnitudes, 학습.
원문 의미: an LLM is on the order of 10 to the
power of 25 FLOPs.
원문 의미: 그리고 the way you obtain FLOPs, 그래서
usually, it's.
원문 의미: a complicated formula.
하지만 in your mind, you can 생각하다 of it.
원문 의미: as something that is a function of
the size of your 데이터,.
그래서 the 번호 of 토큰들 that you 학습하다 it on,.
그리고 the 번호 of 파라미터들 of your 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's not an universal
formula.
왜냐하면 it also is a function of the
architecture.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다, for instance, MOE
based LLMs as requiring,.
원문 의미: let's say, less 컴퓨트 왜냐하면 only some
parts are.
원문 의미: activated compared to, let's say,
dense LLMs.
하지만 you can 그냥 생각하다 of it as it's.
a function of the 번호 of 토큰들 그리고 파라미터들.
원문 의미: It's like O of the product between
the 둘, more or less.
그리고 그다음 there's a 둘째 notation.
that I 원하다 to 소개하다, which is also FLOPS,.
하지만 it's 다른.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, FLOPS stands for floating
포인트 operations.
원문 의미: per 둘째.
그래서 it's a measure of 컴퓨트 speeds.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's 기본적으로 how fast can your
hardware.
원문 의미: execute these operations.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 you also have some order of
magnitudes here.
하지만 if you're into, let's say GPU들,.
원문 의미: you will 보다 that in the description
of GPU들,.
원문 의미: they always indicate FLOPS.
그리고 we will 보다 that in a 둘째.
원문 의미: 하지만 I 그냥 원하다 to call out that FLOPS
here is usually.
원문 의미: all caps, although you may 보다 some
papers that 사용하다 하나.
원문 의미: for the other, which is confusing.
그래서 I'll 그냥 recommend 그냥 contextualizing
this notation.
원문 의미: with respect to the sentence that
it is in 왜냐하면 sometimes.
원문 의미: people 실제로 switch the 둘.
원문 의미: 하지만 this is the common notation.
원문 의미: 그래서 far, 그래서 good?
좋습니다.
그래서 이제, we 알다 that we have a 사전학습 step.
We 알다 it involves a lot of 컴퓨트.
We 알다 it involves a lot of 데이터.
We 알다 our 모델 is large.
원문 의미: 그래서 what people did was trying to
보다.
원문 의미: how the performance evolves as a
function of 모델 size.
그리고 학습 size.
원문 의미: 그리고 there is this 하나 paper called
Scaling Loss.
원문 의미: for Neural 언어모델 that was published
in 2020.
원문 의미: that performed a bunch of
experiments.
원문 의미: by varying these 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they found was the more
컴퓨트 you have,.
원문 의미: the better your 모델 learns about
predicting the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: 같은 for 데이터셋 size.
원문 의미: 그래서 the bigger your 학습 set, the
better it is,.
원문 의미: 그리고 the bigger your 모델, the better
it is.
그래서 for some time, I 생각하다, between 2019
그리고 2024,.
원문 의미: you were seeing 모델들 that were
larger 그리고 larger,.
원문 의미: 그냥 people 그냥 building things that.
원문 의미: were bigger 그리고 bigger 왜냐하면
according to these experiments,.
원문 의미: the performance was 그냥 getting
better.
원문 의미: 그래서 something else that they
noticed.
원문 의미: was bigger 모델들 tend to be more.
원문 의미: what they call sample efficient.
원문 의미: 그래서 what that means is for an equal
amount of 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그것은 processed, you will have a
better입니다.
원문 의미: performance with a bigger 모델
compared to a smaller 하나.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 you can wonder, we don't
have unlimited 컴퓨트.
컴퓨트 is expensive.
원문 의미: It has a lot of drawbacks.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a fixed 컴퓨트, 그리고
people also.
원문 의미: try to 답 the 문제 given a certain
amount of 컴퓨트,.
원문 의미: how can you fix your 학습 set size
그리고 your 모델 size.
원문 의미: in a way that's more optimal?
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 here, you 필요하다 to decide how
big is your 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 what they did is they fixed a
unit of 컴퓨트, which.
원문 의미: is the color of these curves.
그리고 they tried 학습 모델들 of 다른 sizes.
원문 의미: with 다른 학습 set size.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they saw was that there
was always a sweet spot here,.
원문 의미: which followed some kind of
relationship, 그리고 in particular,.
원문 의미: 이것은 a table that summarizes, quote
unquote,입니다.
"the optimal set of 번호 of 파라미터들 그리고 학습
set.
원문 의미: size," which is sometimes called
the Chinchilla law.
원문 의미: 그리고 what they realized was if you
have an amount of 학습.
원문 의미: set size that's about 20 times the
모델 size,.
원문 의미: 그다음 you're spending your 컴퓨트 in a,
quote unquote,.
원문 의미: "an optimal way.".
원문 의미: 그리고 in particular, GPT-3, for
instance, I.
생각하다 it was like 175 billion 파라미터들,.
if I 기억하다 correctly, 하지만 it's only.
학습된 on 300 billion 토큰들.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나, for instance, is,
according to this,.
원문 의미: "정말 undertrained," quote unquote.
I 생각하다 there was a 문제.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: [AUDIO OUT].
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
원문 의미: The 문제 is, do they fit the neural
architecture?
그래서 I 생각하다 by 이제, everyone agrees.
원문 의미: that LLMs are 트랜스포머-based decoder
only 모델들.
원문 의미: 그래서 everyone uses the 같은 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can assume that when I say
LLM here,.
원문 의미: it 기본적으로 means decoder only 트랜스포머-
based 모델들.
원문 의미: [AUDIO OUT].
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 문제 is architecture change does not
play a big role.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's what they say 실제로 in
their paper.
원문 의미: They say the thing that changes the
most.
is the amount of 토큰들 on which you 학습하다.
원문 의미: 그리고 the size of your 모델.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Any other 문제들?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: [AUDIO OUT].
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Good 문제.
그래서 문제 is, is there some kind.
원문 의미: of transfer learning between 다른
versions of 모델들?
원문 의미: 그래서 for a lot of these 모델들, they're
실제로 closed source.
원문 의미: 그래서 they don't exactly reveal these
things.
하지만 I guess it's an interesting 문제,.
하나 that I cannot 답 in a general way.
그래서 maybe I 생각하다 it's the best 답 I can 주다
you.
원문 의미: 하지만 in any 경우, when you 보다 at some
of these papers,.
원문 의미: they always state how much it costs
to 학습하다 this.
그리고 it's always in the order of millions.
원문 의미: It's always an expensive step
regardless.
좋습니다.
그냥 speaking of that, 그래서 사전학습.
원문 의미: has a lot of challenges.
하나 of them is cost.
원문 의미: 그래서 when I say, millions of
dollars, it's minimum.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 it can even cost tens of
millions of dollars.
원문 의미: or sometimes hundreds of millions
of dollars.
원문 의미: It takes a lot of time, 그리고 people.
원문 의미: have been mindful of the impact on
the environment.
원문 의미: 그래서 they've also been including the
ecological costs.
원문 의미: 그래서 the other challenge is that the
사전학습 step.
is on 데이터 that is up to the time at which
you pre-학습하다.
your 모델 on.
원문 의미: 그래서 what that means is that the
knowledge that you acquire.
원문 의미: from 학습 on this 데이터셋 can only.
원문 의미: go up until the date at which you
cut your 데이터셋.
원문 의미: 그래서 this date is called the
knowledge cutoff date.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 what that means is your
base 모델,.
원문 의미: your pre-학습된 base 모델 has no way.
원문 의미: to 알다 by itself knowledge that
occurred 후에 this date.
원문 의미: 그리고 speaking of that, a lot of
papers,.
원문 의미: they have tried to edit knowledge,
inject knowledge.
원문 의미: It's always tricky 왜냐하면 there's not
a clean way.
원문 의미: to change the 가중치 in a way that.
원문 의미: does not penalize some parts.
그래서 I guess what people 원하다 to do.
원문 의미: is inject knowledge 하지만 not regress
in some other domains.
그리고 이것은 a 매우 hard 문제.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 of course, these 모델들, they.
원문 의미: try to predict the 다음 토큰.
그리고 there's this 문제 of what.
if it 그냥 generates something that it.
원문 의미: has seen at 학습 time?
원문 의미: 그래서 what we call plagiarism.
원문 의미: 그래서 there's always a risk.
원문 의미: 그래서 these are all the challenges I
그냥.
원문 의미: 원하다 to illustrate when I said
knowledge cutoff date.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you go on, let's say, the
OpenAI 웹사이트 or Google.
원문 의미: 웹사이트 to 보다 at the 모델 cards, you
will always 보다—
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure as you can 보다 from
here,.
원문 의미: 하지만 there is always a line on
knowledge cutoff date, which.
원문 의미: tells you on when the 사전학습 of this
모델.
원문 의미: was done.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, for instance, GPT-5 was
released a few 주 ago,.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, it says, the knowledge
cutoff date is September 30.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can guess that they've done
their 사전학습.
원문 의미: around that stage.
좋습니다.
Any 문제들 on the 첫째 부분?
원문 의미: All good?
원문 의미: Perfect.
그래서 in this 첫째 부분, we've seen.
원문 의미: that 사전학습 was a crucial step of the
LLM 학습.
원문 의미: process.
원문 의미: 그리고 we've seen all these big
numbers.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 could wonder, well, how can
you 학습하다 such a big 모델.
on such a big amount of 데이터?
원문 의미: How do people do that?
이것은 what we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 here.입니다.
이것은 what I mentioned.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 LLMs, you can 생각하다 of them as
decoder only.
트랜스포머-based 모델들.
그래서 in order to 학습하다 your 모델, you 필요하다
that.
You 필요하다 a lot of 데이터, 하지만 그다음 if you.
원문 의미: 보다 at your architecture, you 보다
that a lot of the operations.
원문 의미: involve 행렬 multiplications.
그리고 I guess I have a 문제 for you.
원문 의미: What is the kind of hardware that.
원문 의미: loves 행렬 multiplications?
GPU들.
원문 의미: Yes.
그래서 you also 필요하다 GPU들.
원문 의미: 실제로 more than 하나.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: You had a 문제.
원문 의미: [AUDIO OUT].
Oh.
문제 is GPT for 추론.
그래서 this 하나, we're ~할 예정입니다 to focus on
학습,.
원문 의미: 하지만 requirements for GPU들, they
differ a little bit.
between 학습 그리고 추론, 하지만 in this 부분,.
we're solely focused on 학습.
그리고 speaking of GPU들, I guess, it's not
GPU들 everywhere.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면, for instance, Google,
they've.
원문 의미: developed their own hardware that's
called TPUs,.
원문 의미: 하지만 any non Google-based 모델들,
they've most likely.
been 학습된 on GPU들.
좋습니다.
그래서 in order to 학습하다 your 모델, what do you
do?
원문 의미: 그래서 첫째 of all, you have your LLM.
which is 이제— 그래서 it is this 모델,.
원문 의미: 하지만 이제, we're representing with a
box 그냥 for simplicity.
원문 의미: You initialize it.
It's a lot of 파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of the scale as
being somewhere around billions.
to hundreds of billions of 파라미터들, 그래서 huge
모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 what are the steps involved to
학습하다 a 모델?
원문 의미: Well, what you're trying to do is
to tune the 가중치,.
원문 의미: 그래서 that the 모델 can 배우다 how to
generate the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 하나 step called the
forward pass, where.
원문 의미: you have a bunch of 데이터 that you're
trying.
원문 의미: to pass through the network.
그리고 while we do that, I 그냥 원하다.
원문 의미: to call out things that are 중요한 to
note that we.
원문 의미: 필요하다 to somehow save in memory.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you do this forward pass,.
원문 의미: you have something that's called
activations, which are 기본적으로.
원문 의미: the values at each layer that are
needed in order to 컴퓨트.
원문 의미: the loss.
원문 의미: 그래서 the loss tells you how off you.
원문 의미: are compared to the label that you
원하다 to 학습하다 this on.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 the amount of memory that
you will 사용하다 here.
원문 의미: is dependent on a lot of things.
원문 의미: It's dependent on the 모델 size,
which impacts.
원문 의미: the 번호 of activations.
원문 의미: It's dependent on how big your
batch of 데이터 is for 학습.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's dependent on how large
your 컨텍스트 length is,.
왜냐하면 if you 기억하다, here we have O of N
squared complexity.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 of this self-attention
operation,.
원문 의미: where N is the 시퀀스 length.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have all these 파라미터들 that
come into play.
원문 의미: 그래서 once you do the forward pass,
let's.
원문 의미: suppose you 컴퓨트 the loss.
원문 의미: You 알다 how off you are compared to
your label.
원문 의미: 이제, the 다음 step is to somehow
tweak.
원문 의미: the 가중치 in a way that minimizes the
loss.
원문 의미: 그래서 how do you do that?
원문 의미: There is this another pass called
backwards pass.
원문 의미: 그래서 what this pass does is quantify
the direction.
where the loss is ~할 예정입니다 to be
minimized.
원문 의미: It's called the gradient.
원문 의미: You 가지다 the gradient of the loss
with respect.
to each 파라미터.
원문 의미: Well, gradients, they also 필요하다 to
be saved somewhere in memory.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have 마지막으로 the 가중치
update,.
원문 의미: which is where you 알다 where the
direction at which your loss.
is ~할 예정입니다 to be minimized.
원문 의미: 그래서 you apply that update to your
가중치.
원문 의미: 그리고 you typically 사용하다 optimizers
out there.
원문 의미: Have you heard of Adam optimizer?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 Adam optimizer is 그냥 a fancy
version.
원문 의미: that has some additional
quantities, which.
원문 의미: keep track of—
원문 의미: which are 기본적으로 a function of the
gradients.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have the 첫째 moment 그리고 the
둘째 moment,.
원문 의미: which is 기본적으로 the moving average
of the gradient.
원문 의미: 그리고 the squared gradients.
원문 의미: 그리고 all these quantities, 그래서 the
첫째 moment,.
원문 의미: the 둘째 moment, you also 필요하다 to
somehow save them.
원문 의미: somewhere in memory.
그래서 it's a lot of things to save.
원문 의미: Well, OK.
원문 의미: Breaking news, memory is not
unlimited.
원문 의미: Memory is limited.
그리고 그래서 here, what we have in front of us.
원문 의미: is the description of a GPU.
I 생각하다.
원문 의미: Yeah.
H100, which is a 매우 good GPU.
원문 의미: 그리고 you will 보다 in that
description,.
원문 의미: there's a line on GPU memory.
원문 의미: 그래서 GPU memory is your amount of
memory per GPU.
It's 80 gig for this 하나.
원문 의미: It's quite large.
그래서 it's in on the order of tens of
gigabytes.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to store all these
things in 80 gigabytes, which.
원문 의미: is not a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 what are we doing?
원문 의미: What will you be doing?
그래서 I guess the 아이디어 is to leverage.
원문 의미: not 하나 하지만 several GPU들 in order to
somehow distribute.
원문 의미: the load across CPUs.
원문 의미: 그리고 in order to do that, you have
several methods,.
which we will 보다 in a 둘째.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 set of methods is called
데이터 parallelism,.
원문 의미: also known as DP.
원문 의미: 그래서 what this set of methods does
is.
원문 의미: it distributes 데이터 across GPU들, 그래서
that this forward.
원문 의미: pass 그리고 backward pass, they can
all be done independently.
그리고 그래서 the 아이디어 here is to divide the
batch of 데이터.
원문 의미: across devices, 그리고 그다음 in order to
do that, of course,.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to have a copy of the 모델
per device.
왜냐하면 of course, you 필요하다 to 컴퓨트 the
activations.
원문 의미: You 필요하다 to 컴퓨트 all these things.
원문 의미: 하지만 when you do that, you're are
able to reduce the memory that.
원문 의미: is linked to the batch size.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's called 데이터 parallelism.
원문 의미: Yes.
원문 의미: 문제 is how about the gradient
update?
Well, it's a great 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 what do you do when you have
independent computations here.
원문 의미: 그리고 there?
원문 의미: Well, the gradient is 그냥 the
average.
원문 의미: of the gradients for this thing.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have some communication in
between the GPU들.
원문 의미: that 기본적으로 aggregates the gradient
for the updates.
그래서 I have a 문제 for you.
원문 의미: Is this the 답 to everything?
원문 의미: If we 그냥 scale up like this for,.
I don't 알다, a lot of GPU들, is it great,
always great.
원문 의미: or do we have cons?
원문 의미: Oh, yeah.
원문 의미: Great 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, you have to fit 하나 모델.
그래서 yeah, this is a great 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 둘째 포인트 that I will add.
원문 의미: is you have an additional cost,
which.
원문 의미: is called communication cost, 왜냐하면
you.
원문 의미: 필요하다 to somehow communicate between
your GPU들.
원문 의미: in order to aggregate some
quantities.
그래서 your 학습 is ~할 예정입니다 to be slower.
It's good.
원문 의미: You can scale up the memory.
Of course, you 필요하다 to fit a 모델 on a
device,.
그리고 we will 보다 how we to do that.
원문 의미: 하지만 you will be incurring those
communication costs,.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's not all great.
원문 의미: 그래서 speaking of the memory 그리고 the
fact.
that we 원하다 to, I guess, be able to at
least.
원문 의미: store a 모델 per device.
원문 의미: 그래서 people have realized that
there's 실제로.
원문 의미: a lot of duplication.
원문 의미: 그리고 there has been a paper on
wanting.
원문 의미: to deduplicate this duplicate
information.
원문 의미: 그리고 this method is called ZeRO,
ZeRO redundancy optimization.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 아이디어 is that on each GPU,.
원문 의미: you store the 같은 파라미터들, you store
the 같은 gradients,.
원문 의미: you store the 같은 optimizer states.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 here is how about we
shard, we partition.
원문 의미: those quantities across GPU들?
원문 의미: 그래서 the 첫째 variation is around
sharing the optimizer state.
원문 의미: 그래서 meaning, we partition those
states across the GPU들.
원문 의미: 그래서 this reduces the memory by a
lot.
원문 의미: We can also partition the
gradients,.
원문 의미: 그리고 we can also partition the
파라미터들.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, we have no redundant
information.
원문 의미: Things are 그냥 partitioned.
Well, the 문제 is you're ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to have even more communication
costs,.
원문 의미: 하지만 at least it allows for us to
decrease the memory.
원문 의미: load on each GPU.
이것은 ZeRO, 그래서 there's ZeRO 1, ZeRO 2, ZeRO
3.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 I guess the variation that you.
원문 의미: will choose will be a function of
how sensitive you are to,.
원문 의미: I guess, 학습 time 그리고 how big is
your 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 whether this will be an actual
문제,.
원문 의미: or are you 그냥 fine with 그냥 storing
everything?
그래서 that's 하나 set of methods.
원문 의미: 그래서 this set of methods is, again,
데이터 parallelism.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's 기본적으로 you having
independent sets of 데이터 that.
are handled by 다른 GPU들.
원문 의미: Well, you have another set of
methods that's.
원문 의미: called 모델 parallelism.
원문 의미: 그래서 모델 parallelism tries to
parallelize the operation even.
원문 의미: within 하나 batch.
그래서 there's a bunch of methods.
원문 의미: I don't 원하다 to sound too like a
catalog.
그래서 we're not ~할 예정입니다 through them all
하지만 하나 by 하나.
원문 의미: 하지만 I will 그냥 call out a few that
are worth noting.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 기억하다 지난 강의, we talked
about MOE-based LLMs.
원문 의미: 그리고 how 시퀀스들 were being sent to 다른
experts.
원문 의미: Well, there is a way to distribute
that.
원문 의미: across GPU들 via this expert
parallelism techniques, which.
원문 의미: is having, let's say, 하나 expert on
a device, another 하나.
원문 의미: on another device.
원문 의미: 그래서 that's 하나 thing worth noting.
원문 의미: Another 하나, I will say, 그래서 a
tensor parallelism.
원문 의미: is when you have big 행렬
multiplications to somehow cut.
원문 의미: that in a way that decreases the
memory required for that.
원문 의미: 그리고 maybe the 지난 하나 I will say is
pipeline parallelism.
원문 의미: It's when you consider a forward
pass.
원문 의미: as involving several layers.
그래서 you're ~할 예정입니다 to say that 하나 GPU is
~할 예정입니다 to only.
be responsible for, let's say, layers 1 to
3 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: another 하나 layer 3—
sorry, 4 to 5, 4, 5, 6, 그리고 그래서 on 그리고 그래서
forth.
원문 의미: 그래서 you also have that kind of
parallelism.
원문 의미: 하지만 anyways, there's a bunch of
techniques.
원문 의미: 그리고 the ones that I mentioned they.
원문 의미: fall in the bucket of 모델
parallelism.
원문 의미: 만들다 sense?
No 필요하다 to 알다 the details on there.
원문 의미: 하지만 I 생각하다 그냥 knowing that there
are several methods.
그리고 그냥 a rough 아이디어, I 생각하다, is a good
thing to have in mind.
좋습니다.
그래서 what did we do?
원문 의미: 그래서 we realized that during the 학습
process,.
원문 의미: we had to save a lot of things in
memory.
원문 의미: 그래서 what we saw was techniques
that.
원문 의미: reduce the burden of having memory
per GPU,.
원문 의미: 그래서 we are trying to distribute
that across GPU들.
그래서 we saw 데이터 parallelism 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: the ZeRO method that has some extra
optimizations.
그리고 we saw 모델 parallelism as well.
그래서 이제, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 another
technique that leverages.
원문 의미: the structure of the GPU.
원문 의미: 그리고 you may have heard of this
technique.
원문 의미: It's called flash attention.
It was 실제로 developed here at Stanford in
2022.
원문 의미: 그리고 in order for me to talk to you
about this technique,.
원문 의미: I 원하다 to tell you more about what
the GPU is composed of.
원문 의미: 그래서 if you 보다 under the hood—
원문 의미: well, GPU is 매우 complicated 그리고 I'm
for sure not—
원문 의미: I don't 알다 everything either.
하지만 what I 알다 is that we have 둘 kinds of
memories in GPU.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 하나 kind of memory
that's big 하지만 relatively slow.
그것은 in the HBM.입니다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 another kind of memory that
is fast 하지만 much,.
원문 의미: much smaller, which is on chip 다음
to where.
원문 의미: the 컴퓨트 happens.
원문 의미: 그것은 called the SRAM.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have HBM 그리고 SRAM.
원문 의미: HBM has something around tens of
gigabytes.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's like the GPU memory that
you saw in the description.
원문 의미: SRAM is much smaller.
원문 의미: It's like something around several
tens of megabytes.
원문 의미: let's say.
그래서 it's much smaller, 하지만 그다음 it is 10
times faster.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나 is a few terabytes per
둘째 let's say.
원문 의미: 그리고 the SRAM is tens of terabytes
per 둘째.
그래서 it's a noticeable difference in speed.
그래서 what we 원하다 is to somehow leverage.
원문 의미: the strength of these kinds of
memories.
원문 의미: in order to speed up the attention.
원문 의미: computation in an exact way.
원문 의미: 그래서 what do I mean by exact way?
원문 의미: 그래서 what I mean is we're not making
any approximations.
원문 의미: to the computation.
What we're doing is we're 그냥 leveraging.
원문 의미: the strength of these components
그리고 sending the computation.
원문 의미: in a clever way.
원문 의미: 기억하신다면, the self-attention
computation.
원문 의미: is done with this 매우 중요한 formula.
그래서 it's softmax of queries 그리고 keys.
원문 의미: over some scaling factor times V.
원문 의미: 그래서 this allows queries to interact
with everyone else.
그래서 in 행렬 form, you can 생각하다 of queries.
원문 의미: as having the 번호 of rows equal to
the 시퀀스 length.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 columns to being the 차원 of
the query.
그리고 그다음 같은 for key 그리고 value.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have this big 행렬
multiplications.
그래서 if you do it—
원문 의미: if you do this computation, the
standards.
원문 의미: the vanilla way, what you would do.
원문 의미: is store them in the big 하지만 slow
memory.
원문 의미: component of the GPU.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would store it in the HBM.
원문 의미: 그래서 here is what you would do if
you were.
원문 의미: to not do any optimization.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would 가지다 those 행렬들 from
the big 하지만 slow HBM,.
원문 의미: perform the computation, 그리고 그다음
write it back to the HBM.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you would read that 결과
again from the HBM,.
원문 의미: 컴퓨트 the softmax, 그리고 그다음 write it
back to the HBM.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you would again load this
plus the value 행렬,.
원문 의미: multiply them, 그리고 그다음 write them
to the HBM.
원문 의미: 보다, there's a lot read 그리고 write to
the HBM.
그래서 it's a lot of 데이터 transfer, which 실제로.
원문 의미: becomes the bottleneck.
그래서 a GPU is 매우, 매우 fast, 하지만 그다음 you
spend a lot of time.
원문 의미: 그냥 loading your 행렬들 from the
memory.
원문 의미: The reason why you do that is 왜냐하면
of this softmax.
원문 의미: operation.
원문 의미: 그래서 do you 기억하다 what a softmax
does?
원문 의미: 그래서 it normalizes the quantities,
그래서 that they sum to 1.
원문 의미: 하지만 it's row dependent meaning that
each row needs.
to sum up to 1.
원문 의미: 그래서 in a sense, you 필요하다 that
computation to happen 첫째.
원문 의미: 전에 you do your softmax.
If you 그냥 보다 at it like that,.
원문 의미: you would 생각하다, yeah, you 필요하다 to
do the whole thing 첫째.
원문 의미: Well, it turns out that you don't.
필요하다 to do everything at once.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 the core 아이디어 behind flash
attention.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 what flash attention does is
it.
원문 의미: tries to minimize the amount of
read.
원문 의미: 그리고 write from 그리고 to the HBM 그리고
instead takes small blocks—
원문 의미: 그리고 it's called tiling, the method
is called tiling.
원문 의미: It takes small blocks that it sends
to the SRAM,.
원문 의미: 그래서 that it gets computed from end.
원문 의미: to end 전에 being sent back to the
HBM.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: 아이디어는 let's send small 행렬들 into the
SRAM,입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 that it does the whole full
end-to-end computation.
원문 의미: 그리고 그냥 send it back to the HBM,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 we 원하다 to minimize the amount
read.
원문 의미: 그리고 write from the HBM.
원문 의미: 그래서 here is how you would do it.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 기억하다, the softmax
computation.
원문 의미: with the query 그리고 the key 그리고 그다음
the value.
원문 의미: Well, what you would do is to cut
your 행렬들.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 proceed step by step.
하지만 그다음 there's a cool trick that I.
원문 의미: 원하다 to talk to you about, which is.
원문 의미: that you don't 필요하다 to 컴퓨트 the
whole 행렬.
원문 의미: inside a softmax in order to
achieve the whole softmax.
원문 의미: computation.
왜냐하면 if you 생각하다 about it, let's suppose.
원문 의미: you have a whole 행렬, 그리고 그다음 you
have 다른,.
원문 의미: let's say, columns or submatrices,
S1 to SN,.
원문 의미: well, softmax of this huge 행렬.
원문 의미: is equal to this 행렬, where the
softmax is taken.
원문 의미: with respect to each of these
submatrices.
원문 의미: up to some scaling factor.
원문 의미: 이것은 the core trick.입니다.
그리고 if you 원하다 to be convinced of it,.
원문 의미: 그냥 보다 at the softmax formula,.
원문 의미: it's exponential of something over
some quantity, which.
원문 의미: is shared across the row.
원문 의미: 그래서 this scaling factor will 그냥 fix
this with respect to that.
원문 의미: 그래서 with this in mind, what we will
do.
원문 의미: is 가지다 each respective slices of
this 행렬들,.
원문 의미: do the whole computation, 그리고 그다음
populate.
원문 의미: the corresponding entry in the
output 행렬.
원문 의미: 그래서 we will do that between, let's
say,.
원문 의미: the 첫째 slice of the query 그리고 the
첫째 slice.
원문 의미: of the keys 그리고 the values.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 we will repeat for the
other slice until the end.
other queries.
원문 의미: as well until the end.
원문 의미: 그래서 what the paper explains is how
this scaling factor.
원문 의미: is being computed.
원문 의미: 그래서 this 하나 is some formula that I
did not put on the 슬라이드,.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's not necessary for you to
memorize the formula.
It's 그냥 the 아이디어.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 아이디어 is exactly this trick.
원문 의미: 그래서 once you do that, you 기본적으로 end
up.
원문 의미: with only 하나 read from the HPM.
원문 의미: 그리고 these [INAUDIBLE] quantities
are stored in the SRAM.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 they're read from the SRAM,
which.
is 매우 fast, 그리고 그다음 computed, 그리고 그다음 back
to the SRAM.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 at the end, in order to
accumulate the results,.
원문 의미: they're being sent back to the HBM.
그래서 그냥 to 만들다 sure we're clear.
그래서 in green, it's 기본적으로 when it's read
from SRAM,.
그리고 그다음 in blue, it's from the HBM.
원문 의미: You have a 문제?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: [AUDIO OUT].
The 문제 is, do you 가지다 the whole row or a
portion of it?
그래서 you can 가지다 a portion of it.
원문 의미: 하지만 그냥 for illustrative purposes,.
원문 의미: here we 가지다 the exclusive.
원문 의미: 이것은 그냥 for illustrative
purposes.입니다.
원문 의미: You can 생각하다 of your 행렬 as being
completely a grid.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you 그냥 multiply
accordingly.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, this is 그냥 for
illustrative purposes.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, are you computing
alpha.
원문 의미: 그리고 all these quantities on the
fly.
원문 의미: or do you have some estimation?
그래서 all of this is exact, 그리고 they're.
원문 의미: computed in an iterative basis.
원문 의미: 그래서 the way it works is when you
populate the output,.
원문 의미: you will keep on having some extra
quantity that.
원문 의미: will adjust for that.
생각하다 of it as 그냥 some formula that works.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, I highly recommend
looking at the paper.
원문 의미: They 실제로 explicit that quite a lot.
원문 의미: 그래서 the paper is Flash Attention,
fast.
원문 의미: 그리고 memory efficient exact
attention with IO awareness.
원문 의미: All of the links are in the 슬라이드.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, I highly recommend 그냥.
원문 의미: looking at the exact formula in 경우
you 원하다 to be convinced.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 하지만 the 아이디어 makes sense overall?
원문 의미: Any 문제들 on this?
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Well, this was flash attention, 하지만
there's 실제로.
원문 의미: another 아이디어 from the paper.
원문 의미: 그래서 this was only the 첫째 아이디어,
which.
원문 의미: was around making the attention
computation faster.
원문 의미: The 둘째 아이디어 is given that the
attention computation is.
원문 의미: faster, 이제 let's try to be smarter.
원문 의미: about the backwards pass, 왜냐하면 when
you 컴퓨트.
원문 의미: in the backwards pass, when you
컴퓨트.
원문 의미: the gradient of the loss with
respect to a 파라미터,.
원문 의미: the chain rule will surface some
activations that you.
필요하다 to have in memory.
원문 의미: Well, here, given that computing
these activations is 매우 fast,.
하나 아이디어 is to 그냥 not store activations.
원문 의미: from the forward pass or at least
not store everything,.
원문 의미: 하지만 instead in the backwards pass,.
원문 의미: 컴퓨트 these activations again.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's called the recomputation.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you do the forward pass,
you 컴퓨트 an activation.
to be able to 컴퓨트 the loss, 하지만 그다음.
원문 의미: instead of saving it to reuse it
during the gradient update,.
you will 그냥 discard it 그리고 그다음.
원문 의미: recompute the activation during the
backwards pass.
원문 의미: with this 매우 fast technique.
원문 의미: 그리고 when you do that, it's 실제로
quite remarkable.
원문 의미: 그래서 you do more operations.
그래서 gigaFLOPs is 그냥 a derivative of FLOPs.
그래서 it's the 번호 of operations you're
doing.
원문 의미: 그래서 with flash attention, you're
doing more operations.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 you're 실제로 recomputing things.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 그래서 you also 보다 fewer read
그리고 writes from the HBM.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, for instance, it was 40.3
in the standard way.
그리고 그다음 4 포인트— 그래서 it's like almost a 10x
reduction.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 you 보다 that the runtime is
also smaller.
이것은 매우 remarkable 왜냐하면 usually,입니다.
원문 의미: when you recompute things, you are
saving memory.
원문 의미: 하지만 at the expense of runtime.
원문 의미: You're 그냥 taking longer.
원문 의미: 하지만 here, you're not only taking
less amount of time,.
원문 의미: you're also saving memory.
원문 의미: 그래서 you're 기본적으로 having everything.
원문 의미: It's the best of all worlds.
원문 의미: 이것은 what flash attention
mentioned.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you will 보다 that there are some
other, I guess,.
원문 의미: variants of flash attention.
원문 의미: 그래서 flash attention 2, flash
attention 3.
원문 의미: 그리고 I would say that these are more
adaptation of these methods.
원문 의미: to the current infra, 왜냐하면 each new
GPU comes.
원문 의미: with new pros 그리고 cons, 그래서
strengths 그리고 weaknesses.
그리고 I guess there's always a way to 만들다.
원문 의미: these optimizations better.
원문 의미: 하지만 yeah, I would say flash
attention is.
quite a common trick, 그리고 I 생각하다 it's a 매우
good thing to.
원문 의미: 그래서 does that 만들다 sense?
좋습니다.
I'll 가지다 that as a yes.
OK.
좋습니다.
OK, 그래서 지난 thing—
원문 의미: no, we have a few things that I 원하다
to talk to you about.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have your LLM with a bunch
of 가중치.
원문 의미: These 가중치 are all floating points.
그래서 you can 생각하다 of them as 그냥 being.
원문 의미: numbers with a bunch of numbers 후에
the decimal.
원문 의미: 하나 natural 문제 you can ask yourself.
is, do you 정말 필요하다 to 알다 that much
precision.
후에 the decimal 포인트 to be able to do a good
job?
원문 의미: I guess put another way, can you
그냥.
원문 의미: cut your precision in some way to
save on memory.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 keep the 같은 performance?
원문 의미: 이것은 the 아이디어 behind
quantization.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 quantization is the process of
converting.
원문 의미: the precision of a 번호 from, let's
say,.
원문 의미: 하나 setting to another.
원문 의미: In order to better understand
that,.
I 생각하다 it's 중요한 to 알다 how floating points—
원문 의미: sorry, floating 포인트 numbers, how
they are encoded.
그래서 in practice, they're 그냥 a bunch of
bits.
원문 의미: 그리고 here, you have some bits that
are responsible for,.
원문 의미: let's say, the exponent, some that.
원문 의미: are responsible for the mantissa,
which is 기본적으로.
원문 의미: how granular your 번호 is.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 하나 that is about the sign.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a bunch of
representations of floats.
원문 의미: 그래서 the most common ones are in
this table.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have 그래서 single 포인트
precision, half precision,.
원문 의미: floating 포인트 64, brain float 16.
원문 의미: that are each having 다른
granularities for the 셋.
차원들.
그래서 if we 가지다 the 첫째 둘 rows, which.
원문 의미: are the 둘 most common
representations that you will.
원문 의미: 보다 out there, floating 포인트 16 is
only represented on 16 bits.
compared to 32.
원문 의미: 그래서 it takes 기본적으로 half the memory.
if you 원하다 to 생각하다 about it this way.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 it's less precise, meaning
it's less granular.
그래서 I guess 하나 아이디어 that we could.
원문 의미: have is to somehow decrease the
granularity of these 가중치.
원문 의미: 그리고 these numbers, hoping that it
will not impact performance.
원문 의미: too much.
원문 의미: 그래서 another thing that I 원하다 to
mention.
원문 의미: is back to that GPU description.
원문 의미: You 보다 that there is also a bunch
of information.
원문 의미: around the 컴퓨트 speed.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if you can 보다 매우
well on there.
원문 의미: Can you 보다 매우 well on the 슬라이드?
그래서 I'll read it.
원문 의미: The 컴퓨트 speed as a function of
which representation.
원문 의미: you're using.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, if you're using FP64,
which.
원문 의미: is this super granular way of
representing numbers,.
원문 의미: you only have 34 teraFLOPs of 컴퓨트
speed.
하지만 그다음 if you're using a, let's say,.
원문 의미: FP32, which is half of it, you can
double your 컴퓨트 speed.
그리고 그래서 on.
원문 의미: You have all these other numbers as
well.
원문 의미: 아이디어는 you can save on memory.입니다.
원문 의미: You can also go faster.
그래서 with this in mind, I 그냥 원하다.
to touch on 하나 지난 technique 전에 giving it.
원문 의미: to Shervin, which is mixed
precision 학습.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 behind mixed precision
학습.
is to leverage 다른 granularities of float.
원문 의미: representations such that it will
not.
원문 의미: hurt the performance too much 하지만
allow you to save on memory.
원문 의미: 그리고 do things faster.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 아이디어 behind mixed precision
학습.
원문 의미: is you have your 모델들 or you have
your 모델, you.
원문 의미: keep your 가중치 in high precision,
그래서 FP32,.
원문 의미: 그리고 all the operations that you do.
원문 의미: in the forward 그리고 backward pass,.
you're ~할 예정입니다 to do it in a lower
precision.
그래서 in this 경우, FP16.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 the 가중치 updates will be
done still in FP32.
원문 의미: 그래서 the authors of the paper, when
they did that,.
원문 의미: 기본적으로 what they realized was the
performance.
원문 의미: was not degraded too much.
원문 의미: 하지만 그다음 you had a lot of savings on
memory.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 it was running faster.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제 you may wonder, well, why
are you keeping the 가중치.
원문 의미: at a high precision 하지만 not the
activations 그리고 그래서 on?
그래서 I can offer you 그냥 a bit of 직관.
원문 의미: 그래서 whenever you perform a forward
pass,.
you're performing that on a set of 데이터.
원문 의미: 하지만 that set of 데이터 can be noisy in
itself.
원문 의미: 그래서 maybe all the decimal points
후에—
원문 의미: 그래서 all the numbers 후에 the decimal
포인트.
원문 의미: may not be as useful.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can 생각하다 of this update as
being more in which direction.
원문 의미: should the 가중치 go to a more optimal
state.
원문 의미: 그래서 it doesn't require them to be
super precise,.
하지만 그다음 it's much more 중요한 to keep your
가중치,.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 가중치 of the 모델 in high
precision in order.
원문 의미: to not accumulate errors due to
quantization.
그것은 하나 way 그냥 생각하다 about it.입니다.
원문 의미: 하지만 the long story short is if you.
원문 의미: reduce the granularity of some
numbers,.
원문 의미: 그다음 you will have a lot of
benefits.
원문 의미: 그리고 not a lot of disadvantages in
terms of the performance.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그것은 a great 문제.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, do you apply this
technique.
to all 가중치 of all layers or 그냥 to some of
them?
원문 의미: 그래서 there has been a lot of papers
on that.
원문 의미: 그리고 the 답 is there are some
variations to it.
그리고 그래서 the 답 is not necessarily.
원문 의미: 그래서 I do have some pointers.
원문 의미: Happy to share them with you.
원문 의미: 하지만 some parts may be more 중요한 than
others.
원문 의미: 그래서 this strategy is a little bit a
high level 아이디어,.
원문 의미: 하지만 there are always some
variations from setup to setup.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 is your 문제 that people rely on
the relationship.
원문 의미: between 컴퓨트—
그리고 sorry, not 컴퓨트, 파라미터들 그리고 토큰.
원문 의미: from the Chinchilla paper, 하지만 it.
원문 의미: may be 다른 from their setup which.
원문 의미: may 소개하다 something— this is 기본적으로
your 문제?
그래서 the 문제 is, is there also.
an optimal precision to 사용하다?
원문 의미: 그래서 I would say, people 사용하다 다른
things.
원문 의미: There's not like a set way where
everyone does something.
원문 의미: 하지만 I would say that these scaling,
like this Chinchilla.
원문 의미: law, is 실제로 something that some
authors,.
원문 의미: they try to reproduce for their own
모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 실제로, for instance, the Llama 3
paper,.
원문 의미: there's a whole 부분 around trying.
원문 의미: to have some relationship between
given.
a fixed amount of 컴퓨트, what is the optimal
번호 of 토큰들.
그리고 그다음 a 번호 of 파라미터들 that is unique to
their setup.
원문 의미: 그래서 what people do is they do this
thing themselves.
on a small amount of 학습 set 그리고 on smaller
모델들,.
원문 의미: 그래서 that it doesn't cost them too
much.
원문 의미: They try to 보다 what the
relationship is for their setup,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 they extrapolate.
원문 의미: 그리고 I believe that's how Llama 3—
그래서 I 생각하다 there's a 모델 that—
그래서 Llama 3, 405 billion 파라미터들.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 they had the whole section
그냥 justifying.
원문 의미: that they came up to this 번호 with
some experiments.
원문 의미: that they run.
그래서 to your 문제, I 생각하다 it highly.
원문 의미: depends on the kind of 모델 that
someone is 학습.
원문 의미: 그리고 they'll probably have this
analysis,.
원문 의미: I guess, with respect to their own
setup.
원문 의미: Does that 답 your 문제?
좋습니다.
OK.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: The 문제 is, is there something.
원문 의미: you can do about the range?
원문 의미: 그래서 there are several types of
quantization.
원문 의미: We're not ~할 예정입니다 into details
here,.
원문 의미: 하지만 I can 주다 you a ZeRO 포인트
quantization 그리고 absmax.
원문 의미: quantization, which are 다른
techniques that.
원문 의미: play with these ranges.
원문 의미: There's also quantization
technique.
원문 의미: that Shervin will cover that also
talks about that.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, stay tuned for this.
하지만 I 생각하다 ZeRO 포인트 quantization 그리고
absmax are.
원문 의미: ones that maybe you can 보다 into for
this.
좋습니다.
그래서 with that, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to 주다 it to
Shervin.
원문 의미: Thank you, Afshin.
그래서 이제, we have seen how a 사전학습 worked.
우리는 보다 together the 다음 stages of 학습.할
것입니다.
그래서 as we saw with Afshin, 사전학습.
원문 의미: was a way to build the 직관 to the 모델
about how language.
원문 의미: was constructed 그리고 about the main
characteristics of what is.
contained in the 학습 데이터.
원문 의미: 그것은 general enough.입니다.
원문 의미: 이것은 why we had corpuses that spans
huge corpora of texts입니다.
원문 의미: that are typically of the size of
what.
원문 의미: you find on the internet.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, 매우 large 그리고 raw 그리고
conveying.
원문 의미: aspects of language.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제, you might 원하다 to ask
yourself,.
원문 의미: how can we 만들다 such knowledge 실제로
helpful?
이것은 something that we're going입니다.
to discuss 그냥 in a 둘째.
원문 의미: 하지만 전에 we discuss about what could
motivate further 학습,.
원문 의미: I 원하다 to come back to some 매우 간단한
예시 that will surface.
원문 의미: what could be such a 필요하다.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's 가지다 our favorite 예시 about
our teddy bear.
그리고 let's say, we have a 매우 practical 사용하다
경우.
원문 의미: 그래서 we have thoroughly loved our
teddy bear.
하지만 이제, it has become a bit dirty, 그래서 we
필요하다 to wash it.
원문 의미: 그리고 you might 원하다 to ask your
favorite LLM if you can put it.
원문 의미: in the washer.
원문 의미: 그래서 with the description that
Afshin mentioned.
of LLM 사전학습, I 원했습니다 to ask.
원문 의미: you all what was your opinion about
what.
원문 의미: could the output to this be.
원문 의미: 그래서 any guesses?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Excellent.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 답, the guess was maybe
another 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 that is a great guess
that could definitely be it.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, in the 예시, we put some
other sentence.
원문 의미: that could be likely, 하지만 the gist
is the 같은.
It has been 학습된 on 다음 토큰 예측,.
원문 의미: not being an assistant or someone
that is helpful to you.
이것은 why it will try to mimic입니다.
원문 의미: what could be the pattern here 그리고
what could.
원문 의미: be potential likely 다음 words.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, the 예시 we put here.
원문 의미: is something that relates to how
the teddy bear is composed of.
그리고 왜냐하면 it's in the 같은 domain as teddy
bear.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 when you talk about washer,
그다음.
원문 의미: maybe it has been 학습된 on 데이터 that
includes.
원문 의미: materials of teddy bears.
그래서 that could be it.
원문 의미: 그리고 I have a 문제 with you all.
원문 의미: Are you happy with it?
No.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Exactly.
이것은 why we're ~할 예정입니다 to see입니다.
원문 의미: what we can do with the 모델 to 만들다
it helpful to you.
원문 의미: 그리고 this stage is called 파인튜닝.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that it enables
us to,.
in the general 경우 of LLMs, 만들다.
원문 의미: the LLM a helpful assistance, 하지만
also,.
원문 의미: if you have a specific 사용하다 경우,
you.
원문 의미: can also 사용하다 this technique to
tune.
원문 의미: the general representation of the
language.
원문 의미: towards your task of interest.
하지만 we're ~할 예정입니다 to focus 첫째 on what.
원문 의미: is done for LLMs in general.
그래서 첫째, I 원하다 to 정의하다 some terms.
그래서 모델 파인튜닝 is commonly known as SFT.
원문 의미: SFT is short for supervised 파인튜닝.
원문 의미: 그래서 the supervised 부분 suggests that
we 필요하다 some labels.
그리고 it's 실제로 the 경우.
그래서 it's pairs of inputs 그리고 outputs.
that we provide the 모델 to be 학습된 on.
그리고 이것은 why it's called supervised.입니다.
그리고 그다음 파인튜닝 is the term that.
원문 의미: refers to refining the 가중치 that
have been already 학습된.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 시작하다 from the pre-학습된 가중치,.
그리고 you further 학습하다 the 모델 on additional
데이터.
원문 의미: to get a fine tuned 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 하나 interesting note that I
will tell you all.
원문 의미: is that the objective function,
even though it's the 같은,.
원문 의미: will differ a bit from the 사전학습
task.
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 사전학습 task, you 시작하다 with
the BOS 토큰,.
원문 의미: beginning of sentence, 그리고 you fit.
원문 의미: all your corpora of 데이터 trying to
predict the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: 하지만 here, since we have this
supervised 파인튜닝 setup,.
원문 의미: where you 원하다 the 모델 to do
something useful in cases.
원문 의미: of interest, 그래서 let's say, when I
ask the 모델.
원문 의미: about washing my teddy bear, 그래서
washing my teddy bear.
is 실제로 an input that I 주다 to the 모델.
It's fixed.
원문 의미: I don't 원하다 the 모델 to parrot what I
say.
I 원하다 the 모델 to be a helpful assistance.
to what I conditioned it on.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this setup, the input is not
a location.
원문 의미: where you would predict the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: You would not do teacher forcing on
it.
원문 의미: 하지만 rather 시작하다 from this input 그리고
그다음 predict.
원문 의미: the 다음 토큰 onwards.
그리고 그다음 you're ~할 예정입니다 to tune what.
the optimal 분포 of 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: can be based on this input.
그래서 any 문제들 on the overall 아이디어 of SFT.
전에 we dive in a bit deeper?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is we don't put a loss
over the input.
그것은 right.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 시작하다 from the input, 그리고
you 시작하다.
원문 의미: predicting the 다음 토큰.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the loss calculation starts
from there.
원문 의미: Everything good?
OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 what I was 그냥 telling you is.
원문 의미: that SFT can be done to tune your
own task of interest,.
원문 의미: 하지만 also, it's something that is
being.
원문 의미: done at 하나 of the main stages of 학습
LLMs.
원문 의미: as you 사용하다 it every day.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 this transition from the
모델.
원문 의미: being a good representation of
language to a useful assistance.
원문 의미: is a subcategory of SFT called
instruction tuning.
원문 의미: 그래서 instruction tuning comes from
the fact.
that we 원하다 the 모델 to 답 instructions.
그래서 이제, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to 보여주다 with the
graph what.
원문 의미: I was 그냥 mentioning regarding
predicting the 다음 word.
그래서 실제로, 그냥 in a bit.
첫째, we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 at the 데이터.
원문 의미: 그래서 with Afshin, we saw that the
composition.
of the 데이터 for 사전학습 was 기본적으로.
원문 의미: the whole internet where you had
sources that were carrying.
원문 의미: knowledge such as Wikipedia.
원문 의미: 그리고 in general, masses of text of
English.
원문 의미: that tells the 모델 about how English
그리고 other languages.
원문 의미: work, as well as coding.
그리고 here, it's slightly 다른.
For instruction tuning, we're ~할 예정입니다.
to 보다 at 데이터 that's presents to the 모델.
원문 의미: how it can most helpfully respond
to instructions.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can divide this in several
categories.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, we present some
원문 의미: that could be helpful to users of
LLMs.
원문 의미: For 예시, story writing.
원문 의미: You're interested in writing a
story.
You 주다 it a set of instructions,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 you have a ground truth
that is attached to it.
원문 의미: Other 예시들 include a poem creation,
list generation,.
원문 의미: explanation, 그리고 many more that are
부분.
원문 의미: of the 데이터 mixture of SFT.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, you run all these
supervised 파인튜닝 학습.
원문 의미: with the inputs that is given, 그리고
그다음 you 학습하다 the 모델.
원문 의미: on predicting the output.
그리고 I'm ~할 예정입니다 이제 to 보여주다 what it looks
like.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say your instruction is
here.
원문 의미: 그래서 you ask your 모델 to do
something.
그래서 it could be formulated in a 다른 way.
하지만 그냥 to keep it short, I 그냥 said, do X.
그리고 그다음 the yellow 부분 is where.
원문 의미: you 시작하다 fitting your objective
function on.
원문 의미: Does this 만들다 sense?
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 as I was mentioning, the 데이터
mixture.
원문 의미: includes instruction geared 데이터.
원문 의미: 그래서 for 예시, you had all of these
kinds of tasks.
원문 의미: that users might ask for at 추론
time.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's what I put under the
category assistant dialogues.
원문 의미: 그리고 these days, since you have all
these large 모델들 that.
원문 의미: already exist out there, 그리고 let's
say.
원문 의미: you 원하다 to generate a new 하나, you
don't necessarily.
원문 의미: have to 시작하다 from scratch.
원문 의미: 그래서 all of these that I mentioned
were originally human written.
원문 의미: 그래서 you had all these instructions.
원문 의미: that people gathered, 그리고 you had
expert linguists that.
원문 의미: had set of instructions on how to
write the best 답 that.
원문 의미: was fluent, helpful, 그리고
everything.
원문 의미: that was geared towards maximizing.
원문 의미: your happiness as a user.
원문 의미: 하지만 these days, you can 사용하다 these
already 학습된 LLMs.
원문 의미: to generate such 데이터.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, when you have a
large 모델 that.
원문 의미: is 매우 performant, you can feed it
such instructions, sample.
원문 의미: some generated outputs, 그리고 그다음
have a human or some other LLM.
원문 의미: 복습하다 the quality.
그래서 it's something that speeds up a bit.
원문 의미: the curation of such 데이터 sets.
그래서 I 그냥 원했습니다 to emphasize on the fact.
원문 의미: that it's not only human generated
these days,.
원문 의미: 하지만 you can have some assistance.
원문 의미: 그리고 besides all of the categories.
원문 의미: that you care about, 그래서 typically,
math.
원문 의미: or how you write a proof, how
things follow each other,.
원문 의미: or codes, high quality code bases,.
원문 의미: you also have other aspects that
are 매우 중요한 which.
원문 의미: when you release a product like
this to the wider population.
원문 의미: that come under the umbrella of
safety.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 원하다 your 모델 to be helpful
하지만 also harmless.
원문 의미: 그래서 you also have in the 데이터
mixture.
원문 의미: oftentimes a subset that enforces
the 모델's behavior.
원문 의미: not to repeat some of the harmful
content it.
원문 의미: might have seen on its 사전학습 말뭉치.
원문 의미: 그래서 it will include techniques
that.
원문 의미: might reject some user 프롬프트들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you might have tested on your
own the limits of an LLM 오늘.
원문 의미: If you submit queries that might
lead to something that is.
원문 의미: considered bad, it would 그냥 say,
OK, sorry,.
원문 의미: I cannot 답 this.
원문 의미: 그리고 this sorry, I cannot 답 could be
done via regex 하지만 매우.
원문 의미: rarely 왜냐하면 it's not scalable.
원문 의미: 그리고 people 실제로 embed this property
as 부분 of the 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have techniques that
rejects user queries that.
원문 의미: are seen as harmful.
원문 의미: Or there is some other phenomenon.
원문 의미: such as hedging that nuance the
output of the 모델.
원문 의미: in order to not 만들다 blanket
statement as well.
원문 의미: 그래서 you might have 데이터 sets that
includes such flavors.
원문 의미: 그리고 you can have many more
depending.
원문 의미: on the task of interest that you're
dealing with.
원문 의미: 하지만 what I'm listing here is what
usually the LLMs out there.
원문 의미: that aim at being general
assistance gather.
원문 의미: They tend to be like general tasks
that are being 학습된 on.
Any 문제들 on the 데이터?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is the story writing 예시.
원문 의미: doesn't precise what kind of
poetry.
원문 의미: the story should be about.
그래서 it might be ambiguous.
원문 의미: How can it generalize?
그래서 that is a great 포인트.
그래서 we rely on the 모델's knowledge.
원문 의미: that it has accumulated at 사전학습
time.
원문 의미: to be able to generalize beyond the
예시들.
원문 의미: that it has been fed.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say, 이제, you have a story
about poetry,.
원문 의미: 그리고 from 사전학습, it knows about all
kinds of poetry.
원문 의미: that exist out there.
원문 의미: 그래서 you could imagine, 후에 fitting
such an 예시 at.
원문 의미: supervised 파인튜닝 time, that you
could 주다 more details.
to this 프롬프트.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 모델 has the ability.
원문 의미: to generalize the generation of the
story with respect.
원문 의미: to those other attributes.
원문 의미: 그래서 you can have—
원문 의미: I 생각하다, the 예시 that you mentioned.
원문 의미: is a great 예시 of the magical
ability of LLMs.
원문 의미: to adapt to natural language.
원문 의미: 그리고 all of that has to do with the
kind of 분포.
원문 의미: it has seen in the past 그리고 what we
teach it.
그래서 I 생각하다 the 개념 itself of writing
stories.
원문 의미: is the key learning to the 모델 that
it can 그다음 generalize.
이해되나요?
원문 의미: Yeah.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: I 생각하다 there was another 문제 here.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is about the term of
alignment.
원문 의미: Is this post 학습 what is called as
being aligned?
원문 의미: 그래서 you are ahead of me.
In a few 슬라이드, we're ~할 예정입니다 to talk
about it.
원문 의미: Great 문제들.
원문 의미: Any other 문제?
원문 의미: Awesome.
그래서 그리고 그다음 그냥 like Afshin did it for the
사전학습 부분,.
저는 주다 some orders of magnitude.할 것입니다.
그래서 the 같은 GPT-3 그리고 Llama 3 papers.
원문 의미: that Afshin referred some numbers
from.
원문 의미: don't 실제로 주다 their statistics.
원문 의미: in terms of 토큰 numbers for the
instruction tuning side.
하지만 실제로 in 번호 of 예시들.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 보다 you have about 13 K used
GPT-3 그리고 10 million.
원문 의미: for Llama 3.
그리고 OK.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's do some quick estimation.
Let's say each 예시 is about 1,000 토큰들.
원문 의미: When you multiply that with the 번호
of 예시들,.
원문 의미: you 보다 that the size of the 데이터
sets used for SFT.
원문 의미: is several orders of magnitude
lower than the 하나 used.
원문 의미: for 사전학습.
원문 의미: 그래서 the mental 모델 that you 필요하다 to
have here.
is that 사전학습 is a lot of 데이터.
원문 의미: you 원하다 to 배우다 about general
characteristics, about language.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 SFT is more exactly what—
원문 의미: 그래서 someone was mentioning 그냥 이제.
원문 의미: regarding alignments— was aligning
the goal of the 모델.
원문 의미: to being suited for your tasks.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, 매우 high quality 데이터.
원문 의미: sets 그리고 much more concise 그리고
precise in terms of 번호.
원문 의미: 그래서 less order of magnitude.
OK.
좋습니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제, let's try this exercise
again.
원문 의미: What do you 생각하다 could be the 답 to
our instruction tuned.
이제 모델 to the 같은 문제?
원문 의미: Anyone wants to 가지다 a guess?
원문 의미: You 원하다 to try again.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 답 was yes.
원문 의미: You can put in the teddy bear in
the washer,.
원문 의미: except that you shouldn't put your
teddy bear in the washer.
원문 의미: You should handwash it.
원문 의미: 그래서 it will 주다 you the 답 that is
helpful to the user.
원문 의미: 그리고 indeed, this time respond to
the query.
원문 의미: 그래서 which is pretty nice.
원문 의미: 그래서 이제, we talked about all the
things.
원문 의미: that are great about supervised
파인튜닝.
이제, I'm ~할 예정입니다 to detail a bit more
about what.
원문 의미: could 만들다 it hard or challenging.
그리고 그다음 motivate the optimization 부분 that
we're.
~할 예정입니다 to 보다 afterwards.
그래서 첫째, we talked about it a bit.
원문 의미: When we have these 데이터 sets, these
데이터.
원문 의미: mixtures for SFT 학습, we 필요하다 high
quality 데이터.
원문 의미: 그리고 when you say high quality 데이터,.
원문 의미: means oftentimes human involved in
the loop,.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to 만들다 sure it abides with
all the rules 그리고 all.
원문 의미: the characteristics that the user
will care about.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, it's highly
involved.
그래서 originally, these 첫째 모델들,.
원문 의미: they were almost all human.
원문 의미: 하지만 이제, you might have some mixture
of human 그리고 generation.
원문 의미: 하지만 하나 good thing about these
things.
원문 의미: is that the 데이터 sets they are 학습된
on are reused.
원문 의미: 그래서 it's a work that you do once,
그리고 you can complement.
원문 의미: with respect to time.
하지만 it's still 매우 expensive in time 그리고
resources.
그래서 the 둘째 포인트 I 원하다 to mention comes back
to a 포인트.
원문 의미: that someone 그냥 made regarding the
분포 of your SFT.
원문 의미: 데이터 sets 그리고 how it would align
with actual 추론.
분포.
원문 의미: 그래서 in the 경우 of the story
regarding.
원문 의미: a specific kind of poetry, the 분포.
원문 의미: of 프롬프트들, that precise the kind of
poetry.
원문 의미: seems close enough for
generalization to be made.
원문 의미: 하지만 you could 생각하다 about 예시들 that
widely differ.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say you ask for a story
that is in some movie plots,.
원문 의미: 그리고 it differs from the stories
that you might 보다 in textbooks.
원문 의미: 그래서 this could be slightly out of
분포,.
원문 의미: 그리고 it could have trouble
generalizing to that.
그래서 프롬프트 분포 is 매우 중요한.
원문 의미: 그리고 aligning that 프롬프트 분포 with
respect.
원문 의미: to the target task is of interest.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: Great 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is about, let's say,.
원문 의미: you have SFT tuned your 모델, 그리고 이제,
you put a 학습.
원문 의미: input back to the 모델.
원문 의미: Will you get the 같은 story?
원문 의미: 그래서 it has to do with the
phenomenon.
원문 의미: that Afshin was mentioning
regarding memorization.
원문 의미: 그래서 in practice, you will not 보다
the 같은 story most likely.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 the 샘플링 that you're doing.
원문 의미: is with a non ZeRO temperature.
원문 의미: It will maybe have the 같은 flavor
하지만 not word for word.
원문 의미: 그다음 the flavor of that story, if
you.
원문 의미: have the exact 같은 프롬프트들, might be
the 같은.
원문 의미: It depends on what it has seen at
사전학습 time.
하지만 yeah, 그래서 the 답 is that if I.
had to 주다 a guess on that precise 예시,.
원문 의미: it might be the 같은 flavor 하지만
definitely not the 같은 wording.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 그리고 it might be a 다른 story.
원문 의미: if the 샘플링 goes through some other
region of the space.
원문 의미: Stories are highly creative 그리고
사전학습 corpora.
원문 의미: of 데이터 mixture had all kinds of
stories in there.
그래서 the specific 예시 of story is.
원문 의미: likely to generate 다른 outcomes.
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, will how much the 모델
wanders around.
원문 의미: depend on the temperature 파라미터?
원문 의미: 그리고 yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, when you have a
higher temperature, you also—
원문 의미: 그래서 it's also called more creative.
원문 의미: 그리고 it's for that reason.
원문 의미: It might also generate things that.
원문 의미: are less likely in its output 분포
with respect.
원문 의미: to what it has learned.
그리고 이것은 exactly a 경우 of something that we
배우다.입니다.
그래서 the 답 is yes.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, is there any way to
tune that?
원문 의미: 그래서 when you tune the temperature,.
원문 의미: you exactly do that.
원문 의미: Or were you thinking about
something else?
원문 의미: Yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, is there something
else.
원문 의미: you could do to have variations in
the response?
그래서 for that, I have a 간단한 하지만 hard 해결책.
원문 의미: You will 필요하다 more 데이터 in that
category that.
원문 의미: will ground the 모델 into seeing what
kind of 분포.
원문 의미: we target with such queries.
원문 의미: 그리고 I 생각하다 that will be 하나 way for
the 모델.
원문 의미: to generalize more.
그래서 I 생각하다 it will be working on the 데이터
부분.
원문 의미: Was there another 문제?
원문 의미: All good.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
이것은 a 매우 relevant 문제입니다.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 it touches on the topic of
generalization.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah.
원문 의미: 그래서 데이터 mixture matters a lot.
원문 의미: 그리고 having points that are sparse
enough.
in the 분포 space to 주다.
원문 의미: the gist to the 모델 of what it needs
to 배우다,.
원문 의미: rather than repeating the 같은 story
again 그리고 again,.
원문 의미: will have a lot to do with
generalization powers.
그리고 그다음 this is something we are ~할 예정입니다
to 보다 in a 둘째,.
원문 의미: how do you evaluate such 모델들?
원문 의미: The feeling that you get as a user
on how helpful.
a 모델 tends to be subjective.
그래서 how can you put some 번호 on it is ~할
예정입니다.
원문 의미: to be a key topic of interest.
그리고 그다음 also 매우 soon, we're ~할 예정입니다.
원문 의미: to 보다 how to 만들다 the computations
not that expensive.
원문 의미: 그래서 Afshin talked about 학습
optimization techniques.
하지만 이제, when we're at the 파인튜닝 stage,.
maybe we can go 하나 step further 그리고 보다.
원문 의미: what simplification assumption we
could 만들다.
OK.
원문 의미: Awesome.
원문 의미: 이제, let's dive into 하나 of these
challenges,.
원문 의미: which was the evaluation 부분.
원문 의미: 그래서 people have decomposed what
they care about in categories.
그래서 I'm listing here some 차원들.
원문 의미: that are evaluated against 그리고
that.
원문 의미: gives some quantitative 번호.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have a general language
where.
원문 의미: this benchmark that is popular is
generally 하나 score.
원문 의미: that people reports.
원문 의미: It's a MMLU, which massive
multitask.
원문 의미: language understanding.
그래서 it has, I 생각하다, 50 or 그래서 tasks in
there.
원문 의미: where the 모델 is being evaluated
against,.
원문 의미: 그리고 you have some score that you
can compare with.
원문 의미: You have benchmarks on reasoning,.
원문 의미: on math reasoning, as well as code
generation.
원문 의미: 그래서 here, you have all sorts of
acronyms,.
원문 의미: 그리고 there is even way more.
원문 의미: 그래서 기본적으로, the setting up
benchmark.
원문 의미: has been 하나 area of research.
원문 의미: 그래서 you always 보다 more 그리고 more
benchmark.
원문 의미: coming in 왜냐하면 people tend to
optimize for those that exist.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there are some gaps that
might.
원문 의미: be filled by further ones.
원문 의미: 그리고 the GSM 8K stands for grad
school—
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, grad school math.
8K stands for the 번호 of 예시들.
Yeah, I 생각하다 그래서.
원문 의미: Or maybe G stands for something
else,.
하지만 it's high school topics 기본적으로.
원문 의미: 그리고 하나 매우 interesting pattern that
people.
원문 의미: have seen as these 모델들 came out.
원문 의미: 그리고 as they were evaluated against
these benchmarks.
원문 의미: is that sometimes for the 같은 kind
of 모델,.
원문 의미: you 보다 all of a sudden a spike in
numbers with respect.
원문 의미: to some of these benchmarks without
a clear explanation.
원문 의미: behind it.
원문 의미: 그리고 there is this paper that I
highly.
원문 의미: recommend taking a 보다, which
explores.
원문 의미: the phenomenon of 학습 on the test
task, not the test set.
원문 의미: The test task.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you have benchmarks
regarding math reasoning,.
원문 의미: let's say, it matters a lot if the
모델 has.
been 학습된 on a 데이터 that relates.
원문 의미: to that kind of reasoning versus
not.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 why when you type in those
kinds of benchmarks,입니다.
원문 의미: you will 보다 that there are sets of
so-called auxiliary 학습.
원문 의미: that can be used for the 모델 to be.
학습된 on the 같은 domain.
원문 의미: 그리고 in that way, it enables the
fact.
원문 의미: of comparing 모델들 with respect to
that specific capability.
원문 의미: 그래서 what the paper tries to convey
here.
원문 의미: is that if you 원하다 to compare 모델들
between each other,.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to compare the 학습 mixture
it has been 학습된 on.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 ensure parity in terms of
학습 on the test task.
원문 의미: 그래서 you 필요하다 to 만들다 sure that, for
예시, the 둘 have.
원문 의미: been 학습된 on the test task or not.
그리고 if it's 하나 그리고 the other not,.
원문 의미: 그다음 it might not be a good thing to
compare them.
원문 의미: It doesn't 주다 you the intrinsic
value of the 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 yeah, that's an interesting
phenomenon here.
질문 있나요?
OK.
좋습니다.
그래서 we can 이동하다 on.
원문 의미: 그래서 하나 thing that I was mentioning
here.
원문 의미: is that it's 매우 hard to get a sense
of how good.
원문 의미: a 모델 is, even with respect to
benchmark scores,.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 oftentimes what happens is
that as they come out,.
원문 의미: people design 데이터 on the 학습 site.
원문 의미: that resembles more what we try to
solve on the benchmark side.
원문 의미: 그래서 sometimes you end up with 모델들
that score great.
원문 의미: everywhere, 하지만 you as a user don't
necessarily.
보다 added value to it.
그리고 it's not the fault of 모델들.
원문 의미: It's not the fault of the
benchmarks.
It's 그냥 that it's 매우 hard to 주다 a 번호 that
conveys.
원문 의미: the value to you of the 모델.
원문 의미: 이것은 why people have come up with
other techniques입니다.
to put a 번호 on 모델 evaluation.
원문 의미: 그리고 you might have heard of
Chatbots Arena.
원문 의미: Have any folks heard of it here?
원문 의미: Yeah.
그래서 it's a 웹사이트 where 모델들 can be
submitted,.
원문 의미: 그리고 users come in, 그리고 they ask
their 문제들,.
원문 의미: 그리고 they're presented responses
from 둘 모델들.
원문 의미: 그리고 they're being asked to judge
which 하나 is better.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 with some pairwise
computations done on the 웹사이트.
원문 의미: side, they come up with some
ranking in the end that ranks.
원문 의미: 모델 with respect to, quote unquote,
"user preference.".
그래서 it's a 번호 that is being put.
원문 의미: on the vibes seen by the user.
그리고 is it all perfect?
실제로, no.
원문 의미: 그래서 it suffers from several issues
that are—
원문 의미: another set of issues that are hard
to deal with.
원문 의미: 그래서 among them, when you have a new
모델 that comes in,.
원문 의미: you have some noise at the
beginning with respect.
원문 의미: to which other 모델 it's being
compared against.
원문 의미: 그리고 these 첫째 few steps 실제로
influence quite a bit.
원문 의미: the actual ranking, which makes it
a brittle property.
그리고 there is a paper that 실제로.
원문 의미: shows that it's easily possible to
rig such a leaderboard.
원문 의미: 그래서 I'm not sure if there is any
evidence that it.
원문 의미: has been done in the past.
원문 의미: 하지만 you can 사용하다 any 모델, if you.
원문 의미: ask the 문제, who are you, it's.
그냥 ~할 예정입니다 to say who it is.
원문 의미: If you ask ChatGPT, who are you.
It's ~할 예정입니다 to say, hey, I'm ChatGPT,.
원문 의미: I'm a helpful assistant.
원문 의미: 그리고 this paper observed on this 매우
간단한 property.
원문 의미: that it was able to detect what 모델.
원문 의미: was being evaluated against.
원문 의미: 그리고 let's say, you have an
adversarial player,.
원문 의미: it could rig the ranking 그냥 by
selecting the right 모델.
그래서 it's not foolproof.
그리고 그다음 on other aspects, 그래서 some.
원문 의미: of the benchmarks that evaluate
these 모델들,.
원문 의미: they're 실제로 curated by experts.
원문 의미: that 알다 매우 well about the target 분포
of what.
a given 프롬프트 should 주다.
원문 의미: 그래서 it has a set of guidelines that
says clearly, OK, this.
원문 의미: is factual.
원문 의미: 이것은 non-factual.입니다.
원문 의미: 그래서 they're able to determine what
is good versus bad.
원문 의미: 그리고 you as a user, you might not 알다
about it.
원문 의미: 왜냐하면 let's 그냥 가지다 the 예시 of the
teddy bear.
원문 의미: that you 원했습니다 to put in the
washer,.
if I don't 알다 that I 필요하다 to hand wash my
teddy bear,.
원문 의미: 그리고 if I have a detailed response
regarding.
원문 의미: you 필요하다 to wash it with a machine
wash cold,.
원문 의미: 그리고 I could, as a user, find these
pieces of advice.
원문 의미: helpful 왜냐하면 they are actionable to
me.
원문 의미: 하지만 실제로, are they factual?
원문 의미: 그것은 a whole other set of issues
that you as a user입니다.
원문 의미: wouldn't be able to tell on a lot
of queries.
원문 의미: 그리고 another challenge that we have
here is a user preference.
원문 의미: 그래서 who here likes it when there
are emojis in LLM responses?
원문 의미: Yes?
No?
원문 의미: Yeah.
Personally, I do.
원문 의미: 그리고 I 생각하다 there are strong
opinions.
원문 의미: 그리고 some people don't like it at
all.
원문 의미: 그래서 they will down rank such
responses.
원문 의미: 하지만 실제로, it's something that the
user should.
원문 의미: be able to tell 그리고 choose.
그리고 그다음 the 분포 of people.
원문 의미: who choose the best 모델 with
respect.
원문 의미: to the 분포 of the wider population
that.
is ~할 예정입니다 to 사용하다 these 모델들 is ~할 예정입니다.
to be 다른 oftentimes.
그리고 I 생각하다 the emoji 경우 is a good 예시,.
왜냐하면 I 생각하다 generally, emojis.
원문 의미: are popular in the wider
population.
원문 의미: 하지만 I 생각하다 domain experts might not
like it as much.
원문 의미: 그래서 I 생각하다 that mismatch is 하나 that
you would 보다 here.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the 지난 하나 I will mention
here is the safety side.
그래서 you as a user, you don't 정말.
원문 의미: like it when a 모델 rejects your
프롬프트들.
원문 의미: When you ask about something, 그리고
it says, OK, hey, sorry,.
I cannot 답 it.
원문 의미: 그래서 there will be a bias towards
responses that 실제로 respond.
원문 의미: to your query, rather than respect
some safety principle.
원문 의미: that might be eventually the
intended product decision.
원문 의미: 그래서 there is also this kind of bias
that pops up here.
그리고 as I was mentioning, evaluation is a
hard 문제.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have all these angles that
you can explore.
그리고 it's not 하나 번호 that's ~할 예정입니다 to tell
you.
원문 의미: what you care about.
원문 의미: It's the combination of all of
these.
그리고 in the end, it's tailored to what you
실제로 필요하다.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would 필요하다 to 보다 the
strengths 그리고 weaknesses.
of a given 모델 그리고 to determine which 하나
corresponds.
to your 사용하다 경우.
그래서 I'm ~할 예정입니다 to come back to 하나 문제
about alignment here.
그래서 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 at the 다음 강의 a
further step.
원문 의미: into aligning the 모델 to do what.
원문 의미: you 원하다 to do in a step called
preference tuning.
그리고 그다음 the combination of 파인튜닝 그리고
preference tuning,.
원문 의미: which comes 후에 사전학습, is what.
원문 의미: we call alignment of the 모델.
원문 의미: 그래서 these 둘 steps are called
alignments.
그리고 I 원하다 to call out 하나 other thing.
원문 의미: There is 하나 step we didn't mention
here.
원문 의미: 그것은 called mid 학습 that has been
emerging입니다.
원문 의미: 매우 recently, which consists in a
step.
그냥 후에 사전학습 in aligning the kind of 데이터.
원문 의미: that the 모델 is being 학습된 on to the
tasks.
원문 의미: that you 정말 care about.
그래서 it's the 같은 사전학습 objective.
원문 의미: 하지만 aligning the kind of tasks 그리고
the kind of 데이터 sets.
원문 의미: to something that you care about.
그리고 yeah, 그래서 it's an emerging trend.
원문 의미: I have not mentioned it, 하지만 그냥 그래서
that you 알다,.
원문 의미: mid 학습 is something that you.
원문 의미: would have between 사전학습 그리고 파인튜닝.
원문 의미: All good?
OK.
좋습니다.
그래서 이제, we're ~할 예정입니다 to tackle 하나 aspect
of the challenges.
원문 의미: that we had mentioned regarding
파인튜닝, which.
원문 의미: is computational expense—
원문 의미: the fact of being computationally
expensive.
그리고 we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 at it with 하나
well-known technique.
원문 의미: called LoRA, which is a technique.
원문 의미: to fine tune your 가중치 at the 파인튜닝
stage.
원문 의미: in an efficient manner.
그래서 it's widely used.
그리고 it saves a lot of 컴퓨트.
그래서 when you 보다 at your 가중치 행렬들,.
원문 의미: instead of directly 파인튜닝 the whole
가중치 행렬,.
원문 의미: the LoRA technique decomposes the
파인튜닝.
원문 의미: between the 가중치 of the pre-학습된 모델.
원문 의미: 그리고 additional 가중치 that it
decomposes into a low rank.
원문 의미: multiplication.
원문 의미: 그래서 in this formulation, the pre-
학습된 가중치.
원문 의미: that you have is frozen.
그래서 this W0 is frozen.
그리고 그다음 B 그리고 A are the 행렬들 that you 필요하다
to tune.
그래서 B 그리고 A are typically—
원문 의미: 그래서 they have 차원들 that will match
the 번호 of rows.
그리고 번호 of columns respectively.
for the 번호 of rows of B 그리고 번호 of columns
of A.
하지만 그다음 the 차원 of the columns of B 그리고 그다음
rows of A.
원문 의미: is R, which is the rank of these
행렬들, which is typically.
원문 의미: taken 매우 small.
그래서 the 차원들 of W is typically hundreds or
thousands,.
그리고 the 차원 of R is typically up to 10 or O
of 10.
원문 의미: 그래서 as you can imagine, it results
in much less 가중치.
to 학습하다.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 I will mention 그냥 other
techniques.
원문 의미: to improve efficiency 그리고 그다음 ease
the 파인튜닝,.
원문 의미: some methods called a prefix tuning
그리고 adapters.
원문 의미: 그래서 they're explained in the 수업
textbook.
하지만 we're not ~할 예정입니다 to dive deep into
them 왜냐하면 they're.
원문 의미: less commonly used.
하지만 그냥 그래서 that you 알다.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's walk through in detail
how does LoRA work.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you 원하다 to fine tune your
모델,.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have all these ways for
which.
원문 의미: you have already learned a 분포.
at 사전학습 time.
그래서 하나 naive way of operating 파인튜닝.
원문 의미: would be to directly iterate on
these 가중치.
하지만 what we're doing here, as we said,.
원문 의미: is to decompose these into the 가중치
that we have already.
pre-학습된 on 그리고 this product of 행렬들.
원문 의미: 그리고 what LoRA says is that you can
do a forward pass.
원문 의미: on both these terms 그리고 그다음 adds.
원문 의미: these quantities in the end.
그리고 A 그리고 B is ~할 예정입니다 to be a
characterization.
원문 의미: of your task of interest.
원문 의미: 그래서 let's say you have a 모델 that—
원문 의미: 그래서 Afshin was mentioning the kinds
of tasks.
원문 의미: that you can maybe specialize your
모델 on, for 예시,.
원문 의미: spam detection.
원문 의미: 그래서 you would 가지다 your pre-학습된 모델,.
instantiate this B 그리고 A in 가중치,.
원문 의미: in the 가중치 of your 모델, fine tune on
them.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 what you will have is that
B 그리고 A.
원문 의미: are ~할 예정입니다 to be specific to this
task of spam detection,.
원문 의미: similarly for sentiment extraction
그리고 그래서 on.
그래서 it's a 매우 nice property that you.
원문 의미: can 시작하다 from a base 모델, further
tune your 가중치,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 have your A's 그리고 B's that
are task specific.
그래서 I 원하다 to comment 이제 on where were.
원문 의미: these 행렬들 being learned.
원문 의미: 그래서 in the original paper of LoRA,.
원문 의미: it mentioned 학습 only on the
attention 행렬들.
원문 의미: 하지만 later on, people realized that
it might not.
원문 의미: be the place where it has the most.
원문 의미: positive impact on performance.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 there is a blog that came
out a few 주 ago.
원문 의미: that studies this into detail, 그리고
그다음 they.
원문 의미: realized that the feed-forward
blocks are 실제로.
원문 의미: those where putting LoRA is most
beneficial.
원문 의미: 그래서 오늘, typically, both these
components carry LoRA 행렬들,.
원문 의미: 하지만 the bulk of the performance
improvements.
원문 의미: is 실제로 contained in the feed-
forward block.
그리고 그다음 I 원하다 to mention 둘 interesting
properties.
원문 의미: about LoRA.
원문 의미: 그래서 when you fine tune with LoRA
가중치,.
원문 의미: you 원하다 to 사용하다 a higher learning
rate.
원문 의미: 그래서 typically, 10 times more is the
guidance.
그리고 그다음 하나 interesting fact is that it.
원문 의미: doesn't perform as well when you
학습하다 it with larger batch size.
원문 의미: 그래서 I don't have a good theoretical
explanation.
원문 의미: to 주다 you for each of them.
원문 의미: It's more empirical observations
that have been emitted.
원문 의미: 하지만 to 주다 the main lines behind the
mindset shared.
원문 의미: from people who study this
phenomenon,.
원문 의미: the 첫째 하나 might be guided by the
rank of the LoRA 행렬들.
원문 의미: that might be small.
그리고 as a 결과, given the regions of space.
원문 의미: that it needs to explore, you 필요하다
a higher learning rate.
그리고 그다음 the 둘째 하나, the hypothesis.
원문 의미: here is that the 학습 dynamic of
products of 행렬들.
is 다른 than a full 행렬.
원문 의미: 그리고 이것은 where the increasing batch
size phenomenon occurs.입니다.
그래서 it's 기본적으로 the explanations,.
원문 의미: tentative explanations given there.
그래서 이제, we're ~할 예정입니다 to explore an
optimization of this.
원문 의미: 하지만 전에 I dive deep into that 부분,.
원문 의미: does anyone have any 문제들 on the
LoRA 부분?
원문 의미: Yep.
원문 의미: Great 포인트.
원문 의미: 그래서 the 문제 is, do you do grid
search on the rank?
원문 의미: 그래서 you could.
그래서 it's a design choice to rank R.
Typically,.
원문 의미: people would have done it 전에 you.
원문 의미: 그래서 you have an 아이디어 of what rank
could be well suited.
원문 의미: for your 사용하다 경우.
원문 의미: 그래서 you could definitely do grid
search,.
원문 의미: or you could 그냥 pick a popular
value.
I 생각하다 a 4 is used commonly.
원문 의미: You can 그냥 go with 하나 of them.
원문 의미: Yeah.
그리고 we are ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 that the
reduction in 번호.
원문 의미: of 파라미터들 is 그래서 huge already that
reducing even more.
원문 의미: maybe doesn't matter that much.
원문 의미: That initial reduction by orders of
magnitude goes a long way,.
그리고 that is 그냥 a hyperparameter tuning.
원문 의미: 그리고 you can 보다 a given rank in a
given.
원문 의미: setup as being a design choice.
그래서 we have 둘 minutes, 그리고 we're.
원문 의미: ~할 예정입니다 to quickly cover quantized
LoRA.
원문 의미: 그래서 the techniques that Afshin
mentioned.
그냥 이제 regarding quantizing 가중치.
원문 의미: 그리고 그래서 reducing the memory
footprint.
is something that we're ~할 예정입니다 to 보다 그냥
here.
그래서 when you 보다 at these 행렬들 W0 그리고 A 그리고
B,.
원문 의미: what people have done in this
paper.
is to quantize the 가중치 of W0 into a format
that is 매우 smart.
그리고 그다음 컴퓨트 그리고 iterate on these 행렬들.
원문 의미: that are being learned, A 그리고 B in
full precision, which.
is in that 경우 BF16.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the quantization of these
frozen 가중치.
원문 의미: is super smart.
원문 의미: It's in a format called NF4, which.
원문 의미: assumes that the 가중치 are
distributed normally.
원문 의미: 그리고 it splits the space into
quantiles rather than buckets.
원문 의미: of fixed size, which puts about the
같은 amount of 번호.
원문 의미: of values into each.
원문 의미: 그래서 it optimizes the bits that you
사용하다 for encoding.
원문 의미: 그리고 what it does is that it does a
double quantization process.
그래서 it quantizes the 가중치.
그리고 그다음 in a 둘째 step, it quantizes.
원문 의미: the quantization constants that we
didn't 보다 at length here.
원문 의미: 하지만 기본적으로, when you 원하다 to convert
your full 가중치 in.
원문 의미: 그리고 out of quantized states, you
have.
원문 의미: constants that are generated.
원문 의미: 그리고 they propose to quantize these
constants as well.
원문 의미: 그래서 this method generated minus 16X
VRAM savings,.
원문 의미: 그리고 그다음 the double quantization
methods gave some extra savings.
원문 의미: 하지만 not that much.
하지만 it's interesting to 알다.
그리고 그다음 we are exactly on time.
원문 의미: Thank you for your time.